<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<akn:LegalDocML xmlns:akn="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/akn-core/v1.0/" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/akn-core/v1.0/os/part2-specs/schemas/akomantoso30.xsd">
	<akn:Jurisdictions>
		<akn:Jurisdiction key="jur:nz" sameAs="http://example.org/jurisdiction#newzealand"/>
	</akn:Jurisdictions>
	<akn:LegalSources key="ls1">
		<akn:LegalSource key="NZBC.E2" sameAs="https://www.building.govt.nz/assets/Uploads/building-code-compliance/e-moisture/e2-external-moisture/asvm/e2-external-moisture-3rd-edition-amendment-8.pdf"/>
	</akn:LegalSources>
<documents documentNumber="E2" subtitle="For New Zealand Building Code Clause E2 External Moisture" title="Acceptable Solutions and Verification Methods">
	<metadata>
		<cover>
			<code>E2</code>
			<title>Acceptable Solutions and Verification Methods</title>
			<p>For New Zealand Building Code Clause E2 External Moisture</p>
		</cover>
		<commentary title="Status of Verification Methods and Acceptable Solutions">
			<p>Verification Methods and Acceptable Solutions are prepared by the Ministry of Business, Innovation and Employment in accordance with section 22 of the Building Act 2004. Verification Methods and Acceptable Solutions are for use in establishing compliance with the New Zealand Building Code.</p>
			<p>A person who complies with a Verification Method or Acceptable Solution will be treated as having complied with the provisions of the Building Code to which the Verification Method or Acceptable Solution relates. However, using a Verification Method or Acceptable Solution is only one method of complying with the Building Code. There may be alternative ways to comply.</p>
			<p>Users should make themselves familiar with the preface to the New Zealand Building Code Handbook, which describes the status of Verification Methods and Acceptable Solutions and explains alternative methods of achieving compliance.</p>
			<p>Defined words (italicised in the text) and classified uses are explained in Clauses A1 and A2 of the Building Code and in the Definitions at the start of this document.</p>
		</commentary>
		<Paragraph title="Document Status">
			<p>The most recent version of this document (Amendment 8), as detailed in the Document History, is approved by the Chief Executive of the Ministry of Business, Innovation and Employment. It is effective from 30 November 2018 and supersedes all previous versions of this document.</p>
			<p>The previous version of this document (Amendment 7) will cease to have effect on 31 March 2019.</p>
			<p>People using this document should check for amendments on a regular basis. The Ministry of Business, Innovation and Employment may amend any part of any Verification Method or Acceptable Solution at any time. Up-to-date versions of Verification Methods and Acceptable Solutions are available from www.building.govt.nz</p>
		</Paragraph>
		<table title="E2: Document History">
			<tr>
				<th>Date</th>
				<th>Alterations</th>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<td>First published</td>
				<td>July 1992</td>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<td>Second Edition</td>
				<td>28 February 1998</td>
				<td>Document revised - Second edition issued</td>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<td>Third Edition</td>
				<td>E2/VM1 effective from 1 July 2004</td>
				<td>E2/AS1 effective from 1 February 2005</td>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<td>Amendment 1</td>
				<td>E2/AS1 effective from 1 July 2005</td>
				<td>p. 2 Document Status September 2004</td>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<td>Reprinted incorporating Amendment 1</td>
				<td>September 2004</td>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<td>Amendment 2</td>
				<td>Effective from 1 July 2005</td>
				<td>p. 2 Document History, Document Status pp. 25-43, 45-47, 49, 50, 55-57, 59-67, pp. 5-7, 9, 10 Contents 69-89, 93-100, 102, 103, 105-107, pp. 13-16 References 111-119, 121-125, 127-135, 138, pp. 17-20 Definitions 140-144, 146, 147, 149, 150, pp. 21-24 E2/VM1 153-155, 157,163-169 E2/AS1 pp. 173, 174, 177, 178 Index</td>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<td>Erratum 1</td>
				<td>Effective from 1 December 2005</td>
				<td>p. 166 Table 23</td>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<td>Amendment 3</td>
				<td>21 June 2007</td>
				<td>pp. 3 and 4, Building Code Clause E2</td>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<td>Amendment 4</td>
				<td>Effective from 1 May 2008 until 31 January 2012</td>
				<td>p. 2 Document History, Document Status pp. 171-180 E2/AS2 pp. 8 and 12 Contents p. 181 Index pp. 13-14 References</td>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<td>Amendment 5</td>
				<td>1 August 2011</td>
				<td>p. 2 Document History, Document Status pp. 25-180 E2/AS1 pp. 5-12 Contents pp. 183-184,189-190 E2/AS2 pp. 13-16A References p. 191 E2/AS3 pp. 17-20 Definitions pp. 193-204 Index pp. 21-24 E2/VM1</td>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<td>Errata 2</td>
				<td>Effective from 24 December 2011 until 14 August 2014</td>
				<td>p. 2 Document History, Document Status pp. 29, 41, 43, 49, 55-57, 80, 81, p. 9 Contents 87, 91, 93, 94, 101, 106-108, 110-115, 117, 158, 160, 172, 176, 191 E2/AS1</td>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<td>Amendment 6</td>
				<td>Effective from 14 February 2014 until 30 May 2017</td>
				<td>p. 2A, Document History, Document Status p. 23, E2/VM1 1.5.1, 1.5.2, 1.5.3 p. 5, Contents pp. 36, 68, 172, 175, 175 E2/AS1 4.3.4, pp. 13,15,16A References 8.3.4.2, Tables 20, 21, 22 p. 17, Definitions</td>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<td>Amendment 7</td>
				<td>Effective 1 January 2017 until 31 March 2019</td>
				<td>p. 16A References</td>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<td>Amendment 8</td>
				<td>Effective 30 November 2018</td>
				<td>p. 5 Contents p. 21-23A E2/VM1 1.3, 1.3.1, 1.3.2, p. 14 References 1.3.2.1, 1.4.4.1, 1.4.5.1, 1.5, 1.6, 1.7</td>
			</tr>
			<notes>
				<note>Page numbers relate to the document at the time of Amendment and may not match page numbers in current document.</note>
			</notes>
		</table>
	</metadata>
	<definitions title="Definitions">
		<p>This is an abbreviated list of definitions for words or terms particularly relevant to these Verification Methods and Acceptable Solutions. The definitions for any other italicised words may be found in the New Zealand Building Code Handbook.</p>
		<term>
			<atom key="nz.nzbc.">Air seal</atom>
			<description>
				<p>A continuous seal fitted between a window or door reveal and the surrounding wall framing to prevent the flow of air into the interior of the building.</p>
			</description>
		</term>
		<term>
			<atom key="nz.nzbc.">Anti-ponding board</atom>
			<description>
				<p>A board laid under the lowest row of concrete and clay roof tiles and supports the roof underlay. The board is sloped to ensure moisture under the tiles is directed to the exterior of the roof.</p>
			</description>
		</term>
		<term>
			<atom key="nz.nzbc.">Apron flashing</atom>
			<description>
				<p>A near flat or sloping flashing with a vertical upstand, used at junctions between roofs and walls.</p>
			</description>
		</term>
		<term>
			<atom key="nz.nzbc.">Attached garage</atom>
			<description>
				<p>A garage that shares a common wall or walls with a habitable building, and is enclosed by roof and wall claddings that are continuous with the habitable part of the building.</p>
			</description>
		</term>
		<term>
			<atom key="nz.nzbc.">Base metal thickness (BMT)</atom>
			<description>
				<p>The thickness of the bare or base metal before any subsequent coating, such as galvanizing.</p>
			</description>
		</term>
		<term>
			<atom key="nz.nzbc.">Bird's beak</atom>
			<description>
				<p>A double fold applied to the edge of a horizontal metal flashing to stiffen the edge and to assist in deflecting moisture away from the cladding system below. Refer also Kick-out and Drip edge.</p>
			</description>
			<commentary title="COMMENT:">A bird's beak is used at the bottom of a capping to deflect water away from the enclosed balustrade cladding.</commentary>
		</term>
		<term>
			<atom key="nz.nzbc.">Butt flashing</atom>
			<description>
				<p>A preformed wall flashing, used to flash windows and corners on horizontal profiled metal wall cladding. A butt flashing is shaped to underflash the cladding, with the cladding butting against the exposed box portion of the flashing.</p>
			</description>
		</term>
		<term>
			<atom key="nz.nzbc.">Cantilevered deck</atom>
			<description>
				<p>A deck where no support is provided at the outer extremities of the deck.</p>
			</description>
			<commentary title="COMMENT: ">Cantilevered decks are often constructed by extending framing members through the cladding beyond the building face. Cantilevered decks are sometimes known as balconies.</commentary>
		</term>
		<term>
			<atom key="nz.nzbc.">Capping</atom>
			<description>
				<p>A flashing formed to cover the top of an enclosed balustrade or parapet. Also known as a coping.</p>
			</description>
		</term>
		<term>
			<atom key="nz.nzbc.">Cavity batten</atom>
			<description>
				<p>A vertical packing member used to create a drained cavity as part of a cladding system.</p>
			</description>
		</term>
		<term>
			<atom key="nz.nzbc.">Cavity wall</atom>
			<description>
				<p>A term used to describe a wall that incorporates a drained cavity.</p>
			</description>
		</term>
		<term>
			<atom key="nz.nzbc.">Cavity spacer</atom>
			<description>
				<p>A short block used to provide intermittent support for fixings or pipe penetrations through a drained cavity, while not interrupting drainage within the cavity. A cavity spacer is required to be set to a slight fall (5° minimum from horizontal) to allow drainage of any moisture from the top.</p>
			</description>
		</term>
		<term>
			<atom key="nz.nzbc.">Cladding</atom>
			<description>
				<p>The exterior weather-resistant surface of a building.</p>
			</description>
			<commentary title="COMMENT:">Includes any supporting substrate and, if applicable, surface treatment.</commentary>
		</term>
		<term>
			<atom key="nz.nzbc.">Cladding system</atom>
			<description>
				<p>The outside or exterior weather-resistant surface of a building; including roof cladding and roof underlays, wall cladding and wall underlays, and cavity components, rooflights, windows, doors and all penetrations, flashings, seals, joints and junctions. Where required by this Acceptable Solution, the cladding system shall include a drained cavity. </p>
			</description>
		</term>
		<term>
			<atom key="nz.nzbc.">Control joint</atom>
			<description>
				<p>A joint designed to prevent damage by accommodating movement. See also Expansion joint. </p>
			</description>
		</term>
		<term>
			<atom key="nz.nzbc.">Damp-proof course (DPC)</atom>
			<description>
				<p>A strip of durable vapour barrier placed between building elements to prevent the passage of moisture from one element to another. </p>
			</description>
		</term>
		<term>
			<atom key="nz.nzbc.">Damp-proof membrane (DPM)</atom>
			<description>
				<p>A sheet material, coating or vapour barrier, having a low water vapour transmission, and used to minimise water and water vapour penetration into buildings. Usually applied against concrete in contact with the ground. (Also known as a concrete underlay.) </p>
			</description>
		</term>
		<term>
			<atom key="nz.nzbc.">Deck</atom>
			<description>
				<p>An open platform projecting from an exterior wall of a building and supported by framing. A deck may be over enclosed internal spaces, or may be open underneath. Refer also Enclosed deck. Also known as a balcony. </p>
			</description>
		</term>
		<term>
			<atom key="nz.nzbc.">Direct fixed</atom>
			<description>
				<p>A term used to describe a wall cladding attached directly to the wall framing, without the use of a drained cavity. </p>
			</description>
		</term>
		<term>
			<atom key="nz.nzbc.">Dormer</atom>
			<description>
				<p>or dormer window A framed structure that projects from a sloping roof, and has a window at its outer end. </p>
			</description>
		</term>
		<term>
			<atom key="nz.nzbc.">Drained cavity</atom>
			<description>
				<p>A cavity space, immediately behind a wall cladding, that has vents at the base of the wall. Also known as a drained and vented cavity and referred to in this Acceptable Solution as a cavity or drained cavity. A drained cavity assists drying by allowing water which occasionally penetrates the wall cladding system to drain to the exterior of the building, and any remaining moisture to dry by evaporation. Where this Acceptable Solution requires a nominal 20 mm drained cavity, the depth shall be between limits of 18 mm and 25 mm. For definition of masonry veneer cavity refer to SNZ HB 4236. </p>
			</description>
		</term>
		<term>
			<atom key="nz.nzbc.">Drip edge</atom>
			<description>
				<p>Fold(s) applied to the edge of a horizontal metal flashing to deflect moisture away from the cladding system below.  Refer also Bird's beak and Kick-out. </p>
			</description>
		</term>
		<term>
			<atom key="nz.nzbc.">Dwang</atom>
			<description>
				<p>A short (usually horizontal) member fixed between framing timbers. Also known as nogging. </p>
			</description>
		</term>
		<term>
			<atom key="nz.nzbc.">Eaves</atom>
			<description>
				<p>That part of the roof construction, including cladding, fascia and eaves gutter (spouting), that extends beyond the exterior face of the wall. </p>
			</description>
		</term>
		<term>
			<atom key="nz.nzbc.">EIFS</atom>
			<description>
				<p>(Exterior Insulation and Finish System). A polystyrene sheet-based cladding system that uses mesh reinforced polymer-modified cement-based or polymer-based plaster base coats and a protective top coating. </p>
			</description>
		</term>
		<term>
			<atom key="nz.nzbc.">Electrolytic corrosion</atom>
			<description>
				<p>Galvanic corrosion commonly resulting from the contact of two dissimilar metals when an electrolyte such as water is present. </p>
			</description>
		</term>
		<term>
			<atom key="nz.nzbc.">Enclosed balustrade</atom>
			<description>
				<p>A timber-framed barrier with cladding across all exposed faces. Refer also Parapet. </p>
			</description>
		</term>
		<term>
			<atom key="nz.nzbc.">Enclosed deck</atom>
			<description>
				<p>A deck, whether over an interior or exterior space, that has an impermeable upper surface and is closed on the underside. May also be known as a balcony. </p>
			</description>
		</term>
		<term>
			<atom key="nz.nzbc.">Envelope complexity</atom>
			<description>
				<p>The categorisation of the complexity of the total building envelope into one of four classes, depending on the particular features of the building as specified in this Acceptable Solution. </p>
			</description>
		</term>
		<term>
			<atom key="nz.nzbc.">EPDM</atom>
			<description>
				<p>(Ethylene Propylene Diene Monomer) A thermosetting synthetic rubber used as a resilient part of a sealing washer, or as a roof membrane. </p>
			</description>
		</term>
		<term>
			<atom key="nz.nzbc.">Expansion joint</atom>
			<description>
				<p>A joint designed to prevent damage by accommodating movement. See also Control joint. </p>
			</description>
		</term>
		<term>
			<atom key="nz.nzbc.">External wall</atom>
			<description>
				<p>Any vertical exterior face of a building consisting of primary and/or secondary elements intended to provide protection against the outdoor environment. </p>
			</description>
		</term>
		<term>
			<atom key="nz.nzbc.">Finished ground level</atom>
			<description>
				<p>(FGL) The level of the ground against any part of a building after all backfilling and/or landscaping and/or surface paving has been completed. </p>
			</description>
		</term>
		<term>
			<atom key="nz.nzbc.">Flashing</atom>
			<description>
				<p>A component, formed from a rigid or flexible waterproof material, that drains or deflects water back outside the cladding system. </p>
			</description>
		</term>
		<term>
			<atom key="nz.nzbc.">Flexible flashing tape</atom>
			<description>
				<p>A flexible self-adhesive waterproof tape. Usually used as an accessory for wall underlays, to seal corners and intersections. </p>
			</description>
		</term>
		<term>
			<atom key="nz.nzbc.">Flush-finished</atom>
			<description>
				<p>The description of a cladding and joints system which relies on a protective coating applied to the face of the cladding to prevent the penetration of water. </p>
			</description>
		</term>
		<term>
			<atom key="nz.nzbc.">Framing</atom>
			<description>
				<p>Timber members to which lining, cladding, flooring, or decking is attached; or which are depended upon for supporting the structure, or for resisting forces applied to it. </p>
			</description>
		</term>
		<term>
			<atom key="nz.nzbc.">Hem</atom>
			<description>
				<p>A flat fold, not completely closed, applied to the edge of a metal flashing. </p>
			</description>
		</term>
		<term>
			<atom key="nz.nzbc.">Hidden gutter</atom>
			<description>
				<p>A gutter located within the boundaries of the roof framing. Hidden gutters may also be known as secret gutters or internal gutters. See also Valley gutters. </p>
			</description>
			<commentary title="COMMENT:">Hidden gutters are distinct from gutters or spouting that are externally located beyond the bounds of the roof and wall framing. </commentary>
		</term>
		<term>
			<atom key="nz.nzbc.">Hook</atom>
			<description>
				<p>An open fold applied to the edge of a metal flashing.</p>
			</description>
			<commentary title="COMMENT:">A hook is distinct from a hem, as it is open at an acute angle rather than flattened.</commentary>
		</term>
		<term>
			<atom key="nz.nzbc.">Kick-out</atom>
			<description>
				<p>A single fold applied to the edge of a horizontal metal flashing to deflect moisture away from the cladding system below. Refer also Bird's beak.</p>
			</description>
			<commentary title="COMMENT:">A kick-out is used at the bottom of a capping or other flashing to deflect water away from the cladding below.</commentary>
		</term>
		<term>
			<atom key="nz.nzbc.">Lining</atom>
			<description>
				<p>The rigid sheet covering for a wall, ceiling or other interior surface.</p>
			</description>
		</term>
		<term>
			<atom key="nz.nzbc.">Masonry tiles</atom>
			<description>
				<p>Clay or concrete tile roof cladding.</p>
			</description>
		</term>
		<term>
			<atom key="nz.nzbc.">Masonry veneer</atom>
			<description>
				<p>Clay or concrete block veneer cladding.</p>
			</description>
		</term>
		<term>
			<atom key="nz.nzbc.">Membrane</atom>
			<description>
				<p>A non-metallic material, usually synthetic, used as a fully supported roof cladding, deck surface or, in conjunction with other claddings, as gutters or flashings.</p>
			</description>
		</term>
		<term>
			<atom key="nz.nzbc.">NZBC</atom>
			<description>
				<p>New Zealand Building Code.</p>
			</description>
		</term>
		<term>
			<atom key="nz.nzbc.">Parallel flashing</atom>
			<description>
				<p>A roof flashing that runs along the roof slope, parallel to the roof cladding profile. Also known as a longitudinal flashing.</p>
			</description>
		</term>
		<term>
			<atom key="nz.nzbc.">Parapet</atom>
			<description>
				<p>A timber-framed wall that extends above the level of the roof cladding. Refer also Enclosed balustrade.</p>
			</description>
		</term>
		<term>
			<atom key="nz.nzbc.">Purlin</atom>
			<description>
				<p>A horizontal member laid to span across rafters or trusses, and to which the roof cladding is attached.</p>
			</description>
		</term>
		<term>
			<atom key="nz.nzbc.">Rafter</atom>
			<description>
				<p>A framing timber, normally parallel to the slope of the roof, providing support for sarking, purlins or roof cladding.</p>
			</description>
		</term>
		<term>
			<atom key="nz.nzbc.">Risk matrix</atom>
			<description>
				<p>A table that allows the calculation of a risk score by the allocation and summing of scores for a range of design and location factors applying to a specific building design.</p>
			</description>
		</term>
		<term>
			<atom key="nz.nzbc.">Risk score</atom>
			<description>
				<p>An aggregated numerical score for a proposed building as defined by this Acceptable Solution. The risk score is determined by completion of the risk matrix.</p>
			</description>
		</term>
		<term>
			<atom key="nz.nzbc.">Roof</atom>
			<description>
				<p>That part of a building having its upper surface exposed to the outside and at an angle of 60° or less to the horizontal.</p>
			</description>
		</term>
		<term>
			<atom key="nz.nzbc.">Roof underlay</atom>
			<description>
				<p>An absorbent permeable building paper that absorbs or collects condensation or water in association with roof cladding performance.</p>
			</description>
		</term>
		<term>
			<atom key="nz.nzbc.">Saddle flashing</atom>
			<description>
				<p>A flashing used to weatherproof the junction between a horizontal and vertical surface.</p>
			</description>
		</term>
		<term>
			<atom key="nz.nzbc.">Scupper</atom>
			<description>
				<p>An opening in a parapet or enclosed balustrade to allow water to drain into a rainwater head.</p>
			</description>
		</term>
		<term>
			<atom key="nz.nzbc.">Sill support bar</atom>
			<description>
				<p>A bar or mechanism complying with EM6, E2/VM1 tests, and Clause B2 of the Building Code, and used to support the weight of aluminium window and door joinery that is installed over drained cavities.</p>
			</description>
		</term>
		<term>
			<atom key="nz.nzbc.">Soft edge</atom>
			<description>
				<p>A compatible soft edging seamed onto flashings to provide closure to profiled cladding.</p>
			</description>
		</term>
		<term>
			<atom key="nz.nzbc.">Specific design</atom>
			<description>
				<p>Design and detailing for compliance with the Building Code, of a proposed part or parts of a building which are not shown in this Acceptable Solution. </p>
			</description>
		</term>
		<term>
			<atom key="nz.nzbc.">Stanchion</atom>
			<description>
				<p>A connecting device, fixed into the structure of a building, that provides support for handrails, aerials and similar structures.</p>
			</description>
		</term>
		<term>
			<atom key="nz.nzbc.">Stopend</atom>
			<description>
				<p>A turn-up at the upper edge of profiled metal cladding, or at the end of gutters and some types of flashings.</p>
			</description>
			<commentary title="COMMENT:">A stopend assists the control of moisture by ensuring any moisture reaching the edge of the roofing is deflected from further entry. </commentary>
		</term>
		<term>
			<atom key="nz.nzbc.">Storey</atom>
			<description>
				<p>That portion of a building included between the upper surface of any floor and the upper surface of the floor immediately above, except the top storey shall be that portion of a building included between the upper surface of the topmost floor and the ceiling or roof above.</p>
			</description>
		</term>
		<term>
			<atom key="nz.nzbc.">Stucco</atom>
			<description>
				<p>A wall cladding system formed from reinforced solid plaster over a rigid or non.rigid backing.</p>
			</description>
		</term>
		<term>
			<atom key="nz.nzbc.">Stud</atom>
			<description>
				<p>A vertical framing timber.</p>
			</description>
		</term>
		<term>
			<atom key="nz.nzbc.">Transverse flashing</atom>
			<description>
				<p>A roof flashing that runs across the roof slope, at right angles to the roof cladding profile.</p>
			</description>
		</term>
		<term>
			<atom key="nz.nzbc.">Trapezoidal</atom>
			<description>
				<p>A type of profiled metal cladding with symmetrical or asymmetrical crests, with troughs between the crests.</p>
			</description>
		</term>
		<term>
			<atom key="nz.nzbc.">Trough profile</atom>
			<description>
				<p>A type of profiled metal cladding comprising vertical ribs with flat, or lightly profiled pans between the ribs. Also known as ribbed, secret fixed or tray profile.</p>
			</description>
		</term>
		<term>
			<atom key="nz.nzbc.">Underlay</atom>
			<description>
				<p>The material used behind a roof or wall cladding. Refer Wall underlay and Roof underlay.</p>
			</description>
		</term>
		<term>
			<atom key="nz.nzbc.">Valley gutter</atom>
			<description>
				<p>A gutter running down the valley formed by the intersection of two pitched roof surfaces.</p>
			</description>
		</term>
		<term>
			<atom key="nz.nzbc.">Wall</atom>
			<description>
				<p>refer External wall.</p>
			</description>
		</term>
		<term>
			<atom key="nz.nzbc.">Wall underlay</atom>
			<description>
				<p>A building paper, synthetic material or rigid sheathing used as part of the wall cladding system to assist the control of moisture by ensuring moisture which occasionally penetrates the wall cladding is directed back to the exterior of the building.</p>
			</description>
		</term>
		<term>
			<atom key="nz.nzbc.">Waterproof</atom>
			<description>
				<p>and waterproofing The complete and total resistance of a building element to the ingress of any moisture.</p>
			</description>
		</term>
		<term>
			<atom key="nz.nzbc.">Weathertightness</atom>
			<description>
				<p>and weathertight Terms used to describe the resistance of a building to the weather. Weathertightness is a state where water is prevented from entering and accumulating behind the cladding in amounts that can cause undue dampness or damage to the building elements.</p>
			</description>
			<commentary title="COMMENT:">The term weathertightness is not necessarily the same as waterproof. However, a weathertight building, even under severe weather conditions, is expected to limit moisture ingress to inconsequential amounts, insufficient to cause undue dampness inside buildings and damage to building elements. Moisture that may occasionally enter is able to harmlessly escape or evaporate. </commentary>
		</term>
		<term>
			<atom key="nz.nzbc">Wetwall</atom>
			<description>
				<p>The exterior cladding on a wall with a drained cavity.</p>
			</description>
		</term>
		<term>
			<atom key="nz.nzbc.">Wind zone</atom>
			<description>
				<p>Categorisation of wind force experienced on a particular site as determined in NZS 3604, Section 5.</p>
			</description>
			<commentary title="COMMENT:">Maximum ultimate limit state speeds are: Low wind zone = wind speed of 32 m/s Medium wind zone = wind speed of 37 m/s High wind zone = wind speed of 44 m/s Very high wind zone = wind speed of 50 m/s Extra high wind zone = wind speed of 55 m/s. Specific design is required for wind speeds greater than 55 m/s.</commentary>
		</term>
	</definitions>
	<document key="E2/VM1" title="Verification Method E2/VM1">
		<part key="1.0" title="Cladding systems of buildings, including junctions with windows, doors and other penetrations">
			<section key="1.1" title="General">
				<p>This Verification Method is for determining compliance with NZBC E2.3.2 of cladding systems and associated window and door junctions only, for buildings of importance Levels 1 or 2 as described in Table 1.1(a) of NZS 3604.</p>
				<p>The tests in this Verification Method shall be undertaken in a test facility with IANZ or equivalent accreditation for testing the weathertightness of claddings to the procedures of AS/NZS 4284, and as used to establish the performance criteria detailed in Paragraph 1.4 Test Procedures.</p>
				<commentary title="COMMENT:">The weathertightness testing of AS/NZS 4284 is modified in this Verification Method for generic domestic-oriented cladding because the Standard was developed primarily for testing specific, non-absorptive facades and curtain wall systems on high-rise commercial buildings.</commentary>
			</section>
			<section key="1.2" title="Scope">
				<paragraph key="1.2.1">
					<p>The scope of this Verification Method shall be restricted to buildings that:</p>
					<ol>
						<li key="1.2.1.a">are in accordance with the scope of Paragraph 1.0 of E2/AS1, and within the wind zones covered by Section 5 of NZS 3604, and</li>
						<li key="1.2.1.b">have claddings that include a drained and vented cavity of nominal 20 mm minimum depth with minimum ventilation opening of 1000 mm2/m at the foot, including any claddings that require a rigid wall underlay in accordance with Paragraph 9.1.7.2 of E2/AS1, and</li>
						<li key="1.2.1.c">include window and door units that are manufactured to comply with the relevant requirements of NZS 4211, and</li>
						<li key="1.2.1.d">may include buildings based on (a), (b) and (c) above, but with specific engineering design frame elements of at least equivalent stiffness to the framing provisions defined in NZS 3604.</li>
					</ol>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="1.2.2">
					<p>This Verification Method may also be used for individual buildings that comply with (a) to (d) above, and that are designed for a specific wind pressure up to a maximum ultimate limit state (ULS) of 2500 Pa.</p>
					<commentary title="COMMENT: ">While the test specimens used for this Verification Method may include window and door units, it is only the junctions of these elements with other cladding elements that are assessed in the test.</commentary>
				</paragraph>
			</section>
			<section key="1.3" title="Specimen details">
				<p>The minimum size of the wall cladding specimen to be tested shall be 2.4 m x 2.4 m. Any cladding system within an Extra High wind zone or subject to a specific design wind pressure up to ULS 2500 Pa that relies on this Verification Method shall have a rigid underlay installed in accordance with Paragraph 9.1.7 of E2/AS1. In either of these two circumstances, a rigid underlay is not necessary for the verification tests as a flexible wall underlay may suffice - unless the cladding to be tested specifically includes a rigid underlay as part of the cladding system, and its removal would compromise the structural fixings or support for the cladding.</p>
				<commentary title="COMMENT: ">Testing a cladding with flexible underlay, but then verifying the cladding for use with rigid underlay, is allowed in order to make testing quicker and easier. It is expected that cladding systems with a cavity within the scope of E2/VM1 will perform better with a rigid underlay than with a flexible underlay, although this has not been proven.</commentary>
				<p>For cladding systems intended to be available for use in multiple situations, including cladding systems for which a New Zealand supplier has commissioned the testing for the purposes of providing product assurance, Class 1 or Class 2 testing must be selected. Class 1 and Class 2 each include a mandatory minimum set of details to be included in the specimen. If any of the mandatory details from Class 1 or Class 2 are omitted from the specimen, then E2/VM1 compliance to Class 1 or Class 2 cannot be claimed.</p>
				<paragraph key="1.3.1">
					<p>Class 1: Cladding systems where only vertical joints are required, and having no penetrations through the cladding. Test specimens shall include vertical joints, internal and external corners of the external wall junctions, and footer and header termination systems.</p>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="1.3.2">
					<p>Class 2: All cladding systems within the scope of this document that are not Class 1. Testing is to include representative samples of penetrating building elements or joints to be used.</p>
					<ol>
						<li key="1.3.2.a">Test specimens must include vertical and horizontal control joints, internal and external wall junctions, windows and/or doors, a parapet or enclosed balustrade capping with a saddle flashing, a 200 mm diameter pipe penetration, and footer and header termination systems.</li>
						<li key="1.3.2.b">Test specimens may also include other details relevant to the use of the cladding system on the building, such as scupper penetrations, meter boxes, junctions with other cladding systems or building elements, and junctions where roof and enclosed deck terminations, gutters, or other features occur within walls (including within the sides of framed chimneys with cladding).</li>
					</ol>
					<commentary title="COMMENT:">Although only certain details are mandatory for inclusion within test specimens, the inclusion of other additional details could enable manufacturers, suppliers and specifiers who commission tests to demonstrate compliance for a wider range of situations than those which the mandatory details cover. Manufacturers, suppliers and specifiers should ensure that test specimens include all cladding details or junctions for which compliance with this Verification Method is intended to be demonstrated and claimed.</commentary>
					<p>A 15 mm diameter round hole shall be formed in the internal lining below the window to simulate the effect of power points, light switches and other air leakage through the internal lining. Where a cladding specimen is larger than 2.4 m x 2.4 m, an additional 15 mm hole shall be added for each 7 m. of cladding area (or part thereof).</p>
					<subparagraph key="1.3.2.1">
						<p>To allow the observation of any water penetration, one of the following options must be followed:</p>
						<ol>
							<li key="1.3.2.1.a">For specimens that include a rigid wall underlay, adjacent to critical elements where visual access is required a proportion of the underlay shall be made using transparent material of sufficient structural capability and similar airtightness to the specified wall lining material, and able to resist the applied wind pressures. The proportion shall be at least 2%, but shall be small enough that it does not affect the ability of the specimen to represent the performance of the underlay within the cladding system; or</li>
							<li key="1.3.2.1.b">For specimens that do not include a rigid wall underlay, adjacent to critical elements where visual access is required, the wall underlay shall be cut through and removed, or fastened back onto the framing, with a rigid transparent internal lining used to support the air pressure. It is required that between 2% and 100% of the area of the wall underlay (or equivalent) be so removed; or</li>
							<li key="1.3.2.1.c">For specimens that include a flexible or a rigid underlay, small video cameras and/ or borescopes shall be installed within the cavity to provide a clear view of all critical elements where visual access is required. Borescopes and cameras must be positioned clear of all junctions, and must be installed in a manner that does not affect the airtightness of the air barrier (rigid underlay or internal wall lining) or affect the path of any moisture that enters the cavity.</li>
						</ol>
						<commentary title="COMMENT:">The use of borescopes and cameras requires care to achieve these requirements, but may be the most appropriate option in situations such as when other AS/NZS 4284 tests are to be performed on the same specimen, or to help resolve doubts about whether the replacement of a proportion of the lining or underlay with a transparent material will affect the performance of the cladding.</commentary>
					</subparagraph>
				</paragraph>
			</section>
			<section key="1.4" title="Test procedure">
				<p>The Verification Method shall consist of the extended water penetration test methodologies of AS/NZS 4284, following a preconditioning pressure loading exposure.</p>
				<paragraph key="1.4.1" title="Preconditioning">
					<p>Apply a preconditioning loading to the external face of the test sample for a period of 1 minute of positive pressure, followed by a period of 1 minute of negative pressure (suction). The loading shall be 1515 Pa.</p>
					<commentary title="COMMENT:">As the ventilated cavity is subjected to the same applied pressure, it is necessary that the material serving as the air seal is able to sustain the same applied loading. Where the test wall is utilising a permeable wall underlay or membrane, the internal wall lining will be required to sustain the serviceability limit state (SLS) wind pressures.</commentary>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="1.4.2" title="Series 1 Static Pressure Water Penetration">
					<p>The water penetration test by static pressure shall be conducted in accordance with Clause 8.5 of AS/NZS 4284 and at the maximum test pressure of 455 Pa.</p>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="1.4.3" title="Series 1 Cyclic Pressure Water Penetration">
					<p>The water penetration test by cyclic pressure shall be conducted in accordance with Clause 8.6 of AS/NZS 4284 and to the cyclic pressure of 455 - 910 Pa at the prescribed Stage 3, with the Stage 1 and Stage 2 tests deleted.</p>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="1.4.4" title="Series 2 'Water Management Testing'">
					<p>Paragraphs 1.4.2 and 1.4.3 shall be repeated, following the formation of 6 mm diameter holes through the wetwall as allowed in AS/NZS 4284 Clause 9.9 in at least 4 places, as noted below:</p>
					<ol>
						<li key="1.4.4.a">Through the window/wall joint at 3/4 height of both window/door jambs,</li>
						<li key="1.4.4.b">Immediately above the head flashing,</li>
						<li key="1.4.4.c">Through the external sealing of the horizontal and vertical joints, and</li>
						<li key="1.4.4.d">Above any other wetwall penetration detail.</li>
					</ol>
					<p>The introduction of defects is intended to simulate the failure of the primary weather-defence/sealing. It must only penetrate to the plane of the back of the wetwall so the water management of the cavity can be assessed.</p>
					<subparagraph key="1.4.4.1">
						<p>Immediately upon the conclusion of the Water Management Tests (within 30 minutes) (Paragraph 1.4.4), the layers behind the wetwall that support air pressure (including sealing in the window trim cavity) shall be removed, and any evidence of non-compliance (as defined in Paragraph 1.5) noted.</p>
					</subparagraph>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="1.4.5" title="Series 3 'Wetwall Test'">
					<subparagraph key="1.4.5.1">
						<p>Repeat Paragraph 1.4.2 with an air pressure of 50 Pa, applied across the wetwall only, for 15 minutes.</p>
					</subparagraph>
				</paragraph>
			</section>
			<section key="1.5" title="Non-compliance">
				<paragraph key="1.5.1">
					<p>Non-compliance shall be the presence of water (as defined in Paragraph 1.5.2), or evidence of any water, either:</p>
					<ol>
						<li key="1.5.1.a">On the removed surfaces of the cavity after carrying out the tests in Paragraphs 1.4.2 and 1.4.3, and the subsequent 'water management' tests in Paragraph 1.4.4, and/or</li>
						<li key="1.5.1.b">During or after the test in Paragraph 1.4.5.</li>
					</ol>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="1.5.2">
					<p>Water which is able to penetrate to the back of the wetwall through introduced defects and joints shall be controlled. It may contact battens and other cavity surfaces, but no water shall be transferred to the plane of the wall underlay, cavity air sealing or structural framing due to a design or systemic failure. Water that may arrive on the underlay due to an 'isolated blemish' may be disregarded. No water may drip through an airspace within the cavity where it is possible for water to impact on a surface in the cavity and splash onto the wall underlay. However, any spattering of water into the cavity through the introduced defects shall be ignored. During the Wetwall Test, water is allowed to spatter up from the footer flashing, provided it is not held above any cavity obstruction.</p>
				</paragraph>
			</section>
			<section key="1.6" title="Existing verification certificates as at 31 March 2019">
				<paragraph key="1.6.1">
					<p>E2/VM1, included in E2 Acceptable Solutions and Verification Methods Amendment 8, is effective from 30 November 2018.</p>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="1.6.2">
					<p>E2/VM1, included in E2 Acceptable Solutions and Verification Methods Amendments 5 - 7 remains effective (excluding transitional arrangements for E2/ VM1 included in E2 Acceptable Solutions and Verification Methods Amendment 4 or earlier) for all cladding systems with verification certificates issued prior to 31 March 2019 provided that any verification certificates issued under E2/VM1 from 31 March 2019 must be under E2 Acceptable Solutions and Verification Methods Amendment 8.</p>
				</paragraph>
			</section>
			<section key="1.7" title="Pro-forma for test details">
				<p>The pro forma attached as Appendix 1 to this Verification Method may be used to provide specifiers with a summary of test details and results.</p>
			</section>
		</part>
		<part key="2.0" title="Pitched roofing systems over a ventilated roof space of 15° pitch or more">
			<section key="2.1">
				<p>AS 4046 Part 9 provides a Verification Method for determining compliance with NZBC E2.3.2 of any tiled roofing system of 15° pitch or more above a roof space (i.e. not a skillion roof). Compliance is based on comparison of performance with a control roofing system described in the Standard. Compliance is achieved where the water penetration is less than, or equal to, the control sample. This test is also a Verification Method for other ventilated roofing systems or skylights with a pitch of 15° or more above a roof space.</p>
			</section>
		</part>
		<part key="3.0" title="Skillion roofs and commercial and industrial roofing">
			<section key="3.1">
				<p>No specific method has been adopted for verifying compliance of skillion roofs or commercial or industrial roofing with NZBC E2.3.2.</p>
			</section>
		</part>
	</document>
	<document key="E2/AS1" title="Acceptable Solution E2/AS1">
		<part key="1.0" title="Scope">
			<p>This Acceptable Solution covers the weathertightness of the building envelope. Notes shown under 'COMMENT', occurring throughout this document are for guidance purposes only and do not form part of this Acceptable Solution.</p>
			<section key="1.1" title="Construction included">
				<p>The scope of this Acceptable Solution is limited to the materials, products and processes contained herein, for buildings within the scope of NZS 3604, and:</p>
				<ol>
					<li key="1.1.a">Up to 3 storeys with a height measured from lowest ground level adjacent to the building to the highest point of the roof (except for chimneys, aerials and the like) of 10 m or less, and</li>
					<li key="1.1.b">With floor plan area limited only by seismic and structural control joints, and</li>
					<li key="1.1.c">External walls that are vertical, and roofs that are 60¼ or less above the horizontal.</li>
				</ol>
				<p>Where buildings are based on NZS 3604, but require specific engineering design input, the framing shall be of at least equivalent stiffness to the framing provisions of NZS 3604.</p>
				<commentary title="COMMENT:">The floor plan limitations of NZS 3604 may be exceeded up to the point that specific design is required to accommodate seismic or wind movement. Beyond that point, specific design is required to demonstrate compliance with Clause E2 of the Building Code. Claddings also required to perform as bracing must comply with NZS 3604. Where a drained cavity is used, specific testing can be used to demonstrate that a cladding on cavity battens can provide the required bracing resistance.</commentary>
				<paragraph key="1.1.1" title="Attached garages">
					<p>Attached garages that are integral with the weathertightness envelope of the building are included within the scope of this Acceptable Solution. Refer to Paragraph 9.1.3.4.</p>
				</paragraph>
			</section>
			<section key="1.2" title="Construction excluded">
				<paragraph key="1.2.1" title="Outbuildings">
					<p>Outbuildings, such as stand-alone garages and other structures that are unlined, are outside the scope of this Acceptable Solution.</p>
					<commentary title="COMMENT:">Details contained in this Acceptable Solution can be used for outbuildings and unlined structures, but the requirements may be in excess of the minimum required by the Building Code. This is particularly the case in regard to unlined and uninsulated buildings, where a drained cavity is unlikely to be necessary. However, care must be taken, as some weathertight details depend on the presence of an internal lining to provide pressure equalisation behind the cladding.</commentary>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="1.2.2" title="Spread of flame">
					<p>Buildings with drained cavities and spread-of-flame requirements, as specified in NZBC C Clauses, are outside the scope of this Acceptable Solution. Cavities in such circumstances must be specifically designed for both weathertightness and spread of flame.</p>
					<commentary title="COMMENT: ">Options could include the provision of a fire rated wall behind the battens, or breaking the cavity at each floor and providing a cavity flashing and fire stop at each level.</commentary>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="1.2.3" title="Acoustics">
					<p>Buildings with drained cavities and acoustic requirements, as specified in NZBC Clause G6, are outside the scope of this Acceptable Solution.</p>
					<commentary title="COMMENT:">Cavities in such circumstances must be specifically designed for both weathertightness and acoustic performance.</commentary>
				</paragraph>
			</section>
			<section key="1.3" title="Provisions for snow">
				<p>Specific design for preventing the ingress of snow melt water is required when the open ground snow load Sg, as defined in NZS 3604, exceeds 1.0 kPa, and the roof is constructed in a way that is likely to cause a build-up of snow.</p>
				<commentary title="COMMENT:">Hidden gutters, parapets and skylights are examples of features within a roof design that are likely to cause a build-up of snow.</commentary>
			</section>
			<section key="1.4" title="Specific design">
				<p>Buildings, components or junction details not included or shown in this Acceptable Solution require specific design.</p>
			</section>
			<section key="1.5" title="Qualifications">
				<commentary title="COMMENT:">An understanding of the proper methods of design and installation and the importance of the correct construction sequence is essential if an NZBC compliant building is to be achieved. Adequate training by those designing and applying particular products and claddings is therefore highly recommended. The design, installation and alteration of claddings will be 'restricted work' under the licensed building practitioner scheme, due to take effect in 2012. Until then, the use of licensed designers, builders and installers is optional. It is important that product suppliers, manufacturers and NZ agents (for imported products) ensure those handling and applying their products are adequately trained to do so, and that site managers oversee the correct integration of adjoining building elements to achieve a complete weathering system.</commentary>
			</section>
		</part>
		<part key="2.0" title="General">
			<section key="2.1" title="Weathertightness">
				<p>Cladding systems shall meet the requirements of NZBC E2.2 to E2.3.7, and the provisions of this Acceptable Solution are acceptable means of achieving this.</p>
				<commentary title="COMMENT:">Most manufacturers provide technical literature for their cladding materials and systems that include recommendations for design and installation. Manufacturers' recommendations may include information additional to that shown in this Acceptable Solution. However, some additional work, such as extra fixings that penetrate flashings, can lead to details that need to be considered in terms of specific design. Additional or alternative details may be required that need supporting documentation or testing to demonstrate compliance in regard to weathertightness.</commentary>
			</section>
			<section key="2.2" title="Materials">
				<p>Materials used to construct the building envelope shall be:</p>
				<ol>
					<li key="2.2.a">In accordance with the durability requirements of NZBC B2,</li>
					<li key="2.2.b">Suitable for their end-use, location and environment as shown in Table 20, and</li>
					<li key="2.2.c">Compatible with adjoining materials as shown in Table 21 and Table 22.</li>
				</ol>
			</section>
			<section key="2.3" title="Systems versus materials">
				<p>All building products shall be considered as part of a system, even if the components of that system are provided from different sources. Materials used to construct the building envelope shall be designed as a complete cladding system rather than as separate items.</p>
				<commentary title="COMMENT:">It is important that the compatibility and durability of the combination of materials is able to be demonstrated for any given application.</commentary>
			</section>
			<section key="2.4" title="Cladding finish colours">
				<p>Finish colours for flush-finished fibre cement sheet and EIFS shall have a reflectivity of 40% or more when measured in accordance with ASTM C1549.</p>
				<commentary title="COMMENT:">Dark colours cause claddings to reach higher temperatures, which results in more thermal expansion and a greater risk of cracking of joints in monolithic wall claddings. Risks of cracking are also associated with dark colours on painted timber wall claddings and trim. Expansion of metal roofing and flashings are affected by dark colours. Colour cards from some coating manufacturers may include reflectance values.</commentary>
			</section>
			<section key="2.5" title="Maintenance - general">
				<p>Maintenance shall be carried out as necessary to achieve the required durability of materials, components and junctions.</p>
				<p>The extent and nature of necessary maintenance is dependent on the:</p>
				<ol>
					<li key="2.5.a">Type of cladding or components used,</li>
					<li key="2.5.b">Position of cladding or components on the building,</li>
					<li key="2.5.c">Geographical location of the building, and</li>
					<li key="2.5.d">Specific site conditions.</li>
				</ol>
				<commentary title="COMMENT:">A deterioration in the appearance of the surface of a cladding does not necessarily relate to a deterioration in the weathertightness of the cladding.</commentary>
				<paragraph key="2.5.1" title="Regular maintenance">
					<p>Regular maintenance of a building will include:</p>
					<ol>
						<li key="2.5.1.a">Washing exterior surfaces,</li>
						<li key="2.5.1.b">Inspecting surfaces and junctions, and repairing or replacing items when necessary, in order to preserve the weathertightness of the building.</li>
						<li key="2.5.1.c">Maintaining clearances between cladding and external ground or paving as per Paragraph 9.1.3.</li>
						<li key="2.5.1.d">Maintaining minimum 35 mm clearances between roofing and membrane decking, and wall cladding above</li>
						<li key="2.5.1.e">Maintaining finish coatings especially for stucco, EIFS and fibre cement claddings.</li>
					</ol>
					<commentary title="COMMENT:">Washing by rain removes most accumulated atmospheric contaminants, but sheltered areas, such as walls directly below eaves, are protected from the direct effects of rain and require regular manual washing. Some heavily textured surfaces will not be as effectively washed by rain as smoother surfaces, so will require more regular manual washing. However, it is important that high pressure water is not directed at sensitive junctions such as window surrounds and other flashings. Great care must be taken to avoid water being driven past anti-capillary gaps and flashings into the wall cavities.</commentary>
				</paragraph>
			</section>
		</part>
		<part key="3.0" title="Weathertightness Risk Factors">
			<commentary title="COMMENT:">Analysis of inspection reports from leaking buildings shows that a high incidence of leaks is associated with junctions within, and penetrations through, the building envelope. It also shows serious problems are more commonly associated with claddings that have limited capacity to drain and dry out any water that gets behind them, when a leak occurs. This Acceptable Solution addresses these problems in two ways: a) By providing details for common junctions and penetrations of the building envelope, and b) By classifying buildings within the scope of this document into risk categories, and requiring different cladding solutions depending on the risk score. Using the risk assessment, risk factors can be identified and changes may be made to a design to lower the risk score.</commentary>
			<section key="3.1" title="Establishing the risk">
				<p>A risk assessment of the proposed design shall be carried out using a building envelope risk matrix. This allows the risks related to various features to be aggregated, resulting in a risk score for the design. Figure 1 shows the process that shall be followed in order to assess the risk.</p>
				<paragraph key="3.1.1" title="Definitions of risk">
					<p>Table 1 sets out the definitions of risk levels relating to the location and design features of the building.</p>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="3.1.2" title="The risk score">
					<p>Table 2 sets out the risk matrix that shall be used to define the risk score for a building within the scope of this Acceptable Solution. A risk score is calculated for each external face of the building. Claddings are then selected from Table 3 according to the risk scores, or the highest risk score may be used for all walls.</p>
				</paragraph>
			</section>
			<section key="3.3" title="Wall claddings">
				<p>The following wall cladding systems are covered in this Acceptable Solution:</p>
				<ol>
					<li key="3.3.a">Masonry veneer - Paragraph 9.2</li>
					<li key="3.3.b">Stucco - Paragraph 9.3</li>
					<li key="3.3.c">Timber weatherboards - Paragraph 9.4</li>
					<li key="3.3.d">Fibre cement weatherboards - Paragraph 9.5</li>
					<li key="3.3.e">Profiled metal wall claddin -  Paragraph 9.6</li>
					<li key="3.3.f">Fibre cement she -  Paragraph 9.7</li>
					<li key="3.3.g">Plywood she -  Paragraph 9.8</li>
					<li key="3.3.h">EIF - Paragraph 9.9</li>
				</ol>
				<p>Other wall claddings are outside the scope of this Acceptable Solution.</p>
				<figure key="1" keyRef="3.1" title="How to assess risk" type="paragraph"/>
			</section>
			<section key="3.4" title="Examples using the risk matrix">
				<p>Paragraphs 3.4.1 to 3.4.3 provide examples that show a range of building styles. The completion of the risk matrix for each design is shown, together with the choice of wall claddings the risk scores indicate.</p>
				<commentary title="COMMENT:">The examples have been selected to show a range of design complexities, features and materials. Refer also to Guide to the Risk Matrix.</commentary>
				<paragraph key="3.4.1" title="Example 1">
					<p>The first example illustrates the use of the risk matrix for a simple traditionally-styled building.</p>
					<commentary title="COMMENT:">The house in this example is a simple single storey L shape and is considered low risk in terms of envelope complexity. The eaves are 500 mm wide, and the site is in a High wind zone. The covered porch is at ground level and so is considered low risk. For this example, the calculations have been done for the south elevation, and this face scores as very low risk. A similar risk score would result for all elevations of this building.</commentary>
					<figure key="2" title="Risk matrix example 1"/>
					<subparagraph key="3.4.1.1" title="Cladding options">
						<p>As all faces score low, cladding options from Table 3 are:</p>
						<ol>
							<li key="3.4.1.1.a">
								<p>Direct fixed claddings:</p>
								<ol>
									<li key="3.4.1.1.a.i">Timber weatherboards - all types shown</li>
									<li key="3.4.1.1.a.ii">Fibre cement weatherboards</li>
									<li key="3.4.1.1.a.iii">Vertical profiled metal - corrugated and symmetrical trapezoidal only</li>
									<li key="3.4.1.1.a.iv">Fibre cement sheet - not flush-finished</li>
									<li key="3.4.1.1.a.v">Plywood sheet</li>
								</ol>
							</li>
							<li key="3.4.1.1.b">
								<p>Wall cladding with a nominal 20 mm drained cavity (note: claddings in Extra High wind zones require rigid underlays):</p>
								<ol>
									<li key="3.4.1.1.b.i">Masonry veneer</li>
									<li key="3.4.1.1.b.ii">Stucco</li>
									<li key="3.4.1.1.b.iii">Horizontal profiled metal - corrugated and trapezoidal only</li>
									<li key="3.4.1.1.b.iv">Fibre cement - flush-finished</li>
									<li key="3.4.1.1.b.v">EIFS.</li>
								</ol>
							</li>
						</ol>
					</subparagraph>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="3.4.2" title="Example 2">
					<p>The second example illustrates the use of the risk matrix for a moderately complex building.</p>
					<figure key="3" title="Risk matrix example 2"/>
					<commentary title="COMMENT:">Overall the house in this example is still a relatively simple design with a single cladding type. It would be considered to be medium risk in terms of envelope complexity. The lean-to style room on the ground floor is quite simple but does introduce a roof-to-wall intersection which requires the correct flashing and particular care with the kick-out at the west end of the junction. This would make this factor very high risk. The timber deck, itself low risk, connects to the house at the first floor level, and so is considered to be medium risk. Any leaks at the connection points have an opportunity to enter the wall below. The eaves are less than 450 mm wide, and the site is in a High wind zone. The calculations have been done for the south elevation. The other elevations of this building score lower because they are simpler. The west elevation still has the deck connection and scores 7. Cladding options would be the same as for the south face. The east elevation scores 6 and the north elevation scores 5, so these have more cladding options.</commentary>
					<subparagraph key="3.4.2.1" title="Cladding options - south and west elevations">
						<p>Cladding options from Table 3, are:</p>
						<ol>
							<li key="3.4.2.1.a">
								<p>Direct fixed claddings:</p>
								<ol>
									<li key="3.4.2.1.i">Bevel-back weatherboards</li>
									<li key="3.4.2.1.ii">Vertical board and batten weatherboards</li>
									<li key="3.4.2.1.iii">Vertical corrugated metal, and</li>
								</ol>
							</li>
							<li key="3.4.2.1.b">
								<p>Wall cladding with a nominal 20 mm drained cavity:</p>
								<ol>
									<li key="3.4.2.1.b.i">Masonry veneer (with 40 mm cavity)</li>
									<li key="3.4.2.1.b.ii">Stucco</li>
									<li key="3.4.2.1.b.iii">Horizontal profiled metal - corrugated and trapezoidal only</li>
									<li key="3.4.2.1.b.iv">Rusticated weatherboards</li>
									<li key="3.4.2.1.b.v">Fibre cement weatherboards</li>
									<li key="3.4.2.1.b.vi">Fibre cement sheet</li>
									<li key="3.4.2.1.b.vii">Plywood sheet</li>
									<li key="3.4.2.1.b.viii">EIFS.</li>
								</ol>
							</li>
						</ol>
					</subparagraph>
					<subparagraph key="3.4.2.2" title="Cladding options - north and east elevations">
						<p>Cladding options from Table 3, for east and north faces, are:</p>
						<ol>
							<li key="3.4.2.2.a">
								<p>Direct fixed claddings:</p>
								<ol>
									<li key="3.4.2.2.a.i">Timber weatherboards – all types</li>
									<li key="3.4.2.2.a.ii">Fibre cement weatherboards</li>
									<li key="3.4.2.2.a.iii">Vertical profiled metal – corrugated and symmetrical trapezoidal only</li>
									<li key="3.4.2.2.a.iv">Fibre cement sheet v) Plywood sheet</li>
									<li key="3.4.2.2.a.v">EIFS, and</li>
								</ol>
							</li>
							<li key="3.4.2.2.b">
								<p>Wall cladding with a nominal 20 mm drained cavity:</p>
								<ol>
									<li key="3.4.2.2.b.i">Masonry veneer (with 40 mm cavity)</li>
									<li key="3.4.2.2.b.ii">Stucc</li>
									<li key="3.4.2.2.b.iii">Horizontal profiled metal – corrugated and trapezoidal only.</li>
								</ol>
							</li>
						</ol>
					</subparagraph>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="3.4.3" title="Example 3">
					<p>The third example illustrates the use of the risk matrix for a complex building.</p>
					<commentary title="COMMENT:">The combination of features present on the south elevation results in a very high risk score. The presence of a parapet at the roof, decks, enclosed balustrade-to- wall junctions and pergola connections all contribute to this risk. The site is in a High wind zone. The risk score is sufficiently high that the south elevation would require specific design, or redesign to lower the risk. Specific design may result in the building consent authority possibly: a) Needing more details to be provided, b) Requiring more inspections during construction, c) Requiring a third party audit of the design. The east and west elevations also score very highly at 18-20, and would require a cladding with a cavity such as vertical profiled steel, masonry veneer or any other cladding with a nominal 20 mm drained cavity. The north elevation scores 14, so would require the use of the same cladding option as the east and west elevations.</commentary>
					<figure key="4" title="Risk matrix example 3"/>
					<subparagraph key="3.4.3.1" title="Cladding options - south elevation">
						<p>As the south face scores over 20, it will require:</p>
						<ol>
							<li key="3.4.3.1.a">Specific design, or</li>
							<li key="3.4.3.1.b">Redesigning the proposal to reduce the risk, so reducing the risk score.</li>
						</ol>
					</subparagraph>
					<subparagraph key="3.4.3.2" title="Cladding options - other elevations">
						<p>As the other faces score from 14 to 20, cladding options from Table 3 are:</p>
						<ol>
							<li key="3.4.3.2.a">
								<p>Direct fixed claddings:</p>
								<ol>
									<li key="3.4.3.2.a.i">Vertical corrugated metal, and</li>
								</ol>
							</li>
							<li key="3.4.3.2.b">
								<p>Wall cladding with a nominal 20 mm drained cavity:</p>
								<ol>
									<li key="3.4.3.2.b.i">Masonry veneer (with 40 mm cavity)</li>
									<li key="3.4.3.2.b.ii">Stucco</li>
									<li key="3.4.3.2.b.iii">Horizontal profiled metal - corrugated and trapezoidal only</li>
									<li key="3.4.3.2.b.iv">Rusticated weatherboards</li>
									<li key="3.4.3.2.b.v">Fibre cement weatherboards</li>
									<li key="3.4.3.2.b.vi">Fibre cement sheet</li>
									<li key="3.4.3.2.b.vii">Plywood sheet</li>
									<li key="3.4.3.2.b.viii">EIFS</li>
									<li key="3.4.3.2.b.ix">Bevel-back weatherboards.</li>
								</ol>
							</li>
						</ol>
					</subparagraph>
				</paragraph>
			</section>
		</part>
		<part key="4.0" title="Flashings">
			<section key="4.1" title="Materials for flashings">
				<p>Acceptable materials for flashing junctions and penetrations are described in Paragraph 4.3.</p>
			</section>
			<section key="4.2" title="Selection of flashing materials">
				<p>Flashing materials shall take into account the following factors:</p>
				<ol>
					<li key="4.2.a">The requirements of NZBC Clause B2 Durability,</li>
					<li key="4.2.b">The environment where the building is located,</li>
					<li key="4.2.c">The specific conditions of use, and</li>
					<li key="4.2.d">Consideration of the surrounding materials.</li>
				</ol>
				<commentary title="COMMENT:">Generally, the durability requirements for flashings specified in B2 are: a) 50 years, where flashings are: i) completely hidden behind claddings such as masonry veneer, or ii) not accessible, b) 15 years, where flashings are: i) exposed, partially exposed, or ii) accessible. Two part flashings allow replacement of the flashing without cladding alteration. An example of a two part flashing is shown in Figure 7.</commentary>
				<paragraph key="4.2.1" title="Environment">
					<p>Flashing materials shall be selected according to the relevant exposure conditions as defined in Table 20 to minimise corrosion.</p>
					<commentary title="COMMENT:">The exposure zone in which a building is located can affect the durability of flashings. Exposure zones are defined in NZS 3604, based on the likely exposure to wind-driven sea-salt. Corrosion due to geothermal or corrosive industrial atmospheres, as defined in NZS 3604, require specific design. Exposure zones are based on AS/NZS 2728. AS/NZS 2728 lists atmospheric classes derived from ISO 9223 for Australia and New Zealand.</commentary>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="4.2.2" title="Surrounding materials">
					<p>Metals which are in contact in locations where they will become wet, or where water can flow over metals or certain plastics onto another metal, shall be selected in accordance with Table 21 and Table 22.</p>
					<p>Uncoated metals shall not be used where carbon deposits or chemical contaminants may accumulate.</p>
					<commentary title="COMMENT:">Undesirable effects can occur when some materials are in contact with each other. Examples are corrosion of metals, stress cracking of plastics and staining of glass. Carbon deposits such as soot will cause accelerated corrosion of damp uncoated metal.</commentary>
				</paragraph>
			</section>
			<section key="4.3" title="Acceptable flashing materials">
				<p>Tables 20, 21 and 22 shall be used to assess suitability of flashing materials for the required durability.</p>
				<commentary title="COMMENT:">Additional guidance on flashing materials can be found in the New Zealand Metal Roof and Wall Cladding Code of Practice.</commentary>
				<paragraph key="4.3.1" title="uPVC flashings">
					<p>uPVC flashings shall be a minimum of 0.75 mm thick. uPVC flashings shall comply with the requirements of the following Clauses of AS/NZS 4256: Part 2:</p>
					<ol>
						<li key="4.3.1.a">Clause 9.2 Impact resistance,</li>
						<li key="4.3.1.b">Clause 9.3 Tensile strength, and</li>
						<li key="4.3.1.c">Clause 9.4 Colourfastness and impact resistance following ultraviolet light exposure.</li>
					</ol>
					<p>Where uPVC flashings are exposed to the weather, they shall also comply with Section 8 of AS/NZS 4256: Part 2. uPVC flashings shall have a finish colour with a reflectance of 40% or more, as outlined in Paragraph 2.4.</p>
					<commentary title="COMMENT:">Manufacturers of uPVC flashings which have a proven performance in use may be able to show compliance with NZBC Clause B2 Durability as detailed in B2/VM1.</commentary>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="4.3.2" title="Aluminium flashings">
					<p>Aluminium flashings shall be a minimum thickness of 0.7 mm, and formed from 5000 series in accordance with AS/NZS 1734.</p>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="4.3.3" title="Galvanized steel flashings">
					<p>Galvanized steel flashings shall:</p>
					<ol>
						<li key="4.3.3.a">have a BMT of 0.55 mm minimum</li>
						<li key="4.3.3.b">be grade G550, or G300 for rolled or crimped flashings</li>
						<li key="4.3.3.c">be selected for corrosion protection according to the intended exposure zone as shown in Table 20.</li>
					</ol>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="4.3.4" title="Aluminium-zinc-magnesium (combinations) coated steel flashings to AS 1397">
					<p>Aluminium-zinc-magnesium coated steel shall:</p>
					<ol>
						<li key="4.3.4.a">have a BMT of 0.55 mm minimum</li>
						<li key="4.3.4.b">be grade G550, or G300 for curved or crimped flashings</li>
						<li key="4.3.4.c">be selected for corrosion protection according to the intended exposure zone as shown in Table 20.</li>
					</ol>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="4.3.5" title="Stainless steel flashings">
					<p>Stainless steel flashings shall be:</p>
					<ol>
						<li key="4.3.5.a">Minimum thickness of 0.45 mm, and</li>
						<li key="4.3.5.b">304 or 316 stainless steel in accordance with Table 1 of ISO/TS 15510.</li>
					</ol>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="4.3.6" title="Copper flashings">
					<p>Copper flashings shall be:</p>
					<ol>
						<li key="4.3.6.a">A minimum thickness of 0.5 mm,</li>
						<li key="4.3.6.b">In compliance with AS 1566, and</li>
						<li key="4.3.6.c">Alloy, designation C11000 or C12200.</li>
					</ol>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="4.3.7" title="Lead sheet flashings">
					<p>Lead sheet flashings shall: </p>
					<ol>
						<li key="4.3.7.a">Comply with AS 1804, and</li>
						<li key="4.3.7.b">Have a minimum unit mass of 17 kg/m2.</li>
					</ol>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="4.3.8" title="Zinc sheet flashings">
					<p>Zinc sheet flashings shall only be used in accordance with Tables 20, 21 and 22. Zinc sheet flashings shall be:</p>
					<ol>
						<li key="4.3.8.a">A minimum thickness of 0.7 mm, and</li>
						<li key="4.3.8.b">In compliance with BS EN 988.</li>
					</ol>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="4.3.9" title="Butyl rubber and EPDM flashings">
					<p>Butyl rubber flashings shall only be used in accordance with Tables 20, 21 and 22. Butyl rubber and EPDM flashings shall be a minimum thickness of 1.0 mm, and shall comply with the following parts of Table 1 in ASTM D6134:</p>
					<ol>
						<li key="4.3.9.a">Tensile strength,</li>
						<li key="4.3.9.b">Elongation,</li>
						<li key="4.3.9.c">Water absorption,</li>
						<li key="4.3.9.d">Water vapour permeance, and</li>
						<li key="4.3.9.e">
							<p>Heat aging followed by:</p>
							<ol>
								<li key="4.3.9.e.i">tensile strength</li>
								<li key="4.3.9.e.ii">elongation.</li>
							</ol>
						</li>
					</ol>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="4.3.10" title="Bituminous flashings">
					<p>Bituminous flashings shall only be used in accordance with Table 20. Flashings made from bitumen-impregnated material shall:</p>
					<ol>
						<li key="4.3.10.a">Comply with AS/NZS 2904, and</li>
						<li key="4.3.10.b">Be used only in fully concealed applications.</li>
					</ol>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="4.3.11" title="Flexible flashing tape ">
					<p>Flexible flashing tape shall comply with Parts 3.2 and 4 of ICBO Acceptance Criteria AC148, shall be compatible with adjacent building wall underlay or roof underlay, and be used only in fully concealed applications.</p>
				</paragraph>
			</section>
			<section key="4.4" title="Fixings">
				<p>Fixings of metal flashings shall comply with Tables 20, 21 and 22. Exposed flashings such as barge and ridge flashings are to be fixed along both edges.</p>
				<commentary title="COMMENT:">Fixings that penetrate flashings should be avoided where possible.</commentary>
			</section>
			<section key="4.5" title="Flashing requirements">
				<p>All flashings shall have expansion joints where required in Paragraph 4.5.2 to provide for thermal expansion.</p>
				<p>Flashings are required to shed or divert water at sensitive areas of the building cladding. These include at:</p>
				<ol>
					<li key="4.5.a">The building periphery, except where gutters are present,</li>
					<li key="4.5.b">Changes of direction in cladding materials,</li>
					<li key="4.5.c">Intersections between cladding materials or with other buildings, and</li>
					<li key="4.5.d">Roof or wall penetrations, including windows, doors and other penetrations.</li>
				</ol>
				<paragraph key="4.5.1" title="Edge treatments for flashings">
					<p>Flashings shall be to the dimensions shown throughout this Acceptable Solution. Exposed bottom edges of flashings shall be folded to a kick-out or a bird's beak as shown in Figure 5. For Low, Medium, High and Very High wind zones, flashing upstands shall have either: 1) A hem or hook to Figure 5, with upstand dimensions as shown throughout the document, or 2) No hooks or hems, and flashing upstand dimensions increased by 25 mm beyond those shown. For Extra High wind zones, hooks and hems shall be used, and flashing upstand dimensions increased by 25 mm beyond those shown in Table 7 or elsewhere in the document.</p>
					<commentary title="COMMENT:">Refer to the New Zealand Metal Roof and Wall Cladding Code of Practice for further edge treatments.</commentary>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="4.5.2" title="Metal flashing joints">
					<p>Where metal flashings require to be joined, the method shall be as shown in Figure 6. Joins of metal flashings shall have the following features:</p>
					<ol>
						<li key="4.5.2.a">
							<p>Rivets used for joining and sealing laps shall be spaced at a maximum of 50 mm centres, and be:</p>
							<ol>
								<li key="4.5.2.a.i">compatible with the flashing material as per Table 21 and Table 22, and</li>
								<li key="4.5.2.a.ii">sealed against moisture, or</li>
								<li key="4.5.2.a.iii">of a sealing type or blind rivet,</li>
							</ol>
						</li>
						<li key="4.5.2.b">
							<p>Expansion joints shall be provided for joined flashings with a combined length exceeding:</p>
							<ol>
								<li key="4.5.2.b.i">12 metres for light coloured steel and stainless steel. 8 metres for dark coloured steel,</li>
								<li key="4.5.2.b.ii">8 metres for copper,</li>
								<li key="4.5.2.b.iii">8 metres for aluminium.</li>
							</ol>
						</li>
						<li key="4.5.2.c">Where both ends of a flashing are constrained, allowance shall be made for expansion,</li>
						<li key="4.5.2.d">
							<p>Where necessary, expansion joints shall be formed as shown in Figure 6, with:</p>
							<ol>
								<li key="4.5.2.d.i">minimum 200 mm laps, and</li>
								<li key="4.5.2.d.ii">sliding clips at both sides of the lap,</li>
							</ol>
						</li>
						<li key="4.5.2.e">When using uncoated galvanized steel, zinc, stainless steel or copper flashings, joints shall be riveted or soldered as described in the New Zealand Metal Roof and Wall Cladding Code of Practice,</li>
						<li key="4.5.2.f">When using uncoated or coated lead flashings, maximum continuous lengths shall be 1300 mm for 17 kg or 1500 mm for 20 kg lead. Where the pitch of the flashing is greater than 15° at the join, the lap at the join shall be 100 mm minimum. Where the pitch of the flashing is 15° or less at the join, the lap at the join shall be 200 mm minimum and the flashing underneath the lap shall have a hook at the edge,</li>
						<li key="4.5.2.g">
							<p>Lap joins on other metal flashings shall be sealed using a neutral cure silicone sealant in conjunction with mechanical fasteners. The sealant shall comply with:</p>
							<ol>
								<li key="4.5.2.g.i">Type F, Class 20LM or 25LM of ISO 11600, or</li>
								<li key="4.5.2.g.ii">low modulus Type II Class A of Federal Specification TT-S-00230C.</li>
							</ol>
						</li>
					</ol>
					<figure key="5" keyRef="4.5.1, 4.5.2, 4.6, 6.4, 7.4.4, 9.0, 9.1, 9.6.7" title="Typical metal flashing edge treatments" type="paragraph"/>
					<figure key="6" keyRef="4.5.2, 8.4.11.1, 9.6.7" title="Joints in metal flashings" type="paragraph"/>
					<commentary title="COMMENT:">Further information may be found in the New Zealand Metal Roof and Wall Cladding Code of Practice for joints in metal flashings.</commentary>
				</paragraph>
			</section>
			<section key="4.6" title="Flashing overlaps and upstands">
				<p>Overlaps and upstands to flashings shall be as specified in this paragraph and Table 7, unless specifically shown otherwise. Refer to Paragraph 8.1 to Paragraph 9.9 for requirements for specific claddings. Flashing edges, with hooks, hems, kick-outs and bird's beaks shall be as required in Table 7 and Paragraph 4.5.1. Where a turn-down to the cover flashing for profiled metal claddings is required, use:</p>
				<ol>
					<li key="4.6.a">A soft edge flashing for corrugated profiles, or</li>
					<li key="4.6.b">A notched turn-down or soft edge flashing for trapezoidal profiles with rib height not exceeding 30 mm and/or rib centres not exceeding 200 mm, or</li>
					<li key="4.6.c">A notched turn-down for trapezoidal profiles with rib height exceeding 30 mm and/or rib centres exceeding 200 mm, or</li>
					<li key="4.6.d">A notched turn-down for trough profiles.</li>
				</ol>
				<p>Where a notched turn-down is used there shall be a gap between the edge of the flashing and the pan of the roof cladding. The gap shall be a maximum of 5 mm.</p>
				<paragraph key="4.6.1" title="Overlap with roof claddings">
					<subparagraph key="4.6.1.1" title="Apron flashing cover over metal roofing">
						<ol>
							<li key="4.6.1.1.a">
								<p>Transverse flashing: Refer to Figure 7 for example of use. The apron shall have:</p>
								<ol>
									<li key="4.6.1.1.a.i">for notched turn-downs, a gap between the flashing and the pan of the roof cladding. The gap shall be a maximum of 5 mm, and</li>
									<li key="4.6.1.1.a.ii">a minimum effective cover to roof cladding, excluding any soft edge or turn-down to the flashing, as shown in Table 7.</li>
								</ol>
							</li>
							<li key="4.6.1.1.b">
								<p>Parallel flashing: Refer to Figure 48 for example of use. The apron shall:</p>
								<ol>
									<li key="4.6.1.1.b.i">be dimensioned to suit the roof cladding profile,</li>
									<li key="4.6.1.1.b.ii">for profiled metal roof cladding, cover at least two crests, (turned-up edge to full crest height constitutes a crest), and</li>
									<li key="4.6.1.1.b.iii">for profiled metal roof cladding, overhang flashing a minimum 10 mm clear of crest and maximum 5 mm clear of trough as shown in Figure 47.</li>
								</ol>
							</li>
						</ol>
					</subparagraph>
					<subparagraph key="4.6.1.2" title="Ridges and hips">
						<p>Refer to Figure 46 for example of use.</p>
						<ol>
							<li key="4.6.1.2.a">For notched turn-downs of the flashing leave a gap between the flashing and the roof cladding. The gap shall be a maximum of 5 mm.</li>
							<li key="4.6.1.2.b">There shall be a minimum effective cover to roof cladding, excluding any soft edge or turn-down to the flashing, in accordance with Table 7.</li>
						</ol>
					</subparagraph>
					<subparagraph key="4.6.1.3" title="Change in metal roof pitches">
						<p>Refer to Figure 44 for example of use.</p>
						<ol>
							<li key="4.6.1.3.a">There shall be a minimum effective lap under roof cladding in accordance with Table 7, with a hem at upper edge.</li>
							<li key="4.6.1.3.b">The apron cover over the roof cladding shall be in accordance with Table 7.</li>
						</ol>
					</subparagraph>
					<subparagraph key="4.6.1.4" title="Roof- or deck-to-wall junctions">
						<p>Refer to Figure 7 for example of use.</p>
						<ol>
							<li key="4.6.1.4.a">
								<p>There shall be a total minimum upstand height of 110 mm, in accordance with Table 7, comprising a minimum:</p>
								<ol>
									<li key="4.6.1.4.i">overlap cover of cladding to the flashing upstand of 75 mm, and</li>
									<li key="4.6.1.4.ii">35 mm clearance from bottom of the wall cladding to roof cladding or finished deck material.</li>
								</ol>
							</li>
						</ol>
					</subparagraph>
					<Rules key="7" title="Metal flashings – general dimensions"/>
					<figure key="7" keyRef="4.6.1.1, 4.6.1.4, 5.1, 8.3.8, 7" title="Basic apron flashing" type="paragraph, paragraph, paragraph, paragraph, table"/>
					<subparagraph key="4.6.1.5" title="Barges">
						<p>Refer to Figure 47 for example of use.</p>
						<ol>
							<li key="4.6.1.5.a">There shall be a minimum effective overlap to the barge board, excluding the drip edge to the flashing, in accordance with Table 7.</li>
							<li key="4.6.1.5.b">The apron cover over the roof cladding shall be as for Paragraph 4.6.1.1.</li>
						</ol>
					</subparagraph>
					<subparagraph key="4.6.1.6" title="Window and door heads">
						<p>Refer to Figures 71 and 81 for example of use.</p>
						<ol>
							<li key="4.6.1.6.a">Slopes and covers of flashings at window and door heads shall comply with Table 7.</li>
							<li key="4.6.1.6.b">Overlap cover of cladding to the flashing upstand and clearance from the bottom of the cladding to top of head flashing slope shall be in accordance with Table 7.</li>
							<li key="4.6.1.6.c">Details for door heads shall be based on those applying to windows.</li>
						</ol>
					</subparagraph>
					<subparagraph key="4.6.1.7" title="Inter-storey junctions">
						<p>Refer to Paragraph 9.1.9.4 and Figure 70.</p>
						<ol>
							<li key="4.6.1.7.a">Minimum slopes and covers of flashings shall be in accordance with Table 7.</li>
							<li key="4.6.1.7.b">Overlap cover of the cladding to the flashing upstand, and clearance from the bottom of the cladding to the top of the slope of the head flashing, shall be in accordance with Table 7.</li>
						</ol>
					</subparagraph>
				</paragraph>
			</section>
		</part>
		<part key="5.0" title="Roof/Wall Junctions">
			<paragraph key="5.1" title="Apron flashings">
				<p>Refer Paragraph 4.3 for acceptable apron flashing materials. All roof-to-wall junctions shall be made weathertight by using an apron flashing as outlined in Paragraph 4.6.1.1, and shown in Figure 7, that:</p>
				<ol>
					<li key="5.1.a">
						<p>Provides a minimum lap under the wall cladding of 75 mm in accordance with Table 7, except that:</p>
						<ol>
							<li key="5.1.a.i">pressed metal tiles shall have a flashing fitted to achieve the minimum required overlap of wall cladding, as shown in Figure 35,</li>
						</ol>
					</li>
					<li key="5.1.b">For profiled metal, incorporates stopends at the upper end of the roof cladding as per Paragraph 8.4.13,</li>
					<li key="5.1.c">Provides a minimum clearance from the wall cladding to the roofing in accordance with Table 7, and</li>
					<li key="5.1.d">
						<p>Extends over the roofing by a minimum cover in accordance with Paragraph 4.6.1.1 and Table 7, depending on the:</p>
						<ol>
							<li key="5.1.d.i">wind zone and,</li>
							<li key="5.1.d.ii">pitch of the roof</li>
						</ol>
					</li>
				</ol>
				<commentary title="COMMENT:">40 mm is the maximum upturn achievable with pressed metal tiles, meaning that a flashing is required.</commentary>
				<p>Details for specific wall cladding systems are given in Paragraph 9.0. Where the roof finishes within the length of an adjacent wall, a kick-out or stopend as detailed in Figure 8B shall be provided to direct water out from the wall cladding onto the roof cladding and gutter.</p>
				<figure key="8A" keyRef="5.3, 8.1.3.1, 8.4.6, 9.7.5, 9.8.6" title="Soffit/wall junction" type="paragraph"/>
				<figure key="8B" keyRef="5.1, 5.2" title="Gutter/wall junction" type="paragraph"/>
			</paragraph>
			<paragraph key="5.2" title="Gutters, barges and fascias">
				<p>Where eaves gutters/spoutings, barges or fascias terminate against claddings, these shall be installed after the wall cladding, and after any protective finishes have been applied. Eaves gutters/spouting, barges and fascias shall terminate so as to leave a gap of 10 mm from the finished wall cladding as shown in Figure 8B.</p>
				<commentary title="COMMENT:">It is important to ensure the wall cladding behind eaves gutters/spoutings, barges and fascias is protected by the surface coating to prevent moisture penetration through the unsealed cladding.</commentary>
			</paragraph>
			<paragraph key="5.3" title="Soffits">
				<p>Eaves shall be enclosed by installing soffit linings direct fixed to framing and comprising minimum 4.5 mm fibre cement sheet, or 7 mm H3 plywood, with joints, fixings and finishes as shown in Paragraphs 9.7 and 9.8. Soffit linings shall be finished to fascias, barges and wall claddings as outlined in Figure 8A generally, or Figure 114 for flush finished fibre cement. Wall underlays shall not be required behind soffit linings.</p>
			</paragraph>
		</part>
		<part key="6.0" title="Parapets">
			<p>Parapets require a drained cavity for claddings except for vertical corrugated steel as outlined in Table 3. Refer also to Paragraph 7.4 Enclosed balustrades.</p>
			<commentary title="COMMENT:">Vertical corrugated profiled metal is considered to have drainage capabilities the equivalent of drained cavities.</commentary>
			<section key="6.1" title="Limitations">
				<p>This Acceptable Solution does not cover parapet cappings that use stucco, EIFS and flush-finished fibre cement materials.</p>
			</section>
			<section key="6.2" title="General">
				<p>Parapets shall be constructed as shown in Figure 10, and shall comply with the following requirements:</p>
				<ol>
					<li key="6.2.a">Timber for framing and cavity battens shall comply with B2/AS1,</li>
					<li key="6.2.b">Sloped packers under cappings shall be polystyrene or timber treated to B2/AS1, or minimum 9 mm H3 plywood on packers, and</li>
					<li key="6.2.c">Framing shall be fully enclosed with wall underlay or roof underlay, in accordance with Table 23 for the specific cladding.</li>
					<li key="6.2.d">claddings shall be installed over a cavity in accordance with Paragraph 9.1.8.</li>
				</ol>
				<p>Details for specific wall cladding systems are given in Paragraph 9.0. Specific requirements for enclosed balustrades are given in Paragraph 7.4.</p>
			</section>
			<section key="6.3" title="Capping materials">
				<p>Parapets shall be capped with metal, butyl or EPDM membrane. Cappings shall comply with the requirements of Paragraph 4.0.</p>
			</section>
			<figure key="9" keyRef="6.3, 6.4, 7.4.4, 9.8.7, 9.9, 10.2" title="General capping joints for parapets and enclosed balustrades" type="paragraph"/>
			<figure key="10" keyRef="6.0, 6.2, 6.4, 7.4, 9.7.7.1, 12, 13, 117, 129, 130" title="General construction of parapet and enclosed balustrade" type="paragraph, paragraph, paragraph, paragraph, paragraph, figure, figure, figure, figure, figure"/>
			<section key="6.4" title="Metal cappings">
				<p>Metal cappings installed over parapets and enclosed balustrades, shall be as outlined in Paragraphs 6.0 and 7.4, and comply with the following requirements:</p>
				<ol>
					<li key="6.4.a">Tops of cappings shall be free of any penetrations,</li>
					<li key="6.4.b">Slope of top shall be 5° (1:12) minimum,</li>
					<li key="6.4.c">The cover at the sides of the capping shall be in accordance with Table 7,</li>
					<li key="6.4.d">All cappings shall have drip edges. The details shown in Figure 5 are acceptable minimum drip edges for parapets,</li>
					<li key="6.4.e">Cappings shall be separated from underlying timber by roof underlay as shown in Figure 10,</li>
					<li key="6.4.f">Lengths of capping shall be joined as shown in Figure 9 (b) or Figure 9 (d),</li>
					<li key="6.4.g">External corners of cappings shall be as shown in Figure 9 (e),</li>
					<li key="6.4.h">
						<p>Expansion joints shall be provided for joined cappings with a combined length exceeding:</p>
						<ol>
							<li key="6.4.h.i">12 metres for light coloured steel and stainless steel, 8 metres for dark coloured steel</li>
							<li key="6.4.h.ii">8 metres for copper</li>
							<li key="6.4.h.iii">8 metres for aluminium.</li>
						</ol>
					</li>
					<li key="6.4.i">Where both ends of a capping are constrained, allowance shall be made for expansion, and</li>
					<li key="6.4.j">
						<p>Where necessary, expansion joints shall be formed as shown in Figure 9 (g), and with:</p>
						<ol>
							<li key="6.4.j.i">minimum 200 mm laps</li>
							<li key="6.4.j.ii">sliding clips at both sides of the lap.</li>
						</ol>
					</li>
				</ol>
				<p>Any textured coating application, except for the finished coat, over flush-finished cladding shall be completed prior to the installation of metal cappings.</p>
				<paragraph key="6.4.1" title="Parapet-to-wall junctions">
					<p>Junctions of parapets to walls shall be flashed to direct water clear of the outside face of the cladding system, using a saddle flashing as shown in Figure 11 and Figure 12. Parapets that are continuous and in-plane with adjacent wall surfaces are outside the scope of this Acceptable Solution. An offset in wall line between parapet and adjacent wall is required as in Figures 11 and 12.</p>
					<commentary title="COMMENT:">Reports on leaky buildings show these junctions have been prone to leakage and care must be taken to detail and build them correctly. In-plane junctions require specific design of flashing arrangements.</commentary>
				</paragraph>
			</section>
			<section key="6.5" title="Membrane cappings">
				<p>Butyl rubber and EPDM cappings shall be in accordance with Paragraph 4.3.9, and comply with the following requirements:</p>
				<ol>
					<li key="6.5.a">Tops of membrane cappings shall be free of any penetrations, and shall have a minimum slope of 10° (1:6),</li>
					<li key="6.5.b">Sides of membrane cappings shall overlap the wall claddings as outlined in Table 7, and</li>
					<li key="6.5.c">Joints shall be in accordance with Paragraph 8.5.5.2.</li>
				</ol>
			</section>
			<section key="6.6" title="Integral surface cappings">
				<p>Cappings formed by using stucco, EIFS and flush-finished fibre cement materials shall not be used for parapets, (but may be used for enclosed balustrades as described in Paragraph 7.4).</p>
				<commentary title="COMMENT:">The tops to parapets are considered to be more risky locations than the tops to enclosed balustrades, as they are less accessible for inspection and regular maintenance.</commentary>
				<figure key="11" keyRef="6.4.1, 7.4.2, 7.4.4.1, 7.4.4.2, 10, 12, 117, 129, 130" title="Parapet/enclosed balustrade-to-wall junctions - plan section" type="paragraph, paragraph, paragraph, paragraph, figure, figure, figure, figure, figure"/>
				<figure key="12" keyRef="6.4.1, 7.4.2, 7.4.4.1, 7.4.4.2, 9.9.10.1, 10, 12, 117, 129, 130" title="General junction of parapet and enclosed balustrade to wall" type="paragraph, paragraph, paragraph, paragraph, paragraph, figure, figure, figure, figure, figure"/>
				<p>Figure 13 deleted</p>
				<figure key="14" keyRef="7.1, 7.3, 8.5.6, 17A, 56, 62, 64" title="Threshold separations" type="paragraph, paragraph, paragraph, figure, figure, figure, figure"/>
			</section>
		</part>
		<part key="7.0" title="Decks and Pergolas">
			<p>Timber used to construct decks, enclosed balustrades and other attachments such as pergolas shall comply with B2/AS1.</p>
			<section key="7.1" title="Thresholds for decks">
				<p>The vertical separation between the opening threshold level and the upper surface of the deck shall be as shown in Figure 14. Opening threshold level may be at or above floor level.</p>
				<paragraph key="7.1.1" title="Slatted decks">
					<p>The level of the upper surface of the slatted deck:</p>
					<ol>
						<li key="7.1.1.a">Shall be a minimum of 50 mm below the threshold level for cantilevereddecks  as shown in Figures 14(b) and 16, or</li>
						<li key="7.1.1.b">May be at the same level as the threshold for non-cantilevered decks that are formed as shown in Figure 14(c).</li>
					</ol>
					<p>For slatted decks, a minimum gap of 12 mm shall be provided between the exterior wall and the adjacent decking slat.</p>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="7.1.2" title="Enclosed decks">
					<p>This Acceptable Solution is limited to enclosed decks with a maximum area of 40 m2. For encloseddecks, the vertical separation between the opening threshold level and the upper surface of the finished deck surface shall be a minimum of 100 mm.</p>
				</paragraph>
			</section>
			<section key="7.2" title="Attachment to building structure">
				<paragraph key="7.2.1" title="Slatted timber decks to walls">
					<p>Junctions of slatted timber decks with walls shall be made weathertight as shown in Figures 15 and 16. Fixings for stringers shall be in accordance with NZS 3604.</p>
					<commentary title="COMMENT:">Separating decks from buildings reduces the risk of water penetration into the framing.</commentary>
					<figure key="15" keyRef="7.1.1, 7.2.2, 14" title="Junction with wall for non-cantilevered timber deck" type="paragraph, paragraph, figure"/>
					<p>Wall claddings that rely on surface coatings to reduce water absorption shall be sealed on outer faces and edges prior to fixing the stringers.</p>
					<subparagraph key="7.2.1.1" title="Cantilevered decks">
						<p>Cantilevered decks shall have the junction with the exterior wall made weathertight as shown in Figure 16. Cladding shall be sealed to the saddle flashing.</p>
					</subparagraph>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="7.2.2" title="Pergolas">
					<p>Connections of other structures, such as pergolas, shall have the junction with the exterior wall made weathertight by using the deck framing connections shown in Figure 15.</p>
					<figure key="16" keyRef="7.1, 7.2.1.1, 7.3.1, 14" title="Junction with wall for cantilevered timber deck" type="paragraph"/>
				</paragraph>
			</section>
			<section key="7.3" title="Level thresholds">
				<p>Where provision for level access is required, this shall be provided as shown in Figure 17A and Figure 17B.</p>
				<paragraph key="7.3.1" title="Enclosed decks">
					<p>Where provision for level access is required for an enclosed deck, this shall be provided in Figure 17A. The underlying membrane deck surface shall be made weathertight as described in Paragraph 8.5.</p>
					<subparagraph key="7.3.1.1" title="Removable surfaces">
						<p>Raised removable surfaces of tiles, pavers or timber shall be provided over the underlying weathertight enclosed deck surface for cleaning and maintenance, as shown in Figure 17A. A minimum gap of 12 mm shall be provided against the wall or balustrade cladding.</p>
					</subparagraph>
					<subparagraph key="7.3.1.2" title="Timber removable surface">
						<p>Timber decking shall be over framing supported off the deck membrane as shown in Figure 17A, with spacing in accordance with B2/AS1. No fixings shall penetrate the underlying deck membrane.</p>
						<commentary title="COMMENT:">Tiled boards or structural pavers sitting on proprietary supports can be adjusted according to level changes in the underlying deck surface. The pavers or tiled boards are spaced to allow free drainage and the ability to lift the top surface off when necessary. The timber option allows access by fixing the timber decking with stainless steel screws, so they may be removed when necessary.</commentary>
					</subparagraph>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="7.3.2" title="Ground floor level access">
					<p>Where provision for level access is required, this may be provided as shown in Figure 17B, with exterior paving or decking that complies with the access route requirements of D1/AS1.</p>
					<commentary title="COMMENT:">The specific features of a building and its site can have a significant effect on the options available for providing level access at doors. These features include the provision of shelter, prevailing winds and ground levels. Where level access is required, it is highly recommended that the services of a designer experienced in this field be obtained.</commentary>
					<subparagraph key="7.3.2.1" title="Concrete slab">
						<p>Where provision for level access is required from a concrete floor slab to exterior paving, this shall be as shown in Figure 17B with:</p>
						<ol>
							<li key="7.3.2.1.a">
								<p>A channel, together with drainage provisions, across the door opening, with:</p>
								<ol>
									<li key="7.3.2.1.a.i">the width to suit capacity in accordance with E1/AS1,</li>
									<li key="7.3.2.1.a.ii">a minimum depth of 150 mm,</li>
									<li key="7.3.2.1.a.iii">a maximum length of 3700 mm, and</li>
									<li key="7.3.2.1.a.iv">1:200 minimum fall along length of channel towards a drainage outlet,</li>
								</ol>
							</li>
							<li key="7.3.2.1.b">
								<p>Grating, in accordance with Tables 21 and 22, over the channel, that:</p>
								<ol>
									<li key="7.3.2.1.b.i">is supported independently of the door frame,</li>
									<li key="7.3.2.1.b.ii">is removable to allow access for cleaning,</li>
									<li key="7.3.2.1.b.iii">is specifically designed to accommodate imposed loads,</li>
									<li key="7.3.2.1.b.iv">has gaps sized to prevent the wheels of wheel chairs or mobility aids entering or being trapped, and</li>
									<li key="7.3.2.1.b.v">has a continuous gap of 12 mm minimum from door frame and wall cladding, and</li>
								</ol>
							</li>
							<li key="7.3.2.1.c">
								<p>Exterior paving that:</p>
								<ol>
									<li key="7.3.2.1.c.i">has a minimum fall of 1:40 away from the channel for a minimum distance of 1 m,</li>
									<li key="7.3.2.1.c.ii">together with the surrounding paving and ground levels, complies with drainage requirements of E1/AS1.</li>
								</ol>
							</li>
						</ol>
						<commentary title="COMMENT:">The grating support must be specifically detailed to suit the condition of the building and site.</commentary>
					</subparagraph>
					<subparagraph key="7.3.2.2" title="Timber floor">
						<p>Where provision for level access is required from a timber floor structure to the exterior, this may be provided as shown in Figure 17B, with clearances in accordance with Paragraph 9.1.3.</p>
					</subparagraph>
				</paragraph>
				<figure key="17A" keyRef="7.3, 8.5.1, 17B" title="Level thresholds for enclosed decks" type="paragraph, paragraph, figure"/>
				<figure key="17B" keyRef="7.3, 17A" title="Level thresholds for ground level" type="paragraph, figure"/>
				<figure key="17C" keyRef="9.1.10.5, 73C, 85, 86, 91, 99, 116, 128" title="Door sills for cavity construction" type="paragraph, paragraph, figure, figure, figure, figure, figure, figure, figure"/>
				<figure key="17D" keyRef="9.1.10.5, 81, 82, 83, 84, 90, 95, 115" title="Door sills for direct fix" type="paragraph, figure, figure, figure, figure, figure, figure, figure"/>
			</section>
			<section key="7.4" title="Enclosed balustrades">
				<p>Enclosed balustrades require a drained cavity for claddings, except for vertical corrugated steel, as outlined in Table 3, and shall be detailed as required for parapets described in Paragraphs 6 and 9.1.8 and Figures 10, 11 and 12. Details for specific cladding systems are given in Paragraph 9.0. Enclosed balustrade cappings for EIFS and flush finished fibre cement may include flush finishes as outlined in Paragraphs 9.7.7 and 9.9.10.</p>
				<commentary title="COMMENT:">Reports on leaky buildings show these junctions have been prone to leakage and care must be taken to detail and build them correctly.</commentary>
				<paragraph key="7.4.1" title="Deck drainage">
					<p>For decks with enclosed balustrades, provision for drainage shall be in accordance with Paragraph 8.5.6 and Paragraph 8.5.10.</p>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="7.4.2" title="Balustrade-to-wall junctions">
					<p>Enclosed balustrade-to-wall junctions shall be flashed to direct water clear of the outside face of the cladding system using a saddle flashing as shown in Figures 11 and 12.</p>
					<commentary title="COMMENT:">Reports on leaky buildings show that these junctions are prone to leakage and care must be taken in detailing and in building them correctly.</commentary>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="7.4.3" title="Balustrade-to-deck floor junction">
					<p>The junction of the enclosed balustrade with the floor of the enclosed deck shall be made weathertight as shown in Figure 18. Junctions with wall claddings shall be as shown in Figure 62.</p>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="7.4.4" title="Metal cappings">
					<p>Metal cappings to enclosed balustrades shall have dimensions as outlined in Table 7. Metal cappings shall have the same requirements as outlined for parapets in Paragraph 6.4, with the exception of the:</p>
					<ol>
						<li key="7.4.4.a">Slope to the top of the capping, for buildings other than housing to be as in F4/AS1,</li>
						<li key="7.4.4.b">Drip edges are required to both sides of the capping. The drip edge to the deck side of the capping shall be a bird's beak as shown in Figure 5.</li>
					</ol>
					<commentary title="COMMENT:">A bird's beak drip edge will avoid danger of injury resulting from the sharp edge of a kick-out.</commentary>
				</paragraph>
				<figure key="18" keyRef="7.4.3, 9.1.3, 56, 62, 63, 64" title="Enclosed balustrade – bottom of cladding" type="paragraph, paragraph, figure, figure, figure, figure"/>
				<paragraph key="7.4.5" title="Stanchions">
					<p>Stanchions for handrails, signs, television aerials or similar structures shall be side-fixed through the cladding system into framing, as shown in Figure 19. These fixings are not included for stucco, EIFS or profiled metal in this Acceptable Solution. Fixing shall be to vertical surfaces only. The sealant shall be compatible with the washer.</p>
				</paragraph>
				<figure key="19" keyRef="7.4.5" title="Stanchion fixing" type="paragraph"/>
			</section>
		</part>
		<part key="8.0" title="Roof Claddings">
			<section key="8.1" title="General">
				<paragraph key="8.1.1" title="Weathertightness">
					<p>Roof claddings shall meet the requirements of NZBC E2.2, and be specified and constructed in accordance with the provisions of Paragraph 8.1.2 to Paragraph 8.5.</p>
					<commentary title="COMMENT:">For roofs used to collect water for human consumption, refer AS/NZS 4020.</commentary>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="8.1.2" title="Limitations">
					<p>The following roof cladding systems are covered in this Acceptable Solution:</p>
					<ol>
						<li key="8.1.2.a">Masonry tiles Paragraph 8.2</li>
						<li key="8.1.2.b">Pressed metal tiles Paragraph 8.3</li>
						<li key="8.1.2.c">Profiled metal roof claddings Paragraph 8.4</li>
						<li key="8.1.2.d">Membrane roofing Paragraph 8.5.</li>
					</ol>
					<p>Other roof claddings are beyond the scope of this Acceptable Solution.</p>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="8.1.3" title="Maintenance">
					<p>Maintenance of claddings shall be carried out as necessary to achieve the expected durability of the materials - refer to Paragraph 2.5.</p>
					<commentary title="COMMENT:">A deterioration in the appearance of the coating of the metal does not necessarily relate to a deterioration in the weathertightness of the roof cladding. Care should be taken to avoid post-installation damage to the cladding when accessing the roof. Additional support is required around roof-mounted units such as air-conditioners to avoid roof distortion.</commentary>
					<subparagraph key="8.1.3.1" title="Projecting eaves">
						<p>Soffits and verges of all projecting eaves shall be closed in. Refer to Paragraph 5.3 for details.</p>
					</subparagraph>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="8.1.4" title="Fixings">
					<p>Fixings shall be as specified in Paragraph 8.2 to Paragraph 8.5. Materials for fixing roof claddings and flashings, where necessary, shall be selected from Tables 20, 21 and 22 to minimise corrosion.</p>
					<commentary title="COMMENT:">The use of stainless steel fixings is not recommended by steel manufacturers for use with coated steel in severe marine and industrial environments, as they are considered to cause deterioration.</commentary>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="8.1.5" title="Roof underlays">
					<p>Roof underlays shall be to Table 23 and NZS 2295, and be either:</p>
					<ol>
						<ul>R1 heavy weight kraft, or</ul>
						<ul>R2 self supporting kraft.</ul>
					</ol>
					<p>Underlays shall be:</p>
					<ol>
						<ul>Layed with minimum numbers of laps</ul>
						<ul>Lapped at all side and end laps by minimum 150 mm</ul>
						<ul>Run horizontally for roof pitches below 10°</ul>
						<ul>Run horizontally or vertically for roof pitches above 10°</ul>
						<ul>Have anti-ponding boards at lower edges of masonry tiles, refer Figure 25(b) and Paragraph 8.2.5.</ul>
					</ol>
					<subparagraph key="8.1.5.1" title="Underlay support">
						<p>Prevent sagging of roof underlay by either:</p>
						<ol>
							<ul>For R1 underlays, fully support with a corrosion resistant material</ul>
							<ul>For R2 self supporting underlays, laid to maximum 1.2 metre span between adjacent supports</ul>
						</ol>
						<commentary title="COMMENT:">Solvent in freshly LOSP-treated timber can affect bitumen in underlays. Any solvent should be allowed to evaporate before the roof underlay is installed.</commentary>
					</subparagraph>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="8.1.6" title="Gutters general">
					<p>Gutters, downpipes and spreaders, including eaves gutters/spoutings are required for the drainage of roof water, and shall:</p>
					<ol>
						<li key="8.1.6.a">Be to the minimum dimensions shown in this Acceptable Solution, or calculated to E1/AS1, whichever is the greater</li>
						<li key="8.1.6.b">If a gutter depth is reduced to allow entry of a valley gutter, the reduced depth must be used to calculate the capacity of the gutter</li>
						<li key="8.1.6.c">For internal, valley, and hidden gutters, have no fixings in gutter bottoms or sides, and be continuously supported on H1.2 minimum treated timber gutter boards or H3 ply which is separated from metal by roof underlay strip.</li>
						<p>Eaves gutters/spoutings shall:</p>
						<li key="8.1.6.d">Be to any of the materials outlined for flashings in Paragraph 4.1 except 4.3.9, 4.3.10 and 4.3.11</li>
						<li key="8.1.6.e">Have a minimum cross sectional area of 2500 mm2</li>
						<li key="8.1.6.f">Be designed to overflow water to the outside.</li>
						<p>Downpipes shall:</p>
						<li key="8.1.6.g">Be formed from any of the materials outlined for flashings in Paragraph 4.1 except 4.3.9, 4.3.10 and 4.3.11</li>
						<li key="8.1.6.h">Upper roofs shall drain via downpipes directly to ground level where possible, or</li>
						<li key="8.1.6.i">Where discharging to a lower roof, be fitted with a spreader as detailed in Figure 20</li>
						<li key="8.1.6.j">Have a maximum catchment area of 25 m2</li>
						<p>if discharging on to a lower roof area. Spreaders shall:</p>
						<li key="8.1.6.k">Be to any of the materials outlined for flashings in Paragraph 4.1 except 4.3.9, 4.3.10 and 4.3.11</li>
						<li key="8.1.6.l">Be to Figure 20 and not be used on masonry tile roofs unless a roof underlay is installed</li>
						<li key="8.1.6.m">Discharge directed away from roofing laps and clear of roof penetrations.</li>
					</ol>
					<commentary title="COMMENT:">Design calculations for a specific roof may allow larger catchment areas per spreader to be used. The alternative to a spreader is to direct an upper level downpipe into a rainwater head. The ends of spreaders should be blocked off where a sideways flow of water is against laps in roof claddings.</commentary>
					<subparagraph key="8.1.6.1" title="Internal gutters">
						<p>Internal gutters shall:</p>
						<ol>
							<li key="8.1.6.1.a">Be formed with continuous butyl or EPDM strip complying with Paragraph 4.3.9, with no cross-joints in the gutter, or aluminium, copper, stainless steel, or zinc sheet to Paragraph 4.3, with joints that are welded</li>
							<li key="8.1.6.1.b">Where butyl or EPDM, be minimum 1.5 mm membrane thickness, or 1.0 mm thickness for gutters less than 1 metre wide</li>
							<li key="8.1.6.1.c">Have a minimum slope of 1:100</li>
							<li key="8.1.6.1.d">Be constructed to at least the minimum dimensions shown in Figure 52, or the capacity calculated to E1/AS1 plus an additional freeboard depth of 20 mm minimum.</li>
							<p>For roofs other than membrane roofs:</p>
							<li key="8.1.6.1.e">Discharge into a rainwater head as shown in Figure 63 (a) and (b), or</li>
							<li key="8.1.6.1.f">
								<p>Discharge to an internal outlet to Figure 64 (b) or (c) with overflows provided by either:</p>
								<ol>
									<li key="8.1.6.1.f.i">a second outlet to a rainwater head, or</li>
									<li key="8.1.6.1.f.ii">an overflow as shown in Figure 63(c), and positioned below the level of any potential overflow into the building.</li>
								</ol>
							</li>
						</ol>
						<p>For internal gutters and membrane roofing, refer to Paragraph 8.5.</p>
					</subparagraph>
					<subparagraph key="8.1.6.2" title="Valley gutters and hidden gutters">
						<p>Valley gutters and hidden gutters shall be constructed as shown in Figures 50 and 51 for the applicable roof cladding (except for membrane roofing) and:</p>
						<ol>
							<li key="8.1.6.2.a">Not change direction in plan</li>
							<li key="8.1.6.2.b">Have a minimum underlap to roof cladding as specified in Figures 27, 37, 50, and 51 for the relevant roof cladding</li>
							<li key="8.1.6.2.c">Be formed from any of the materials outlined for flashings in Paragraph 4.3 except 4.3.10 and 4.3.11</li>
							<li key="8.1.6.2.d">Be fixed at upper ends only, and be secured with a purpose-made clip system for the remaining length to enable expansion/ contraction along the length of the gutter</li>
							<li key="8.1.6.2.e">Discharge into an internal gutter or eaves gutter/spouting.</li>
							<p>In addition:</p>
							<li key="8.1.6.2.f">Have minimum slopes of 8° for hidden gutters, and to Table 8 for valley gutters</li>
							<li key="8.1.6.2.g">Hidden gutters receive no discharge from downpipes or spreaders</li>
							<li key="8.1.6.2.h">Spreaders not discharge directly into a valley gutter</li>
							<li key="8.1.6.2.i">Valley gutters be minimum 250 mm wide where receiving run off from spreaders.</li>
						</ol>
						<commentary title="COMMENT:">Gutters for lower-pitched roofs, or for catchment areas other than those shown in Table 8, require specific design. Additional information may be found in the New Zealand Metal Roof and Wall Cladding Code of Practice.</commentary>
					</subparagraph>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="8.1.7" title="Roof penetrations">
					<p>Roof penetrations shall be made weathertight in accordance with Paragraph 8.2 to Paragraph 8.5. Where roof penetrations are required for large openings such as roof lights and chimneys, this Acceptable Solution is limited to the following requirements:</p>
					<ol>
						<li key="8.1.7.a">The edge of roofing penetrations over 200 mm wide shall be supported in either direction with additional framing as shown in Figure 21, and</li>
						<li key="8.1.7.b">
							<p>For the catchment area of the roof above the penetration as shown in Figure 22, the roof length shall be limited to:</p>
							<ol>
								<li key="8.1.7.b.i">for profiled metal roofing, Table 17</li>
								<li key="8.1.7.b.ii">for other roof claddings, the areas shown in Table 9.</li>
							</ol>
						</li>
					</ol>
					<commentary title="COMMENT:">Flashings for roof penetrations not included in this Acceptable Solution require specific design. For pipe penetrations, refer to details for the roof cladding material used.</commentary>
				</paragraph>
				<figure key="21" keyRef="8.1.7, 8.4.17" title="Penetration support" type="paragraph"/>
				<figure key="22" keyRef="8.1.6, 8.1.7, 9, 17 " title="Catchment area for penetrations" type="paragraph, paragraph, table, table"/>
			</section>
			<section key="8.2" title="Masonry Tiles">
				<paragraph key="8.2.1" title="Materials">
					<p>Concrete tiles shall meet the requirements of NZS 4206 or AS 2049. Clay tiles shall meet the requirements of AS 2049.</p>
					<subparagraph key="8.2.1.1" title="Tile profiles">
						<p>For the purposes of this paragraph, tiles shall be divided into three types as listed below:</p>
						<ol>
							<li key="8.2.1.1.a">Type I: Double profile tiles having two distinct watercourses with a minimum watercourse depth of 18 mm,</li>
							<li key="8.2.1.1.b">Type II: Single profile tiles having one water.course depth of a minimum of 25 mm, or</li>
							<li key="8.2.1.1.c">Type III: Tiles not fitting the Type I or Type II categories, and includes flat tiles and those resembling slates, shakes and shingles.</li>
						</ol>
					</subparagraph>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="8.2.2" title="General">
					<commentary title="COMMENT:">Refer to Paragraph 1.5 for qualification of installers.</commentary>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="8.2.3" title="Installation">
					<p>Masonry tile roof cladding shall be installed in accordance with NZS 4206 or AS 2050 onto minimum H1.2 treated timber battens, except the minimum pitch shall be as specified in Table 10. Where required in AS 2050 and Table 20, underlay shall comply with Table 23. Fixing and fixing patterns shall be to NZS 4206, with the exception that nails shall penetrate a minimum of 35 mm into timber battens, and the minimum pitches and roof underlay shall be as described in Table 10 and Table 23. Use 304 or 316 stainless steel fixings for corrosion zones B, C, D and E, or hot dip galvanised fixings at 450 g/m2 for Zone B and Zone C. Refer to Table 20 for corrosion zones.</p>
					<commentary title="COMMENT:">Rafter length, tile profile and wind zone all affect the allowable minimum pitch of a tile roof. Rafters longer than in Table 10 may require the addition of underlay. Manufacturers may have specific profiles that are suitable for pitches lower than those shown in Table 10, but these are outside the scope of this Acceptable Solution.</commentary>
					<p>Where masonry tiles have been shown to comply with the dynamic weathertightness test requirements of AS 4046: Part 9, a lower pitch may be used providing it is not less than 15°.</p>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="8.2.4" title="Flashings and fixings">
					<p>Materials for flashings, gutters and fixings shall be in accordance with Paragraph 4.0, and:</p>
					<ol>
						<li key="8.2.4.a">Be selected from Table 20 to minimise corrosion, and</li>
						<li key="8.2.4.b">Be compatible with mortar and bedding in accordance with Table 21 and Table 22.</li>
					</ol>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="8.2.5" title="Anti-ponding boards">
					<p>Masonry tile roofs with underlays shall have anti-ponding boards installed to Figure 25. Where anti-ponding boards are used, these shall be set to a minimum fall of 5° (1:12), and shall be treated minimum H1.2 for solid timber and H3 for plywood.</p>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="8.2.6" title="Details and flashings">
					<p>Hips, ridges, valleys and barges shall be made weathertight by using flashings and seals as shown in Figure 23 to Figure 28.</p>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="8.2.7" title="Penetrations">
					<p>Penetrations shall be flashed as shown in Figure 29 to Figure 31. Holes in tiles for pipe penetrations shall be machine-cut to minimise the size of the hole.</p>
				</paragraph>
				<figure key="23" keyRef="8.2.6" title="Masonry tile ridge" type="paragraph"/>
				<figure key="24" keyRef="8.2.6" title="Barge for masonry tile" type="paragraph"/>
				<figure key="25" keyRef="8.1.5, 8.2.5" title="Timber fascia eaves for masonry tile" type="paragraph"/>
				<figure key="26" keyRef="8.2.6" title="Apron details for masonry tile" type="paragraph"/>
				<figure key="27" keyRef="8.2.6, 8.1.6.2" title="Valley for masonry tile" type="paragraph"/>
				<figure key="28" keyRef="8.2.6" title="Roof/wall ridge for masonry tile" type="paragraph"/>
				<figure key="29" keyRef="8.2.7" title="Pipe penetration for masonry tile" type="paragraph"/>
				<figure key="30" keyRef="8.2.7, 9, 31" title="Abutment at framed penetration for masonry tile" type="paragraph, table, figure"/>
				<figure key="31" keyRef="8.2.7, 9, 30" title="Flashing to framed penetration for masonry tile" type="paragraph, table, figure"/>
			</section>
			<section key="8.3" title="Pressed Metal Tiles">
				<paragraph key="8.3.1" title="Limitations">
					<p>This Acceptable Solution is limited to pressed metal tile roofs.</p>
					<commentary title="COMMENT:">Additional guidance on pressed metal tiles can be found in the New Zealand Metal Roof and Wall Cladding Code of Practice.</commentary>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="8.3.2" title="Installation">
					<commentary title="COMMENT:">Refer to Paragraph 1.5 for qualification of installers.</commentary>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="8.3.3" title="Tiles and accessories">
					<p>Tiles and their accessories shall meet the requirements of NZS 4217.</p>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="8.3.4" title="Metal substrate">
					<subparagraph key="8.3.4.1" title="Choice of metal">
						<commentary title="COMMENT:">The exposure zone in which a building is located can affect the durability of flashings. Exposure zones are defined in NZS 3604, based on the likely exposure to wind-driven sea-salt. Corrosion due to geothermal or corrosive industrial atmospheres, as defined in NZS 3604, require specific design. Exposure zones are based on AS/NZS 2728. AS/NZS 2728 lists atmospheric classes derived from ISO 9223 for Australia and New Zealand.</commentary>
					</subparagraph>
					<subparagraph key="8.3.4.2" title="Steel">
						<p>Steel for the manufacture of pressed metal tile and flashing systems shall:</p>
						<ol>
							<li key="8.3.4.2.a">have a base metal thickness (BMT) of 0.39 mm minimum,</li>
							<li key="8.3.4.2.b">be grade G300 or G250,</li>
							<li key="8.3.4.2.c">be selected for corrosion protection according to the intended exposure zone as shown in Table 20.</li>
						</ol>
						<p>Paint coatings may include factory-applied finishes complying with AS/NZS 2728, or factory-painted or bonded resin and chip finishes of minimum 15 year durability.</p>
					</subparagraph>
					<subparagraph key="8.3.4.3" title="Aluminium">
						<p>Aluminium for the manufacture of pressed metal tiles and flashing systems shall comply with AS/NZS 1734, and shall:</p>
						<ol>
							<li key="8.3.4.3.a">Have a base metal thickness (BMT) of 0.7 mm minimum,</li>
							<li key="8.3.4.3.b">Be minimum 5000 series,</li>
							<li key="8.3.4.3.c">For pre-painted aluminium, have a factory-applied finish complying with AS/NZS 2728.</li>
						</ol>
					</subparagraph>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="8.3.5" title="Roof pitch">
					<p>General approximations of profile types for standard profile and shake or shingle profile metal roof tiles are shown in Figure 32.</p>
					<p>The minimum roof pitches for metal tiles where rafter length does not exceed 12 m shall be limited to:</p>
					<ol>
						<li key="8.3.5.a">12° (1:4.75) for profiles resembling standard profiles, and</li>
						<li key="8.3.5.b">15° (1:3.75) for profiles resembling shingle or shake profiles.</li>
					</ol>
					<p>Where rafter length exceeds 12 m, increase minimum pitch by 1° per additional 0.5 m.</p>
					<figure key="32" keyRef="8.3.5" title="Metal tile profiles" type="paragraph"/>
					<commentary title="COMMENT:">Panels are available in a wide range of profiles. Where manufacturers have more stringent requirements, these should be followed to optimise performance and to avoid invalidating guarantees.</commentary>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="8.3.6" title="Underlay">
					<p>All metal tile roofing shall have a roof underlay installed. Roof underlay shall be to Table 23. Refer to Paragraph 8.1.5 for installation details.</p>
					<p>If LOSP-treated timber is used, roof underlay shall not be applied until the LOSP solvent has been allowed to evaporate.</p>
					<commentary title="COMMENT:">Solvent in freshly LOSP-treated timber can affect bitumen in underlays. Any solvent should be allowed to evaporate before the roof underlay is installed.</commentary>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="8.3.7" title="Fixings">
					<p>Pressed metal tiles shall be fixed as shown in Figure 33, with:</p>
					<ol>
						<li key="8.3.7.a">50 x 2.8 mm hot-dipped galvanized painted flat-head annular-grooved nails. For fixings through the top of the tiles, use neoprene washers containing no more than 15% by weight carbon black content, with</li>
						<li key="8.3.7.b">
							<p>Four fixings per sheet through:</p>
							<ol>
								<li key="8.3.7.b.i">the turn-down of the tiles for the body of the roof, and</li>
								<li key="8.3.7.b.ii">the top of the profile slope for sheets at the eaves, avoiding the weather channel of the tiles.</li>
							</ol>
						</li>
					</ol>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="8.3.8" title="Flashings">
					<p>The roof shall be flashed at all boundaries, except at the discharge to a gutter, using the details shown in Figure 34 to Figure 37.</p>
					<p>Metal flashings are generally supplied by the metal tile manufacturer, and shall comply with Paragraph 8.3.4.2 and Table 7, unless specifically shown otherwise in the details.</p>
					<commentary title="COMMENT:">Metal tile manufacturers supply pre-folded or formed accessories and recommendations for their installation.</commentary>
					<figure key="33" keyRef="8.3.7" title="Metal tile fixings" type="paragraph"/>
					<figure key="34" keyRef="8.3.3, 8.3.8" title="Ridge or hip flashings for metal tile" type="paragraph"/>
					<figure key="35" keyRef="8.3.3, 8.3.8" title="Apron flashings for metal tile" type="paragraph"/>
					<figure key="36" keyRef="8.3.3, 8.3.8" title="Eaves and barge for metal tile" type="paragraph"/>
					<figure key="37" keyRef="8.1.6.2, 8.3.3, 8.3.8, 51 " title="Hidden and valley gutter flashings for metal tile" type="paragraph, paragraph, paragraph, figure"/>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="8.3.9" title="Gutters, ridges, barges and fascias">
					<p>Gutters, ridges, barges and fascias shall be as shown in Figures 34-37. Refer to Paragraph 5.2 for termination of roofs against wall claddings.</p>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="8.3.10" title="Roof penetrations">
					<p>Pipe penetrations shall be flashed using EPDM flashings similar to that shown for masonry tiles, Figure 29.</p>
					<commentary title="COMMENT:">Use purpose-made preformed rooflights and ventilators supplied by the manufacturer of the tiles where available.</commentary>
				</paragraph>
			</section>
			<section key="8.4" title="Profiled Metal Roof Cladding">
				<paragraph key="8.4.1" title="Limitations">
					<p>This Acceptable Solution is limited to the following types of profiled metal roof cladding:</p>
					<ol>
						<li key="8.4.1.a">Profiled as outlined in Paragraph 8.4.4,</li>
						<li key="8.4.1.b">Valley gutters that do not change direction in plan,</li>
						<li key="8.4.1.c">Not curved, and</li>
						<li key="8.4.1.d">With sheets no more than 18 metres long.</li>
					</ol>
					<commentary title="COMMENT:">If curved profiled metal sheet is used, the radius of the curve may affect durability. Specific design is required, and manufacturers and the New Zealand Metal Roof and Wall Cladding Code of Practice should be consulted for recommendations.</commentary>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="8.4.2" title="General">
					<commentary title="COMMENT:">Refer to Paragraph 1.5 for qualification of installers.</commentary>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="8.4.3" title="Materials">
					<subparagraph key="8.4.3.1" title="Choice of metal">
						<p>Metal roof cladding and flashings shall be selected according to the exposure conditions in Table 20 as defined in:</p>
						<ol>
							<li key="8.4.3.1.a">NZS 3604, or</li>
							<li key="8.4.3.1.b">AS/NZS 2728.</li>
						</ol>
						<commentary title="COMMENT:">The exposure zone in which a building is located can affect the durability of flashings. Exposure zones are defined in NZS 3604, based on the likely exposure to wind-driven sea-salt. Corrosion due to geothermal or corrosive industrial atmospheres, as defined in NZS 3604, require specific design. Exposure zones are based on AS/NZS 2728. AS/NZS 2728 lists atmospheric classes derived from ISO 9223 for Australia and New Zealand.</commentary>
					</subparagraph>
					<subparagraph key="8.4.3.2" title="Steel">
						<p>Materials for the manufacture of profiled steel roof cladding shall:</p>
						<ol>
							<li key="8.4.3.2.a">have a BMT of 0.4 mm minimum</li>
							<li key="8.4.3.2.b">be grade G550, or G300 for rolled, crimped, or trough profile roofing</li>
							<li key="8.4.3.2.c">be selected for corrosion protection according to the intended exposure zone as shown in Table 20.</li>
						</ol>
					</subparagraph>
					<subparagraph key="8.4.3.3" title="Aluminium">
						<p>Aluminium for the manufacture of profiled aluminium roofing shall comply with AS/NZS 1734, and be a minimum:</p>
						<ol>
							<li key="8.4.3.3.a">Base metal thickness (BMT) of 0.7 mm,</li>
							<li key="8.4.3.3.b">5000 series.</li>
						</ol>
						<p>Pre-painted aluminium roofing shall have a factory-applied finish complying with AS/NZS 2728.</p>
						<commentary title="COMMENT:">A deterioration in the appearance of the coating of the metal does not necessarily relate to a deterioration in the weathertightness of the roof cladding.</commentary>
					</subparagraph>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="8.4.4" title="Profiles">
					<p>Profiles covered in this Acceptable Solution are shown in Figure 38, and consist of:</p>
					<ol>
						<li key="8.4.4.a">Corrugated - curved with a crest height of 16.5 mm minimum,</li>
						<li key="8.4.4.b">Trapezoidal - symmetrical or asymmetrical with a minimum crest height of 19 mm, and for asymmetrical a flat or lightly profiled pan width of 210 mm maximum between crests, and</li>
						<li key="8.4.4.c">Trough profile - with vertical ribs at a minimum height of 38 mm, and flat or lightly profiled pans of 210 mm maximum between crests.</li>
					</ol>
					<figure key="38" keyRef="8.4.4, 9.6.1, 9.6.5, 3" title="Profiled metal profiles" type="paragraph, paragraph, paragraph, table"/>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="8.4.5" title="Roof pitch">
					<p>For roofs up to 18 metres in length without end laps, pitches shall be:</p>
					<ol>
						<li key="8.4.5.a">Corrugated - not less than 8° (1:7).</li>
						<li key="8.4.5.b">
							<p>Trapezoidal - not less than:</p>
							<ol>
								<li key="8.4.5.b.i">4° (1:14) where the crest height is less than 27 mm, or</li>
								<li key="8.4.5.b.ii">3° (1:20) where the crest height is 27 mm or higher.</li>
							</ol>
						</li>
						<li key="8.4.5.c">Trough profile - not less than 3° (1:20).</li>
					</ol>
					<commentary title="COMMENT:">For roofs over 18 metres in length refer to the manufacturer for minimum pitch requirements. Where manufacturers have more stringent requirements, these should be followed to optimise performance and to avoid invalidating guarantees.</commentary>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="8.4.6" title="Structure">
					<p>The maximum span and fixing patterns of profiled metal roof cladding between purlins to comply with this Acceptable Solution are given in Table 11, Table 12 or Table 13, 14 and 15. Spans shown are for steel with BMT, grade and profile as specified in each Table.</p>
					<commentary title="COMMENT:">For purlin sizes, spacing and fixing, refer to NZS 3604. Additional support will be required around roof-mounted services such as air-conditioning in order to avoid roof distortion.</commentary>
					<commentary title="COMMENT:">It is recommended that access to the roof is limited to within 100 mm of purlin lines to avoid damaging the roof cladding.</commentary>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="8.4.7" title="Underlay">
					<p>All profiled metal long-run roofing shall have a roof underlay installed to Table 23. See Paragraph 8.1.5 for installation details.</p>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="8.4.8" title="Fixings: corrugated and trapezoidal">
					<p>Fixings shall be as shown in Tables 11, 12, 14 and 15, and shall be a minimum 12-gauge screw, as shown in Figure 39, which complies with Class 4 of AS 3566: Part 2.</p>
					<commentary title="COMMENT:">Screw fixing is recommended for metal roofing as there is less likelihood of the fixing ‘backing out’ than with a nail. The spacing requirements for fixings are conservative, and a specific design may produce a more optimum spacing, especially with the use of load-spreading washers. Consult roofing manufacturers for information.</commentary>
					<subparagraph key="8.4.8.1" title="Fixing requirements">
						<p>Fixings shall:</p>
						<ol>
							<li key="8.4.8.1.a">Be fixed through crests,</li>
							<li key="8.4.8.1.b">Penetrate purlins by a minimum of 40 mm for nail fixings and 30 mm for screw fixings,</li>
							<li key="8.4.8.1.c">
								<p>Include sealing washers of:</p>
								<ol>
									<li key="8.4.8.1.c.i">neoprene (having a carbon black content of 15% or less by weight),</li>
									<li key="8.4.8.1.c.ii">profiled washer and EPDM washer where required to allow for expansion of the profiled metal roof cladding.</li>
								</ol>
							</li>
						</ol>
					</subparagraph>
					<figure key="39" keyRef="8.4.8, 9.6.6, 20, 22, 24" title="Corrugated and trapezoidal fixings and sheet lap" type="paragraph, paragraph, table, table, table"/>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="8.4.9" title="Fixings: trough profile">
					<p>Clip fixings for trough profiles and spans as shown in Table 13 shall be as shown in Figure 40, and shall:</p>
					<ol>
						<li key="8.4.9.a">Have a minimum BMT of 0.9 mm</li>
						<li key="8.4.9.b">Be a minimum width of 30 mm</li>
						<li key="8.4.9.c">Be made from a material compatible with the cladding, refer to Tables 20 and 21 </li>
						<li key="8.4.9.d">Have clips fastened with a minimum of two 10-gauge by 30 mm waferhead hot-dipped galvanised screws which comply with Class 3 of AS 3566: Part 2.</li>
					</ol>
				</paragraph>
				<figure key="40" keyRef="8.4.9" title="Typical trough profile fixings" type="paragraph"/>
				<paragraph key="8.4.10" title="Allowance for expansion">
					<p>Allowance shall be made for expansion of corrugated and trapezoidal roof cladding as shown in Table 16.</p>
					<p>Where Table 16 requires profiled washers, allowance shall be made for expansion by:</p>
					<ol>
						<li key="8.4.10.a">Fixing the top 50% (closest to the ridge) with conventional fixings, and</li>
						<li key="8.4.10.b">
							<p>Fixing the lower 50% with sealing washers fixed over profiled washers as shown in Figure 39, and:</p>
							<ol>
								<li key="8.4.10.b.i">using oversized holes, and</li>
								<li key="8.4.10.b.ii">positioning fixing in centre of hole.</li>
							</ol>
						</li>
					</ol>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="8.4.11" title="Flashing requirements">
					<p>The roofing shall be flashed at all boundaries to comply with the following:</p>
					<li key="8.4.11.a">At edges discharging to gutters with eaves flashings where required in Figure 45(a)</li>
					<li key="8.4.11.b">Soft edge to cover flashings complying with Paragraph 4.6. Refer to Figure 41 for example of use and Tables 21 and 22.</li>
					<li key="8.4.11.c">Notched turn-downs to cover flashings shall comply with Paragraph 4.6. Refer to Figure 42 for example of use.</li>
					<li key="8.4.11.d">Materials for flashings shall be compatible with the roof cladding material as per Table 21 and Table 22, and shall be in accordance with Paragraph 4.3.</li>
					<li key="8.4.11.e">Provide expansion joints in accordance with Paragraph 4.5.2.</li>
					<subparagraph key="8.4.11.1" title="Fixing flashings">
						<li key="8.4.11.1.a">When fixing flashings to the structure, use screws as for roofing (see Paragraph 8.4.8).</li>
						<li key="8.4.11.1.b">
							<p>When fixing flashings to other flashings or to roofing use:</p>
							<ol>
								<li key="8.4.11.b.i">for galvanized steel, 4 mm diameter monel metal or stainless steel rivets, where compatible as per Table 21,</li>
								<li key="8.4.11.b.ii">for aluminium-zinc coated steel, 4 mm diameter aluminium rivets,</li>
								<li key="8.4.11.b.iii">for aluminium, 4 mm diameter aluminium rivets.</li>
							</ol>
						</li>
						<commentary title="COMMENT:">The use of stainless steel fixings is not recommended by steel manufacturers for use with coated steel, in severe marine and industrial environments, as they are considered to cause deterioration.</commentary>
						<li key="8.4.11.c">Flashing joins, including expansion joints where required, shall be in accordance with Paragraph 4.5.2 and as shown in Figure 6.</li>
						<li key="8.4.11.d">
							<p>Where end-laps are required in flashings, form these as shown in Figure 6 and, before joining the two parts, apply an 8 mm diameter bead of neutral cure sealant complying with:</p>
							<ol>
								<li key="8.4.11.d.i">Type F, Class 20LM or 25LM of ISO 11600, or</li>
								<li key="8.4.11.d.ii">low modulus Type II Class A of Federal Specification TT-S-00230C.</li>
							</ol>
						</li>
					</subparagraph>
					<figure key="41" keyRef="4.6, 8.4.12, 8.4.11" title="Soft edge flashing" type="paragraph"/>
					<figure key="42" keyRef="4.5, 8.4.11, 8.4.12" title="Trapezoidal notched flashing" type="paragraph"/>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="8.4.12" title="Flashing details">
					<p>The roof shall be flashed using details shown below:</p>
					<ol>
						<li key="8.4.12.a">Ridge to hip as shown in Figure 43,</li>
						<li key="8.4.12.b">Apron flashing and change in pitch as shown in Figure 44,</li>
						<li key="8.4.12.c">Eaves and roof/wall ridge as shown in Figure 45,</li>
						<li key="8.4.12.d">Eaves flashing as in Figure 45(a) required for all roofs under 10¼ pitch and soffit widths less than 100 mm,</li>
						<li key="8.4.12.e">Ridge and hip as shown in Figure 46,</li>
						<li key="8.4.12.f">Barge flashings as shown in Figure 47,</li>
						<li key="8.4.12.g">Apron flashing - parallel flashing to profile as shown in Figure 48.</li>
					</ol>
					<commentary title="COMMENT:">Reduced cover for barge and apron flashings may be applicable for specifically designed roofs in low wind zones. Refer to the New Zealand Metal Roof and Wall Cladding Code of Practice for additional guidance on ridge to hip flashings.</commentary>
					<figure key="43" keyRef="8.4.11, 8.4.12" title="Ridge to hip flashings" type="paragraph"/>
					<figure key="44" keyRef="4.5, 8.4.11, 8.4.12, 7" title="Apron flashing and change in pitch for profiled metal" type="paragraph, paragraph, paragraph, table"/>
					<figure key="45" keyRef="4.5, 8.4.11, 8.4.12, 7" title="Eaves and roof/wall ridge for profiled metal" type="paragraph, paragraph, paragraph, table"/>
					<figure key="46" keyRef="4.4, 4.5, 8.4.11, 8.4.12, 7" title="Ridge and hip flashings for profiled metal" type="paragraph, paragraph, paragraph, paragraph, table"/>
					<figure key="47" keyRef="8.4.11, 8.4.12, 7" title="Barge flashings for profiled metal" type="paragraph, paragraph, table"/>
					<figure key="48" keyRef="8.4.11, 8.4.12, 7" title="Parallel apron flashings for profiled metal" type="paragraph, paragraph, table"/>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="8.4.13" title="Stopends">
					<p>The top ends of profiled metal roof cladding shall have stopends as shown in Figure 49 for trapezoidal and trough profile metal roof cladding, where:</p>
					<ol>
						<li key="8.4.13.a">The roof pitch is less than 25°, or</li>
						<li key="8.4.13.b">The building is in a High/Very High/Extra High wind zone.</li>
					</ol>
					<figure key="49" keyRef="8.4.13, 92" title="Profiled metal stopends" type="paragraph, figure"/>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="8.4.14" title="Turn-downs at gutters">
					<p>The lower ends of trapezoidal and trough profile roofing shall be turned down at gutters, where the roof pitch is less than 10°. The turn-down shall be 30° from the plane of the sheet.</p>
					<commentary title="COMMENT:">Specific tools are available and should be used to turn up or turn down ends. Care should be taken to ensure the sheet does not split. Refer to the New Zealand Metal Roof and Wall Cladding Code of Practice for guidance on methods.</commentary>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="8.4.15" title="Profile closure">
					<p>Preformed compressible seals shall not be used at the eaves.</p>
					<commentary title="COMMENT:">Refer to the New Zealand Metal Roof and Wall Cladding Code of Practice for guidance.</commentary>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="8.4.16" title="Hidden, valley and internal gutters">
					<p>Hidden, valley and internal gutters shall be in accordance with Paragraph 8.1.6.</p>
					<subparagraph key="8.4.16.1" title="Hidden gutters">
						<p>Parallel hidden gutters shall be as shown in Figure 50 and Paragraph 8.1.6.2.</p>
					</subparagraph>
					<subparagraph key="8.4.16.2" title="Valley gutters">
						<p>Valley gutters shall be in accordance with catchment areas shown in Table 8, and as shown in Figure 51 and Paragraph 8.1.6.2.</p>
						<commentary title="COMMENT:">Refer to the New Zealand Metal Roof and Wall Cladding Code of Practice for additional guidance on sizing, materials and fixing.</commentary>
					</subparagraph>
					<subparagraph key="8.4.16.3" title="Internal gutters">
						<p>Internal gutters shall be as shown in Figure 52 and Paragraph 8.1.6.1.</p>
					</subparagraph>
					<figure key="50" keyRef="4.3, 4.5, 8.1.6.2, 8.4.16" title="Parallel hidden gutter for profiled metal" type="paragraph"/>
					<figure key="51" keyRef="4.3, 4.5, 8.1.6.2, 8.4.16" title="Valley gutters for profiled metal" type="paragraph"/>
					<figure key="52" keyRef="4.3, 4.5, 8.1.6.1, 8.4.16" title="Internal gutter for profiled metal" type="paragraph"/>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="8.4.17" title="Roof penetrations">
					<p>The maximum length of profiled roof cladding above penetrations shall be as shown in Table 17. The edge of roofing penetrations over 200 mm wide shall be supported in either direction with additional framing as shown in Figure 21.</p>
					<p>Roof penetrations shall be flashed as follows:</p>
					<ol>
						<li key="8.4.17.a">Pipe penetrations up to 85 mm shall be flashed using an EPDM boot flashing as shown in Figure 53,</li>
						<li key="8.4.17.b">Pipe penetrations up to 500 mm shall be flashed using a soaker flashing and EPDM boot flashing as shown in Figure 54,</li>
						<li key="8.4.17.c">Rectangular penetrations up to 1200 mm wide shall be flashed using a soaker type flashing as shown in Figure 55.</li>
					</ol>
					<commentary title="COMMENT:">Penetrations on lower pitched roofs, larger penetrations, or needing specialised complex flashings will require specific design to suit the particular circumstances. The New Zealand Metal Roof and Wall Cladding Code of Practice should be consulted for guidance.</commentary>
					<figure key="53" keyRef="8.3.10, 8.4.17, 9.6.8.5, 9.6.9.6" title="Flashing for small pipes" type="paragraph"/>
					<figure key="54" keyRef="8.4.17" title="Soaker flashing for pipe penetrations" type="paragraph"/>
					<figure key="55" keyRef="8.4.17, 17" title="Soaker flashing for other penetrations" type="paragraph, table"/>
				</paragraph>
			</section>
			<section key="8.5" title="Membrane Roofs and Decks">
				<paragraph key="8.5.1" title="Limitations">
					<p>This Acceptable Solution is limited to membranes composed of butyl or EPDM installed over plywood substrates for:</p>
					<li key="8.5.1.a">Roofs with a minimum fall of 2° (1:30),</li>
					<li key="8.5.1.b">
						<p>Decks with:</p>
						<ol>
							<li key="8.5.1.b.i">a minimum fall of 1.5° (1:40),</li>
							<li key="8.5.1.b.ii">a maximum area of 40 m2,</li>
							<li key="8.5.1.b.iii">no steps in level within deck area except into gutters,</li>
							<li key="8.5.1.b.iv">no integral roof gardens, and</li>
							<li key="8.5.1.b.v">no downpipe direct discharge to deck,</li>
						</ol>
					</li>
					<li key="8.5.1.c">Internal gutters with a minimum fall of 1 in 100, with no cross seams in the gutters, and</li>
					<li key="8.5.1.d">Decks with removable raised surfaces to give level access as shown in Figure 17A.</li>
					<p>The application of directly applied wearing or decorative surfaces to membranes is not covered in this Acceptable Solution.</p>
					<commentary title="COMMENT:">EPDM and butyl rubber membranes are subject to damage when on trafficable roof-decks. A suitable wearing surface will help reduce such damage. Increases in slopes from the previous version recognise deflection tolerances in NZS 3604 and in-service loadings by building owners.</commentary>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="8.5.2" title="General">
					<p>Closed-in construction spaces under membrane roofs and decks require adequate ventilation to prevent the accumulation of moisture under the membrane. Maintain a minimum gap of 20 mm between the underside of the substrate and any insulation, and for membrane roofs greater than 40 m2, refer to manufacturer's details for roof cavity vents and/or substrate vent requirements.</p>
					<commentary title="COMMENT:">Refer to Paragraph 1.5 for qualification of installers.</commentary>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="8.5.3" title="Plywood substrates">
					<p>Plywood shall be:</p>
					<ol>
						<li key="8.5.3.a">A minimum of 17 mm complying with AS/NZS 2269,</li>
						<li key="8.5.3.b">At least CD Grade Structural plywood with the sanded C face upwards, and</li>
						<li key="8.5.3.c">H3 with treatment type compatible with membrane and adhesives used, and kiln dried after treatment.</li>
					</ol>
					<commentary title="COMMENT:">The compatibility of LOSP-treated timber must be checked with membrane suppliers. If using plywood containing copper-based preservatives, check the compatibility of adhesives and membranes with copper with the product manufacturers.</commentary>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="8.5.4" title="Butyl and EPDM">
					<p>Butyl rubber and EPDM rubber sheet and system components used for membrane roofing or decks shall:</p>
					<ol>
						<li key="8.5.4.a">
							<p>Be a minimum thickness of:</p>
							<ol>
								<li key="8.5.4.a.i">1 mm for roofing, or</li>
								<li key="8.5.4.a.ii">1.5 mm for decks, and</li>
							</ol>
							<p>Refer to Paragraph 8.1.6.1 for membranes to gutters</p>
						</li>
						<li key="8.5.4.b">
							<p>Comply with the following parts of Table 1 in ASTM D6134:</p>
							<ol>
								<li key="8.5.4.b.i">tensile strength,</li>
								<li key="8.5.4.b.ii">elongation,</li>
								<li key="8.5.4.b.iii">water absorption,</li>
								<li key="8.5.4.b.iv">water vapour permeance, and</li>
								<li key="8.5.4.b.v">heat aging followed by: a. tensile strength b. elongation, and</li>
							</ol>
						</li>
						<li key="8.5.4.c">
							<p>Have adhesives, primers, seam tapes and pre-formed components where supplied by the manufacturer that:</p>
							<ol>
								<li key="8.5.4.c.i">comply with BRANZ EM 5, and</li>
								<li key="8.5.4.c.ii">are part of a complete system approved by the manufacturer or supplier of the membrane.</li>
							</ol>
						</li>
					</ol>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="8.5.5" title="Installation">
					<subparagraph key="8.5.5.1" title="Plywood">
						<p>Substrates must be dry when membranes are applied. The plywood and timber substructure must be a maximum moisture content of 20% when a membrane is adhered.</p>
						<commentary title="COMMENT:">This will generally require substrates to be covered to prevent rain wetting, or to be pre-primed to avoid moisture uptake. Manufacturers' recommendations should be consulted, as some require a lower moisture content in order to validate guarantees.</commentary>
						<p>Plywood substrates shall be fixed according to the following requirements:</p>
						<ol>
							<li key="8.5.5.1.a">Panels shall be laid with staggered joints (brick bond),</li>
							<li key="8.5.5.1.b">Panels shall be laid with the face grain at right angles to the main supports,</li>
							<li key="8.5.5.1.c">Supports in b) shall be at 400 mm maximum centres,</li>
							<li key="8.5.5.1.d">The edge of sheets shall be supported with dwangs or framing,</li>
							<li key="8.5.5.1.e">External edges shall be chamfered with a minimum radius of 5 mm,</li>
							<li key="8.5.5.1.f">A 20 mm H3.2 triangular fillet shall be used at the base of any 90° upstand, and</li>
							<li key="8.5.5.1.g">
								<p>Shall be fixed:</p>
								<ol>
									<li key="8.5.5.1.g.i">with 3 mm gaps between all sheets,</li>
									<li key="8.5.5.1.g.ii">using 10 g x 50 mm stainless steel countersunk head screws,</li>
									<li key="8.5.5.1.g.iii">at 150 mm centres on edges, and</li>
									<li key="8.5.5.1.g.iv">at 200 mm centres in the body of the sheets.</li>
								</ol>
							</li>
						</ol>
					</subparagraph>
					<subparagraph key="8.5.5.2" title="Butyl and EPDM">
						<p>Seam tapes shall be used on all joints of:</p>
						<ol>
							<li key="8.5.5.2.a">Roofs or decks with falls less than 5° (1:12),</li>
							<li key="8.5.5.2.c">Penetrations through the membrane where butyl or EPDM flashing is required,</li>
							<li key="8.5.5.2.d">EPDM membrane, and</li>
							<li key="8.5.5.2.e">Butyl membranes that contain EPDM.</li>
						</ol>
						<commentary title="COMMENT:">Coloured butyl membranes contain EPDM, which makes them more difficult to adhere properly. Seams should be aligned parallel to the fall of the deck to minimise ponding. Where a penetration is made through the membrane subsequent to laying, the flashing should be installed by the applicator of the membrane system.</commentary>
						<p>All joints in the plywood and junctions of plywood with other materials shall have 25 mm polyethylene release tape applied before application of the membrane.</p>
					</subparagraph>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="8.5.6" title="Roof and deck drainage">
					<p>Membrane roofs and decks shall be constructed to provide:</p>
					<ol>
						<li key="8.5.6.a">Falls as shown in Figure 56 and details in Figures 57-64</li>
						<li key="8.5.6.b">A minimum of 100 mm below an adjoining threshold as shown in Figure 62</li>
						<li key="8.5.6.c">Membrane upstands against all walls, parapets, or enclosed balustrades extending to a minimum level of 150 mm above deck level as shown in Figure 62.</li>
						<commentary title="COMMENT:">If the clearance of the cladding from the deck or roof surface is at the minimum of 35 mm, give an overlap of 115 mm to the cladding.</commentary>
						<li key="8.5.6.d">
							<p>Water discharging either:</p>
							<ol>
								<li key="8.5.6.d.i">into a roof or gutter outlet with a minimum diameter of 75 mm as shown in Figure 64 with either: an overflow as shown in Figure 63 (c) or an extra outlet, with both outlets sized to take the full required capacity. or, </li>
								<li key="8.5.6.d.ii">via a scupper, into a gutter, or rainwater head, as shown in Figure 63 (a), (b) and (d).</li>
							</ol>
						</li>
						<li key="8.5.6.e">Gutters formed with continuous butyl or EPDM strip complying with Paragraph 4.3.9, with no cross-joints.</li>
					</ol>
					<figure key="56" keyRef="8.5.6, 61, 62, 63" title="Falls in membrane roofs and decks" type="paragraph, figure, figure, figure, figure"/>
					<commentary title="COMMENT:">Refer to E1/AS1 for specific drainage requirements outside the scope of this Acceptable Solution. Seams in gutters are particularly difficult to form at outlets through enclosed balustrade walls, and the risk of failure is high. Failure of a seam can result in damage to underlying walls.</commentary>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="8.5.7" title="Control joints">
					<p>All control joints in the substrate shall be accommodated in the membrane roof design. The design of control joints for membrane roofing is subject to specific design and is outside the scope of this Acceptable Solution.</p>
					<figure key="57" keyRef="8.5.8, 59, 62, 63, 64" title="External corner in upstand" type="paragraph, figure, figure, figure, figure"/>
					<figure key="58" keyRef="8.5.8, 62, 64" title="Internal corner in upstand" type="paragraph, figure, figure"/>
					<figure key="59" keyRef="8.5.8, 8.5.9" title="Roofing penetration in membrane" type="paragraph, paragraph"/>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="8.5.8" title="Junctions">
					<p>All junctions of roof or deck to walls, parapets and enclosed balustrades shall be made weathertight using the following appropriate details:</p>
					<ol>
						<li key="8.5.8.a">Figure 57: External corner in upstands,</li>
						<li key="8.5.8.b">Figure 58: Internal corner in upstands,</li>
						<li key="8.5.8.c">Figure 61: Verges and eaves,</li>
						<li key="8.5.8.d">Figure 62: Junctions of decks and walls, and</li>
						<li key="8.5.8.e">Drainage details to Paragraph 8.5.6.</li>
					</ol>
					<subparagraph key="8.5.8.1" title="Junctions with walls">
						<p>Junctions of membrane decks or walls shall be formed as shown in Figure 62. The bottom of the wall cladding above the deck or roof surface shall be sealed prior to fixing.</p>
						<figure key="60" keyRef="8.5.9" title="Pipe penetration in membrane" type="paragraph"/>
					</subparagraph>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="8.5.9" title="Penetrations">
					<p>Penetrations through membrane roofs and decks shall be as shown in Figure 59 and Figure 60.</p>
					<figure key="61" keyRef="8.5.8, 56" title="Verges in membrane" type="paragraph, figure"/>
					<subparagraph key="8.5.9.1" title="Handrails">
						<p>Fixing of posts for handrails into membrane roofs or decks is not covered by this Acceptable Solution.</p>
						<commentary title="COMMENT:">Any fixing of posts into membrane roofs or decks will require specific design. The fixing of posts into tiles over a membrane is particularly risky, and should be avoided.</commentary>
					</subparagraph>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="8.5.10" title="Gutters">
					<p>Deck gutters and internal outlets shall be constructed as shown in Figure 64.</p>
					<commentary title="COMMENT:">Internal outlets should have a dome-type cover to reduce risk of blockage, except where this could constitute a pedestrian hazard.</commentary>
					<figure key="62" keyRef="7.4.3, 56" title="Junctions with walls for membrane" type="paragraph, figure"/>
					<figure key="63" keyRef="8.5.6, 56" title="Rainwater head and scupper opening in membrane" type="paragraph, figure"/>
					<figure key="64" keyRef="8.5.6, 8.5.10" title="Gutters and outlets in membrane" type="paragraph"/>
				</paragraph>
			</section>
		</part>
		<part key="9.0" title="Wall Claddings">
			<section key="9.1" title="General">
				<p>Wall claddings shall meet the requirements of NZBC E2.3.2 to E2.3.7, and comply with the provisions of Paragraph 9.1.1 to Paragraph 9.9.</p>
				<p>Claddings in Extra High wind zones require:</p>
				<ol>
					<li key="9.1.a">Rigid underlays to Paragraph 9.1.7.2</li>
					<li key="9.1.b">Drained cavities to Paragraph 9.1.8</li>
					<li key="9.1.c">Hooks and hems on flashing upstands, and additional 25 mm height to Paragraph 4.6.</li>
				</ol>
				<paragraph key="9.1.1" title="Limitations">
					<p>This Acceptable Solution is limited to the wall cladding systems listed in Paragraph 3.3. Table 3 lists wall cladding systems that shall be used for buildings with varying risk scores. The method of establishing the level of risk associated with the use of a specific wall cladding is given in Paragraph 3.1. Based on this risk score, a wall cladding may require the inclusion of a drained cavity as described in Paragraph 9.1.8. Claddings in Extra High wind zones require rigid underlays and drained cavities - refer to Table 3.</p>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="9.1.2" title="Maintenance">
					<p>Maintenance of wall claddings shall be carried out as necessary to achieve the expected durability of the material - refer to Paragraph 2.5.</p>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="9.1.3" title="Bottom of cladding">
					<p>Separations, clearances to ground level, and overlaps shall be as shown in Figure 65 and Table 18. Clearances to roof claddings and decks shall be minimum 35 mm - refer to Table 7 and Figure 18.</p>
					<p>Clearances shall be measured to:</p>
					<ol>
						<li key="9.1.3.a">The finished plane of any adjacent horizontal surface, or</li>
						<li key="9.1.3.b">The top surface of any adjacent sloped or horizontal apron flashing.</li>
					</ol>
					<commentary title="COMMENT:">This keeps the bottom edge of the cladding dry, and allows cleaning and painting of the bottom surfaces.</commentary>
					<figure key="65" keyRef="9.1.3, 9.1.3.4, 9.2.5, 18" title="Levels and garage openings" type="paragraph, paragraph, paragraph, table"/>
					<subparagraph key="9.1.3.1" title="Concrete slabs">
						<p>Slab levels shall be set to allow reinstatement of final landscaped ground levels as outlined in Figure 65 and Table 18.</p>
						<commentary title="COMMENT:">NZS 3604 may require greater ground clearances depending on floor type and materials. The likely final landscaped ground levels are to be taken into account when planning foundations and earthworks to avoid reductions to the minimum ground clearances in the finished building.</commentary>
					</subparagraph>
					<subparagraph key="9.1.3.2" title="Masonry veneer clearances">
						<p>The height of the floor slab above finished ground level shall be in accordance with Figure 73D and as shown in Table 18.</p>
					</subparagraph>
					<subparagraph key="9.1.3.3" title="Bottom of wall claddings for concrete ground slabs (except masonry veneer)">
						<p>At concrete slab level, the base of the cladding system shall be as shown in Table 18, and:</p>
						<ol>
							<li key="9.1.3.3.a">
								<p>Finish a minimum of:</p>
								<ol>
									<li key="9.1.3.3.a.i">100 mm above a paved surface, or</li>
									<li key="9.1.3.3.a.ii">175 mm above finished unpaved surface,</li>
								</ol>
							</li>
							<li key="9.1.3.3.b">Overlap the concrete slab by 50 mm, and</li>
							<li key="9.1.3.3.c">Be offset horizontally by a minimum of 6 mm for direct fixed claddings to prevent capillary action.</li>
						</ol>
					</subparagraph>
					<subparagraph key="9.1.3.4" title="Garages and openings to garages">
						<p>Refer to Figure 65 and Table 18 for overall level change requirements.</p>
						<commentary title="COMMENT:">This paragraph does not apply to garages that are detached outbuildings.</commentary>
						<p>Garage spaces within, or attached to, the building envelope shall have:</p>
						<ol>
							<li key="9.1.3.4.a">Openings provided with a 50 mm minimum total level change between the interior and the exterior paving,</li>
							<commentary title="COMMENT:">Methods for achieving the required step may include:  A 50 mm difference in finished ground level adjacent to the opening, or A raised threshold at the opening, or Concrete nibs at the opening.</commentary>
							<li key="9.1.3.4.b">Provision to drain water away from the threshold of the opening</li>
							<li key="9.1.3.4.c">Rigid wall underlays, to Table 23, where external garage walls are unlined</li>
							<li key="9.1.3.4.d">linings to garage walls adjoining habitable spaces</li>
							<li key="9.1.3.4.e">weather resisting garage doors</li>
							<li key="9.1.3.4.f">window and door details (where included) to Paragraphs 9.2 to 9.9.</li>
						</ol>
					</subparagraph>
					<subparagraph key="9.1.3.5" title="Bottom of wall claddings for timber floor framing">
						<p>Suspended timber floors shall meet the requirements of NZS 3604. Clearances from paved and unpaved surfaces to the wall framing shall be in accordance with NZS 3604, and Table 18.</p>
						<p>At ground floor level, the base of the cladding system shall:</p>
						<ol>
							<li key="9.1.3.5.a">Overlap the timber floor structure by 50 mm minimum, and</li>
							<li key="9.1.3.5.b">For walls with direct fixed claddings, be offset horizontally from a concrete foundation wall by a minimum of 6 mm</li>
							<li key="9.1.3.5.c">Have no direct connection between sub-floor spaces and drained cavities.</li>
						</ol>
						<commentary title="COMMENT:">Where claddings require drained cavities, care must be taken to ensure air from the subfloor space cannot enter the cavity. This is important, as moisture levels in subfloor air can be high.</commentary>
					</subparagraph>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="9.1.4" title="Barriers to airflow">
					<p>This Acceptable Solution requires external walls to have barriers to airflow, in the form of:</p>
					<ol>
						<li key="9.1.4.a">Interior linings with all joints stopped for wind zones up to Very High, or</li>
						<li key="9.1.4.b">Rigid underlays (and drained cavities) for buildings in Extra High wind zones - refer to Paragraph 9.1.7.2</li>
						<li key="9.1.4.c">Where walls are not lined, such as attic spaces at gable ends, an air barrier complying with Table 23, fixed to framing prior to fixing cladding or cavity battens</li>
						<li key="9.1.4.d">For attached garages, underlays to Paragraph 9.1.3.4.</li>
					</ol>
					<commentary title="COMMENT:">The primary function of air barriers and air seals is to moderate airflows at junctions and inside the wall cavity. Airflows in certain weather conditions encourage significant amounts of water to move along their path, and it is therefore important to manage airflow in cavity walls with barriers and air seals. In the absence of internal linings, an air barrier is required to support wind pressures at locations such as gable ends and unlined garage spaces. Air pressure drop is not always across the internal lining, indicating the wall underlay acts as an air barrier as well.</commentary>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="9.1.5" title="Wall underlays to wall openings">
					<p>Prior to window or door installation:</p>
					<ol>
						<li key="9.1.5.a">Flexible wall underlay shall be cut and dressed into all sides of openings as per Figure 72A and B,</li>
						<li key="9.1.5.b">
							<p>Flexible flashing tape shall be applied to head and sill framing as shown in Figures 72A and 72B. Flexible flashing tape shall</p>
							<ol>
								<li key="9.1.5.b.i">comply with Parts 3.2 and 4 of ICBO Acceptance Criteria AC148, and</li>
								<li key="9.1.5.b.ii">be compatible with the wall underlay</li>
							</ol>
						</li>
					</ol>
					<commentary title="COMMENT:">Dressing the wall underlay around the framing timber and providing a flexible air seal limits airflows around the window reveal. The flexible flashing tape keeps any water that does get past the cladding, or through the joinery, from direct contact with the timber.</commentary>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="9.1.6" title="Air seals">
					<p>Window, door and other penetration openings shall be provided with flexible air seals to minimise the risk of airflows carrying water into the building wall. The air seal shall be:</p>
					<ol>
						<li key="9.1.6.a">Provided between the reveal or frame and the wrapped opening (for example of use, refer to Figure 81), </li>
						<li key="9.1.6.b">Installed over a closed cell polyethylene foam (PEF) backing rod, or similar</li>
						<li key="9.1.6.c">
							<p>Made of:</p>
							<ol>
								<li key="9.1.6.c.i">self-expanding polyurethane foam, or</li>
								<li key="9.1.6.c.ii">sealant complying with: a. Type F, Class 20LM or 25LM of ISO 11600, or b. low modulus Type II Class A of  Federal Specification TT-S-00230C.</li>
							</ol>
						</li>
					</ol>
					<commentary title="COMMENT:">Some sealants can react with bitumen based flashing tape, preventing full curing of the sealant. Where necessary, consult sealant manufacturers for application requirements. Backing rods are used for sealant and for self-expanding polyurethane foam as there is a danger foam will expand to the outside of the wall and form a moisture bridge to the interior. For further information refer to ASTM C1330 for backing rod material performance.</commentary>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="9.1.7" title="Wall underlay">
					<subparagraph key="9.1.7.1">
						<p>Flexible wall underlays shall be in accordance with Table 23, and shall:</p>
						<ol>
							<li key="9.1.7.1.a">Be run horizontally,</li>
							<li key="9.1.7.1.b">Have upper sheets lapped over lower sheets to ensure that direction of laps will allow water to be shed to outside of the wall underlay,</li>
							<li key="9.1.7.1.c">Be lapped not less than 75 mm at horizontal joints,</li>
							<li key="9.1.7.1.d">Be lapped not less than 150 mm over studs at vertical joints, and</li>
							<li key="9.1.7.1.e">Extend 35 mm below bottom plate or bearer,</li>
							<li key="9.1.7.1.f">Be restrained from bulging into a drained cavity. Refer to Paragraph 9.1.8.5.</li>
						</ol>
					</subparagraph>
					<subparagraph key="9.1.7.2">
						<p>Rigid wall underlays, in association with drained cavities (including direct fixed corrugated profiled metal), are required in Extra High wind zones. Refer to Table 3 and Table 23. Rigid underlays are also required to external walls of attached garages that are unlined. Refer Paragraphs 1.1.1 and 9.1.3.4 c).</p>
						<p>Rigid wall underlays shall be in accordance with Table 23, and shall:</p>
						<ol>
							<li key="9.1.7.2.a">Be minimum 7 mm H3 plywood, or 6 mm fibre cement sheet</li>
							<li key="9.1.7.2.b">Be installed with sheet edges fixed over solid framing</li>
							<li key="9.1.7.2.c">Be over-fixed with a flexible wall underlay from Table 23 and installed as in Paragraph 9.1.7.1</li>
							<commentary title="COMMENT:">Some proprietary systems may not require the addition of a flexible underlay</commentary>
							<li key="9.1.7.2.d">Have flexible underlay folded into opening reveals as in Paragraph 9.1.5 a)</li>
							<li key="9.1.7.2.e">Have cavity battens at maximum 600 mm centres</li>
							<li key="9.1.7.2.f">Be finish flushed with underside of bottom plate or bearer.</li>
						</ol>
						<commentary title="COMMENT:">External air pressures in higher wind zones can transfer to interior linings, and exceed recommended loadings prescribed by some lining manufacturers. Rigid underlays will protect linings from undue air pressure loadings, and help ensure cavity depths are maintained for the proper functioning of the drained cavity.</commentary>
					</subparagraph>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="9.1.8" title="Drained cavities">
					<p>Based on the risk score for an external wall calculated as per Paragraph 3.1, a wall cladding may require the inclusion of a drained cavity. Where a drained cavity is required, it shall meet the requirements of Paragraphs 9.1.8 to 9.1.9.4.</p>
					<commentary title="COMMENT:">Cavities manage occasional ingress of water past the cladding, but should not act as gutters or drains.</commentary>
					<subparagraph key="9.1.8.1" title="Limitations">
						<p>This Acceptable Solution is limited to systems where:</p>
						<ol>
							<li key="9.1.8.1.a">Cavity battens are fixed, by the cladding fixings, to the wall framing,</li>
							<li key="9.1.8.1.b">Claddings are fixed through the cavity battens into the wall framing, and</li>
							<li key="9.1.8.1.c">The drained cavity behind claddings, except in masonry veneer, is not vented at the top.</li>
						</ol>
						<p>Systems where the cladding is fixed into the cavity batten only are outside the scope of this Acceptable Solution.</p>
					</subparagraph>
					<subparagraph key="9.1.8.2" title="Requirements">
						<p>Where a drained cavity is required, it shall:</p>
						<ol>
							<li key="9.1.8.2.a">
								<p>Be installed over a wall underlay, either flexible or rigid, that:</p>
								<ol>
									<li key="9.1.8.2.a.i">complies with Table 23, and</li>
									<li key="9.1.8.2.a.ii">is fixed to wall framing,</li>
								</ol>
							</li>
							<li key="9.1.8.2.b">Be formed using vertical cavity battens,</li>
							<li key="9.1.8.2.c">
								<p>Restrict air movement between the drained cavity and:</p>
								<ol>
									<li key="9.1.8.2.c.i">floor, wall and roof framing,</li>
									<li key="9.1.8.2.c.ii">attic roof space, and</li>
									<li key="9.1.8.2.c.iii">subfloor space,</li>
								</ol>
							</li>
							<li key="9.1.8.2.d">Be drained and open to the exterior at the bottom of cavities,</li>
							<li key="9.1.8.2.e">Use vermin-proofing at the cavity base as per Paragraph 9.1.8.3 and Figure 66,</li>
							<li key="9.1.8.2.f">Use cavity spacers as shown in Figure 67, where fixing is required between cavity battens. Alternative cavity spacers to those described in Paragraph 9.1.8.2 are permitted. Refer to Paragraph 9.1.8.4 f).</li>
						</ol>
						<figure key="66" keyRef="9.1.8.2" title="Cavity base closer/vermin proofing" type="paragraph"/>
						<figure key="67" keyRef="9.1.8.2, 9.1.8.4" title="Cavity spacers" type="paragraph"/>
						<commentary title="COMMENT:">Solid horizontal cavity spacers risk obstruction of air flow in cavities and risk bridging moisture across the cavity.</commentary>
					</subparagraph>
					<subparagraph key="9.1.8.3" title="Vermin-proofing">
						<p>Vermin-proofing shall be provided above window and door heads and at the base of the drained cavity. Figure 66 provides one example of an appropriate cavity closer. Aluminium, stainless steel or uPVC in accordance with Paragraph 4.1 shall be used where vermin-proofing material is not readily accessible or replaceable.</p>
						<p>Vermin-proofing shall:</p>
						<ol>
							<li key="9.1.8.3.a">Provide holes or slots between 3 mm and 5 mm,</li>
							<li key="9.1.8.3.b">Provide an area of opening of 1000 mm2 per lineal metre of wall, and</li>
							<li key="9.1.8.3.c">
								<p>Be positioned to allow a minimum drip edge to the wall cladding of:</p>
								<ol>
									<li key="9.1.8.3.c.i">10 mm at the base of walls, and</li>
									<li key="9.1.8.3.c.ii">15 mm above window and door head flashings.</li>
								</ol>
							</li>
						</ol>
						<commentary title="COMMENT:">It is important the openings in vermin-proofing are kept clear and unobstructed in order to maintain draining and venting of the cavity. The closure shown is only one option for vermin-proofing. Provided openings are as specified, other dimensions can vary, so allowing the use of other shapes such as channels and right-angles.</commentary>
					</subparagraph>
					<subparagraph key="9.1.8.4" title="Cavity battens and jamb battens">
						<p>Cavity battens shall:</p>
						<ol>
							<li key="9.1.8.4.a">Be nominal 20 mm (between limits of 18 mm and 25 mm in thickness),</li>
							<li key="9.1.8.4.b">Be a minimum 45 mm wide,</li>
							<li key="9.1.8.4.c">Be fixed, by the cladding fixings, through the wall underlay into the framing,</li>
							<li key="9.1.8.4.d">If timber, comply with B2/AS1,</li>
							<li key="9.1.8.4.e">If polystyrene, comply with Paragraph 9.9.3.1, and be protected from any incompatible vapours from timber treatment.</li>
							<p>Cavity battens and/or cavity spacers that meet E2/VM1 Class 1 testing and B2/AS1, permit air circulation are allowed. The Class 1 test must include a horizontal cladding joint supported on a cavity spacer batten of a proposed type. Jamb battens shall:</p>
							<li key="9.1.8.4.f">be nominal 20 mm (between limits of 18 mm and 25 mm in thickness), minimum 45 mm wide, and of timber complying with B2/AS1. Refer to Figure 72A.</li>
						</ol>
						<commentary title="COMMENT:">The solvents from freshly LOSP-treated timber may melt polystyrene, so these should not be used together. Solid horizontal cavity spacers risk obstruction of air flow in cavities and risk bridging moisture across the cavity. Battens will be fixed by the cladding fixings, which will penetrate the wall framing. Battens will therefore need only temporary fixing until the cladding is fixed. Polystyrene battens may be temporarily adhered to the wall underlay.</commentary>
					</subparagraph>
					<subparagraph key="9.1.8.5" title="Wall framing behind cavities">
						<p>Dwangs shall be at a maximum of 1350 mm centres generally and maximum 480 mm centres for direct-fixed vertical weatherboard profiles, and vertical metal corrugated and symmetrical trapezoidal claddings.</p>
						<p>Where stud spacings are greater than 450 mm, and flexible wall underlays only are used, an intermediate means of restraining the flexible wall underlay and insulation from bulging into the drained cavity shall be installed. Acceptable means of achieving this are by using:</p>
						<ol>
							<li key="9.1.8.5.a">75 mm galvanized mesh or wire galvanized in accordance with AS/NZS 4534,</li>
							<li key="9.1.8.5.b">Polypropylene tape or galvanized wire at 300 mm centres fixed horizontally and drawn taut, or</li>
							<li key="9.1.8.5.c">Vertical cavity battens at 300 mm centres maximum.</li>
						</ol>
					</subparagraph>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="9.1.9" title="Penetrations">
					<subparagraph key="9.1.9.1" title="Penetrations through cavities">
						<p>Window penetrations through cavities shall meet the requirements of Paragraph 9.2 to Paragraph 9.9.</p>
					</subparagraph>
					<subparagraph key="9.1.9.2" title="Other cavity penetrations">
						<p>Where penetrations of the wall cladding are wider than the cavity batten spacing, allowance shall be made for air flow between adjacent cavities by leaving a minimum gap of 10 mm between the bottom of the vertical cavity batten and the flashing to the opening.</p>
					</subparagraph>
					<subparagraph key="9.1.9.3" title="Pipes and service penetrations">
						<p>Pipes and service penetrations shall be made weathertight by using methods shown in Figures 68 and 69. Flashing tape complying with Paragraph 4.3.11, and sealant complying with:</p>
						<ol>
							<li key="9.1.9.3.a">Type F, Class 20LM or 25LM of ISO 11600, or</li>
							<li key="9.1.9.3.b">low modulus Type II Class A of Federal Specification TT-S-00230C.</li>
						</ol>
					</subparagraph>
					<figure key="68" keyRef="9.1.9.3, 126" title="General pipe penetration" type="paragraph, figure"/>
					<commentary title="COMMENT:">Where possible, pipe penetrations, meterboxes and similar penetrations should be located in sheltered areas of the building, such as a porch, or be installed behind a weatherproof glazed panel.</commentary>
					<figure key="69" keyRef="9.1.9.3, 9.6.8.5, 9.6.9.6" title="General meterbox and similar penetrations" type="paragraph"/>
					<subparagraph key="9.1.9.4" title="Inter-storey junctions">
						<p>Inter-storey junctions in claddings over drained cavities shall be formed for walls:</p>
						<ol>
							<li key="9.1.9.4.a">Up to a maximum of two storeys or 7 metres in height, as shown for the specific wall claddings in Paragraph 9.2 to Paragraph 9.9, or</li>
							<li key="9.1.9.4.b">Over two storeys or 7 metres by using an inter-storey flashing bridging the drained cavity as shown in Figure 70.</li>
						</ol>
						<commentary title="COMMENT:">A drained cavity height is limited to manage the moisture handled by the cavity before it is directed to the outside.</commentary>
					</subparagraph>
					<figure key="70" keyRef="4.6.1.7, 9.1.9.4, 16" title="General inter-storey junction" type="paragraph, paragraph, figure"/>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="9.1.10" title="Windows and doors">
					<p>Windows and doors shall comply with the requirements of NZS 4211, and reveals shall comply with NZS 3602. Flashings shall comply with Paragraph 4.0. Window details specific to particular claddings are given in Paragraph 9.2 to Paragraph 9.9. Door details shall be based on window details and shown in Figures 17A-D.</p>
					<p>After installation, the flange forming the window or door facing shall have an overlap to the surrounding cladding material or associated back flashings of a) For jambs - 10 mm minimum b) For sills - 8 mm minimum.</p>
					<subparagraph key="9.1.10.1" title="Scope">
						<p>This Acceptable Solution is limited to aluminium window and door joinery that:</p>
						<ol>
							<li key="9.1.10.1.a">Has horizontal window and door heads only</li>
							<li key="9.1.10.1.b">Has maximum frame dimensions of 5000 mm wide or 5000 mm high, and a maximum overall frame area, for any one frame, of 13.5 m2, or</li>
							<li key="9.1.10.1.c">For sills to floor level, has maximum width of 6 m and maximum overall frame area is 16 m2.</li>
						</ol>
						<commentary title="COMMENT:">Sloped heads require specifically designed kick-out flashings at bottom edges of head flashings. Where width outlined in Paragraph 9.1.10.1 are beyond the limits for sill and head trimmer framing in NZS 3604 specific engineering design of the framing is required. Certain aluminium joinery sections and installation requirements may not be able to meet the details of this Acceptable Solution, especially in regard to window facing cover, sill support, window fixing, and sill flashing requirements. The window details in these cases require specific design.</commentary>
					</subparagraph>
					<subparagraph key="9.1.10.2" title="Treatment of opening">
						<ol>
							<li key="9.1.10.2.a">Treatment of the window openings for direct fixed wall claddings shall be as shown in Figure 72A.</li>
							<li key="9.1.10.2.b">For direct fixed claddings, windows and doors shall have a 5 mm stand-off of the flange to the cladding to allow for air intrusion to the trim cavity for pressure equalisation. Note that this gap is sealed or trimmed down the jambs, but left open along the sill.</li>
							<li key="9.1.10.2.c">Window openings for wall claddings over drained cavities shall be as shown in Figure 72B. Note there shall be no sill flashing.</li>
							<li key="9.1.10.2.d">For cavity fixed claddings, windows and doors shall finish against the cladding, except for flat fibre cement and ply claddings that require a 5 mm stand-off to allow for sealant weather seals between facings and cladding - eg, Figure 116.</li>
							<li key="9.1.10.2.e">Materials for flashings shall be selected from Paragraph 4.0, Table 7, and Table 20.</li>
						</ol>
					</subparagraph>
					<subparagraph key="9.1.10.3" title="Window and door heads">
						<p>Windows and doors shall include head flashings, finished to the wall underlay as shown in Figure 71, by either using flexible flashing tape, or lapping an additional layer of wall underlay over the upstand. The additional wall underlay shall extend to the top of the wall, or to the nearest lap above, and be lapped under the top layer.</p>
						<figure key="71" keyRef="9.1.7, 9.1.10.3, 9.1.10.4" title="General sealing of head flashing" type="paragraph"/>
					</subparagraph>
					<subparagraph key="9.1.10.4" title="Head flashings">
						<p>Head flashings shall be in accordance with Paragraph 4.6.1.6 and Table 7, unless specifically shown otherwise, and shall:</p>
						<ol>
							<li key="9.1.10.4.a">Direct water to the outside of the wall cladding, and</li>
							<li key="9.1.10.4.b">Finish to the window head with clearance dimensions shown in Figure 71</li>
							<li key="9.1.10.4.c">For direct fixed claddings, have 50 mm bead of sealant installed between cladding and each end of the head flashing</li>
							<li key="9.1.10.4.d">
								<p>For wall claddings on cavity walls:</p>
								<ol>
									<li key="9.1.10.4.d.i">incorporate 10 mm turn-ups as stop-ends, terminating at the inside face of the cladding so they do not pass through the cladding, an</li>
									<li key="9.1.10.4.d.ii">permit ventilation of the drained cavities above, by the installation of cavity base closers as shown in Figure 66.</li>
								</ol>
							</li>
							<li key="9.1.10.4.e">For Very High and Extra High wind zones, have sealant installed between underside of head flashing and top edge of window head flange - refer Figure 71 (c) .</li>
						</ol>
						<commentary title="COMMENT:">Stopends are useful to prevent water moving past the ends of head flashings. However, additional problems of weatherproofing occur where the stopend penetrates the cladding.</commentary>
					</subparagraph>
					<subparagraph key="9.1.10.5" title="Window and door sills">
						<ol>
							<li key="9.1.10.5.a">
								<p>Direct fixed claddings shall have</p>
								<ol>
									<li key="9.1.10.5.a.i">sill tray flashings as shown in Paragraphs 9.2 to 9.9 for each cladding type. The sill flashing shall extend back past the condensation channel of the window. Ensure flat sill trays do not slope backwards. The 5 mm gap between the window facing and sill tray must not be sealed.</li>
									<li key="9.1.10.5.a.ii">direct fixed door sills, installed as for windows, and as shown in Figure 17D.</li>
								</ol>
							</li>
							<li key="9.1.10.5.b">
								<p>Claddings over a drained cavity shall have:</p>
								<ol>
									<li key="9.1.10.5.b.iii">window sills as shown in Paragraphs 9.2 to 9.9, without sill flashing</li>
									<li key="9.1.10.5.b.iv">door sills as shown in Figure 17C.</li>
									<li key="9.1.10.5.b.v">Sill support bars and mechanisms for all doors, and for windows with a trim opening wider than 600 mm. Support bars and mechanisms shall comply with BRANZ Evaluation Method EM6, E2/VM1 and B2/AS1. Support bars and mechanisms must be installed prior to installation of the window or door.</li>
								</ol>
							</li>
							<commentary title="COMMENT:">Support bars and mechanisms are rated for their capacity to support the total weight of a joinery unit when installed at given offsets from the frame depending on cladding type. Designers select the an appropriate complying support mechanism for the joinery weight. Manufacturers provide build-in instructions for support bars and mechanisms.</commentary>
							<li key="9.1.10.5.c">Mitred aluminium window and door sills, for both cavity and direct fixed, shall have a corner soaker fitted to the back of the sill/jamb joint and installed at point of manufacture. The soaker will be designed to act as a secondary device to prevent water ingress to the building in support of the primary mitre seals. Soaker materials shall be either uPVC, aluminium, polypropylene, high impact styrene or other semi rigid moulded polymeric material. Sill support bars and mechanisms must be designed to not impede the possible drainage of water from surfaces of sill flashing tape, and permit an air passage (of at least 1000 mm2/m sill width) from the drained cavity to the window/door trim cavity.</li>
						</ol>
					</subparagraph>
					<subparagraph key="9.1.10.6" title="Window and door jambs">
						<p>Jamb flashings shall be installed as shown in Paragraphs 9.2 to 9.9. Where required, jamb flashings shall overlap sill flashings, and direct moisture to the outside face of the cladding system.</p>
					</subparagraph>
					<subparagraph key="9.1.10.7" title="Closed cell foam tape">
						<p>Compressible foam tape shown behind window facings and cladding joints shall be closed cell PVC foam, with:</p>
						<ol>
							<li key="9.1.10.7.a">Hardness 55-60 to ASTM D2240 Scale OO,</li>
							<li key="9.1.10.7.b">Grade VE-43 to ASTM D1667,</li>
							<li key="9.1.10.7.c">Compression set of 20% maximum to ASTM D1667, and</li>
							<li key="9.1.10.7.d">UV weathering in UV Weatherometer for 1500 light hours to ASTM G154 or ASTM G155 with no visible deterioration in appearance.</li>
						</ol>
					</subparagraph>
					<subparagraph key="9.1.10.8" title="Attachments for windows and doors">
						<p>Install windows and doors using pairs of minimum 75 x 3.15 galvanised jolt head nails or 8 gauge x 65 mm stainless steel screws,  through reveals into surrounding framing at:</p>
						<ol>
							<li key="9.1.10.8.a">Maximum 450 mm centres along sills, jambs and heads, and</li>
							<li key="9.1.10.8.b">Maximum 150 mm from reveal ends.</li>
						</ol>
					</subparagraph>
					<figure key="72A" keyRef="9.1.5, 9.1.10.2, 81, 82, 83, 84, 90, 95, 115" title="General window and door opening for direct fixed" type="paragraph, paragraph, figure, figure, figure, figure, figure, figure, figure"/>
					<figure key="72B" keyRef="9.1.5, 9.1.9.3, 9.1.10.2, 73C, 76, 85, 86, 91, 99, 116, 128" title="General window and door opening with drainage cavity" type="paragraph, paragraph, paragraph, figure, figure, figure, figure, figure, figure, figure, figure"/>
				</paragraph>
			</section>
			<section key="9.2" title="Masonry Veneer">
				<paragraph key="9.2.1" title="Limitations">
					<p>This Acceptable Solution is limited to masonry veneer cladding attached to timber wall framing outlined in NZS 3604. Masonry veneer is either:</p>
					<ol>
						<li key="9.2.1.a">Clay brick, or</li>
						<li key="9.2.1.b">Concrete brick or block.</li>
					</ol>
					<commentary title="COMMENT:">Natural stone bricks or blocks may be suitable. However, they are not part of this Acceptable Solution. Refer to the manufacturer's recommendations for specific design information. Refer to Paragraph 1.5 for qualification of installers.</commentary>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="9.2.2" title="General">
					<ol>
						<li key="9.2.2.i">The materials and workmanship of masonry veneer shall be in accordance with SNZ HB 4236 and have a maximum mass of veneer of 220 kg/m2 and minimum veneer thickness of 70 mm</li>
						<li key="9.2.2.ii">Masonry units shall be laid-up in running bond</li>
						<li key="9.2.2.iii">Mortar, materials (cement, sand and admixtures) shall comply with NZS 4210</li>
						<li key="9.2.2.iv">Mortar joints less than 24 hours old shall not be subject to vibration, such as would result from the nailing of interior linings</li>
					</ol>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="9.2.3" title="Installation">
					<p>Masonry veneer construction shall be as shown in Figure 73B, and have:</p>
					<ol>
						<li key="9.2.3.a">A maximum height of veneer above adjacent finished ground level of 7 m.</li>
						<li key="9.2.3.b">A maximum height of veneer of 4.0 m, measured from the top of the concrete masonry wall, foundation wall or slab edge foundation. In the case of a veneer faced concrete block wall or foundation wall height is measured from the top of that wall.</li>
						<li key="9.2.3.c">A maximum height of veneer of 5.5 m on a gable end wall.</li>
						<li key="9.2.3.d">A minimum wall or panel width of 230 mm.</li>
					</ol>
					<p>Note: The bracing demand for framing supporting masonry veneer is determined from values listed in NZS 3604.</p>
					<commentary title="COMMENT:">Refer to Paragraph 1.5 for qualification of installers</commentary>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="9.2.4" title="Flashings">
					<ol>
						<li key="9.2.4.i">
							<p>Sill and head flashings shall be as described in Paragraph 4.3 and be either:</p>
							<ol>
								<li key="9.2.4.i.a">1.5 mm butyl rubber- refer to Paragraph 4.3.9</li>
								<li key="9.2.4.i.b">2 ply asphaltic pliable waterproofing membrane - refer to Paragraph 4.3.10</li>
								<li key="9.2.4.i.c">Pliable polyethylene minimum 0.5 mm thick complying with DPC/DPM Table 23.</li>
							</ol>
						</li>
						<li key="9.2.4.ii">
							<p>Jamb flashings shall be:</p>
							<ol>
								<li key="9.2.4.ii.d">2 ply asphaltic pliable waterproofing membrane complying with AS/NZS 2904</li>
								<li key="9.2.4.ii.e">Pliable polyethylene minimum 0.5 mm thick complying with DPC/DPM Table 23.</li>
							</ol>
						</li>
					</ol>
					<commentary title="COMMENT:">For further information refer to ASTM C1330 for backing rod material performance.</commentary>
					<figure key="73A" keyRef="9.2.8" title="Vertical control joint" type="paragraph"/>
					<figure key="73B" keyRef="9.2.3" title="Masonry veneer height limitations" type="paragraph"/>
					<figure key="73C" keyRef="9.2.4, 9.2.6, 9.2.9" title="Masonry veneer window and door installation" type="paragraph"/>
					<figure key="73D" keyRef="9.2.5" title="Masonry veneer details" type="paragraph"/>
					<figure key="73E" keyRef="9.2.5, 9.2.6" title="Masonry veneer details" type="paragraph"/>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="9.2.5" title="Foundation support and damp proofing">
					<ol>
						<li key="9.2.5.i">
							<p>Masonry veneer shall be supported by one, or a combination of the following:</p>
							<ol>
								<li key="9.2.5.i.a">Concrete of masonry foundation wall</li>
								<li key="9.2.5.i.b">Thickened slab edge footing</li>
								<li key="9.2.5.i.c">Concrete or masonry lower storey wall.</li>
							</ol>
						</li>
						<li key="9.2.5.ii">The level of the concrete slab above ground shall comply with Figure 65.</li>
						<li key="9.2.5.iii">The top of a foundation wall or concrete slab shall be stepped down, so that the surface supporting the veneer is 50 mm or more below the surface supporting the timber framing.</li>
						<li key="9.2.5.iv">
							<p>Provide a damp-proof course to the stepped rebates supporting masonry veneer adjacent to all habitable spaces and garages attached to habitable spaces. This includes stepped rebates in foundations, or on top of concrete or concrete masonry walls supporting veneers. Damp-proofing material shall be as outlined in Table 23 and be either:</p>
							<ol>
								<li key="9.2.5.iv.a">
									<p>For rebates lower than ground floor level:</p>
									<ol>
										<li key="9.2.5.iv.a.i">two coats of bituminous liquid, or</li>
										<li key="9.2.5.iv.a.ii">1.0 mm butyl rubber or bituminous sheet, or</li>
										<li key="9.2.5.iv.a.iii">0.25 mm polythene or polyethylene damp-proof membrane.</li>
									</ol>
								</li>
								<li key="9.2.5.iv.b">
									<p>For rebates above ground floor level:</p>
									<ol>
										<li key="9.2.5.iv.b.i">1.0 mm butyl rubber or bituminous sheet, or</li>
										<li key="9.2.5.iv.b.ii">0.25 mm polythene or polyethylene damp-proof membrane</li>
									</ol>
								</li>
							</ol>
						</li>
						<li key="9.2.5.v">Lap joints in flashings minimum of 150 mm.</li>
						<li key="9.2.5.vi">Dimension rebates to accommodate the required cavity width in Paragraph 9.2.6 and the thickness of the veneer so that the veneer is supported within the tolerances outlined in Figures 73D and E.</li>
					</ol>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="9.2.6" title="Cavities">
					<p>Paragraphs 9.1.8.2(a), 9.1.8.5, and 9.1.9.3 shall apply to masonry veneer cavities.</p>
					<ol>
						<li key="9.2.6.a">The clear width of cavity between the masonry veneer and the exterior face of the wall underlay or bracing attaching to timber framing shall not be less than 40 mm or more than 75 mm wide measured at any part of the cavity.</li>
						<commentary title="COMMENT:">It is important to maintain the minimum cavity width of 40 mm after allowing for construction tolerances and thicknesses of wall underlays and sheet bracing.</commentary>
						<li key="9.2.6.b">Pipes and services shall not be placed in the cavity other than passing directly through the cavity to the exterior.</li>
						<li key="9.2.6.c">
							<p>The cavity shall be drained and vented to outside at the bottom of wall panels, and above openings by open perpends that:</p>
							<ol>
								<li key="9.2.6.c.i">are a minimum of 75 mm in height, by the width of the vertical mortar joint</li>
								<li key="9.2.6.c.ii">at centres not exceeding 800 mm (where drainage/weep holes are less than 75 mm high, decrease spacing to give a ventilation area of 1000 mm2/m wall length)</li>
								<li key="9.2.6.c.iii">are fitted with vermin proofing where gaps greater than 13 mm exist.</li>
							</ol>
						</li>
						<li key="9.2.6.d">The cavity shall be ventilated to the outside at the top of walls by either similar vents as at the bottom, or a continuous 5 mm minimum gap between the top course and soffit board, with a cover bead to outside that maintains a minimum 2 mm gap to masonry - refer to Figure 73E(l).</li>
						<li key="9.2.6.e">The cavity shall be vented under openings exceeding 2.4 metres wide through gaps in perpends positioned at 1/3 points along the opening except at opening ends. Where these vent openings are used, protect from water entry using cantilevered sill bricks, as shown in Figure 73C (f).</li>
						<li key="9.2.6.f">The cavity shall be sealed off from the floor and roof space.</li>
					</ol>
					<commentary title="COMMENT:">Variations in cavity width will require compensating adjustments to the length of masonry tie used.</commentary>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="9.2.7" title="Wall ties">
					<p>Masonry veneer shall be attached to wall framing by wall ties. Wall ties and their spacings and embedment shall be in accordance with the requirements of NZS 4210 and Tables 18A, 18B and 18C. Screw fixings shall be minimum 12 gauge, 35 mm long hex washer face, galvanised or stainless steel to suit the ties required under Table 18C.</p>
					<subparagraph key="9.2.7.1">
						<p>Wall ties and screws shall be determined by the durability zone outlined in NZS 3604 and as outlined in Table 18C.</p>
					</subparagraph>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="9.2.8" title="Control joints">
					<subparagraph key="9.2.8.1" title="Clay bricks">
						<p>Control joints in clay brick masonry veneer are not required, unless specified by the brick manufacturer.</p>
					</subparagraph>
					<subparagraph key="9.2.8.2" title="Concrete bricks">
						<p>Longitudinal shrinkage stresses in concrete masonry veneer shall be controlled by providing vertical control joints at not more than 6 m centres. Vertical control joints shall be located:</p>
						<ol>
							<li key="9.2.8.2.a">Within 600 mm of T joints</li>
							<li key="9.2.8.2.b">Within 600 mm of L shaped corners or by restricting the spacing to the next control joint to 3.2 m maximum</li>
							<li key="9.2.8.2.c">At changes in wall height, exceeding 600 mm</li>
							<li key="9.2.8.2.d">At changes in wall thickness.</li>
						</ol>
						<p>Control joints shall be formed as shown in Figure 73A and comprise: a) A backer rod of compressible foam, and b) Sealant in compliance with: i) Type F, Class 20LM or 25LM of ISO 11600, or ii) low modulus Type II Class A of Federal Specification TT-S-00230C.</p>
					</subparagraph>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="9.2.9" title="Openings in masonry veneer">
					<p>Openings with masonry veneer above shall be spanned by steel angle lintels. Openings in masonry veneer for meter boxes less than 500 mm wide may be installed without lintel bars or head flashings provided the meter box is sealed to wall underlay with flashing tape to Paragraph 4.3.11. Separate steel meter boxes from direct contact with masonry veneer or mortar with flashing tape to Paragraph 4.3.11. Lintels shall:</p>
					<ol>
						<li key="9.2.9.a">Be protected against corrosion as in Table 18D and to exposure zones outlined in NZS 3604.</li>
						<li key="9.2.9.b">
							<p>Have a minimum seating into adjacent veneer of:</p>
							<ol>
								<li key="9.2.9.b.i">100 mm for spans up to, and including 2 m,</li>
								<li key="9.2.9.b.ii">200 mm for spans over 2 m.</li>
							</ol>
						</li>
						<li key="9.2.9.c">Be sized in accordance with Table 18E.</li>
					</ol>
					<subparagraph key="9.2.10" title="Windows and doors">
						<p>The openings in wall framing for windows and doors shall have flexible flashing tape applied, in accordance with Paragraph 9.1.5. Air seals shall be provided in accordance with Paragraph 9.1.6. Window flashings shall be installed in accordance with Paragraph 9.2.4 and Figures 73C and 73D(h).</p>
					</subparagraph>
					<subparagraph key="9.2.11" title="Secondary cladding">
						<p>Where a secondary cladding is used with the masonry veneer, and is direct fixed to framing above windows or at gable ends, this shall be fully sealed on:</p>
						<ol>
							<li key="9.2.11.a">The face of the cladding,</li>
							<li key="9.2.11.b">All edges of the cladding, and</li>
							<li key="9.2.11.c">A 75 mm minimum perimeter strip on the rear of the cladding.</li>
						</ol>
					</subparagraph>
				</paragraph>
			</section>
			<section key="9.3" title="Stucco">
				<paragraph key="9.3.1" title="Limitations">
					<p>This Acceptable Solution is limited to the following types of stucco cladding:</p>
					<ol>
						<li key="9.3.1.a">Solid plaster cladding with a non-rigid backing and a drained cavity, and</li>
						<li key="9.3.1.b">Solid plaster cladding with a rigid backing and a drained cavity. Refer to Figure 74</li>
					</ol>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="9.3.2" title="Structure">
					<p>The timber framing of external walls supporting stucco wall claddings shall comply with NZS 3604 and NZS 4251. The cladding system shall be attached to the wall framing.</p>
					<p>The framing for buildings using stucco exterior cladding systems shall be supported on a:</p>
					<ol>
						<li key="9.3.2.a">Concrete slab-on-ground, or</li>
						<li key="9.3.2.b">Continuous reinforced concrete foundation wall, or</li>
						<li key="9.3.2.c">Reinforced concrete masonry foundation wall.</li>
					</ol>
					<figure key="74" keyRef="9.3.1, 9.3.3" title="Types of stucco cladding" type="paragraph"/>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="9.3.3" title="Stucco cladding system">
					<p>All stucco claddings shall be used over a drained cavity as described in Paragraph 9.1.8, and shown in Figure 74.</p>
					<subparagraph key="9.3.3.1">
						<p>All stucco cladding shall have wall underlay as specified in Table 23 and Paragraphs 9.1.5-9.1.7, and shall be:</p>
						<ol>
							<li key="9.3.3.1.a">Fixed to the framing as specified in Table 23, and</li>
							<li key="9.3.3.1.b">Provided as an overlay to rigid backings to provide a slip layer that permits the independent movement of plaster and backing.</li>
						</ol>
					</subparagraph>
					<subparagraph key="9.3.3.2">
						<p>Have plaster backing installed as in Paragraphs 9.3.5 and 9.3.6.</p>
					</subparagraph>
					<subparagraph key="9.3.3.3">
						<p>Have metal lath reinforcements for stucco plaster attached through the plaster backing as described in Table 24.</p>
					</subparagraph>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="9.3.4" title="Installation">
					<subparagraph key="9.3.4.1" title="General">
						<commentary title="COMMENT:">Refer to Paragraph 1.5 for qualification of installers.</commentary>
						<p>Activities that will cause impact or vibration during plaster application are not permitted until all plastering is completed and fully cured. The materials, proportions, mixes, thickness, reinforcement materials and fixing, control joints, and application and curing of plaster shall comply with NZS 4251.</p>
					</subparagraph>
					<subparagraph key="9.3.4.2" title="Movement control joints">
						<p>Movement control joints shall be as required in NZS 4251.</p>
					</subparagraph>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="9.3.5" title="Non-rigid plaster backings">
					<subparagraph key="9.3.5.1" title="Installation of wall underlays">
						<p>The wall underlay shall be in accordance with Table 23, and as described in Paragraphs 9.1.5-9.1.7.</p>
					</subparagraph>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="9.3.6" title="Rigid plaster backings">
					<p>Rigid backings shall be made of either:</p>
					<ol>
						<li key="9.3.6.a">Plywood, or</li>
						<li key="9.3.6.b">Fibre cement sheet, and Have slip layers to Paragraph 9.3.3 b).</li>
					</ol>
					<p>Backing sheets shall be no more than 3 mm out of plane at the time of plastering.</p>
					<subparagraph key="9.3.6.1" title="Plywood backing">
						<p>Plywood shall be:</p>
						<ol>
							<li key="9.3.6.1.a">Selected from Table 6 of NZS 4251,</li>
							<li key="9.3.6.1.b">H3 treated as per AS/NZS 2269, and</li>
							<li key="9.3.6.1.c">
								<p>Fixed as specified in Clause 4.2.4.4.2 of NZS 4251, except that nails shall:</p>
								<ol>
									<li key="9.3.6.1.c.i">be 2.8 mm in diameter, and</li>
									<li key="9.3.6.1.c.ii">penetrate framing by 35 mm minimum.</li>
								</ol>
							</li>
						</ol>
					</subparagraph>
					<subparagraph key="9.3.6.2" title="Fibre cement sheet backing">
						<p>Fibre cement shall:</p>
						<ol>
							<li key="9.3.6.2.a">Comply with AS/NZS 2908: Part 2,</li>
							<li key="9.3.6.2.b">Be a minimum of 4.5 mm thick,</li>
							<li key="9.3.6.2.c">Span no more than 600 mm centres between cavity battens, and</li>
							<li key="9.3.6.2.d">
								<p>Be fixed as specified in Clause 4.2.4.5.2 of NZS 4251, except that nails shall:</p>
								<ol>
									<li key="9.3.6.2.d.i">be 2.8 mm in diameter, and</li>
									<li key="9.3.6.2.d.ii">penetrate framing by 35 mm minimum.</li>
								</ol>
							</li>
						</ol>
						<commentary title="COMMENT:">When the sheathing is used as bracing, the nailing patterns are subject to specific design, and the use of tested and rated systems.</commentary>
					</subparagraph>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="9.3.7" title="Finishes">
					<p>All stucco surfaces shall be sealed by applying a minimum of a 2-coat latex exterior paint system complying with any of Parts 7, 8, 9 or 10 of AS 3730.</p>
					<commentary title="COMMENT:">Stucco cladding systems cannot be assumed to be completely weatherproof. It is necessary to ensure that corrosive salts are not carried into the plaster by moisture, causing corrosion of the reinforcing and fixings.</commentary>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="9.3.8" title="Bottom of stucco">
					<p>The bottom of stucco wall cladding shall be in accordance with Paragraph 9.1.3, and as shown in Figure 75.</p>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="9.3.9" title="Parapets and enclosed balustrades">
					<p>Parapets shall be in accordance with Paragraph 6.0. Enclosed balustrades shall be in accordance with Paragraph 7.4. Parapets and enclosed balustrades for stucco cladding shall be capped with metal, butyl or EPDM membrane, complying with the requirements of Paragraph 4.0.</p>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="9.3.10" title="Windows and doors">
					<p>Windows and doors shall comply with Paragraph 9.1.10, as shown in Figure 76.</p>
					<figure key="75" keyRef="9.3.8" title="Bottom of stucco cladding" type="paragraph"/>
					<figure key="76" keyRef="9.3.10, 72B" title="Windows and doors in stucco cladding" type="paragraph, figure"/>
				</paragraph>
			</section>
			<section key="9.4" title="Timber Weatherboards">
				<p>Timber weatherboard claddings shall be either direct fixed to framing over a wall underlay or fixed over a drained cavity as described in Paragraph 9.1.8.</p>
				<p>Based on the risk score for an external wall calculated as per Paragraph 3.1, the weatherboard cladding may require the inclusion of a drained cavity.</p>
				<paragraph key="9.4.1" title="Limitations">
					<subparagraph key="9.4.1.1" title="Weatherboard profiles">
						<p>This Acceptable Solution is limited to the following types of timber weatherboards:</p>
						<ol>
							<li key="9.4.1.1.a">Horizontal bevel-back,</li>
							<li key="9.4.1.1.b">Horizontal rebated bevel-back,</li>
							<li key="9.4.1.1.c">Horizontal rusticated,</li>
							<li key="9.4.1.1.d">Vertical shiplap, and</li>
							<li key="9.4.1.1.e">Vertical board and batten.</li>
						</ol>
						<p>Profiles shall be as given in NZS 3617 or BRANZ Bulletin 411.</p>
					</subparagraph>
					<subparagraph key="9.4.1.2" title="Vertical weatherboards">
						<p>This Acceptable Solution is limited to the use of direct fixed vertical weatherboards in risk categories as shown in Table 3.</p>
						<commentary title="COMMENT:">Vertical weatherboards are not used over cavities because of the need for horizontal battens, which if solid would interfere with a drained cavity. Vertical weatherboards are therefore limited to low risk applications.</commentary>
					</subparagraph>
					<subparagraph key="9.4.1.3" title="Horizontal weatherboards">
						<p>Horizontal weatherboards shall be either direct fixed or fixed over a drained cavity, according to the risk categories as shown in Table 3.</p>
					</subparagraph>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="9.4.2" title="Materials">
					<p>Timber weatherboard cladding shall include the following features:</p>
					<ol>
						<li key="9.4.2.a">Wall underlay complying with Table 23 and Paragraphs 9.1.5-9.1.7, and</li>
						<li key="9.4.2.b">Timber selection and treatment of weatherboards in accordance with NZS 3602.</li>
					</ol>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="9.4.3" title="Installation">
					<p>A building underlay complying with Table 23 shall be installed behind:</p>
					<ol>
						<li key="9.4.3.a">All direct fixed timber weatherboards, or</li>
						<li key="9.4.3.b">Cavity battens for timber weatherboards installed over a drained cavity.</li>
					</ol>
					<commentary title="COMMENT:">Refer to Paragraph 1.5 for qualification of installers.</commentary>
					<subparagraph key="9.4.3.1" title="Fixings">
						<p>Fixings shall comply with Tables 20 and 24.</p>
						<p>Timber weatherboards shall be drilled for nailing at all joints and ends. All cut ends of painted weatherboards shall be primed.</p>
					</subparagraph>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="9.4.4" title="Horizontal weatherboards">
					<subparagraph key="9.4.4.1" title="Horizontal laps">
						<p>Laps shall be:</p>
						<ol>
							<li key="9.4.4.1.a">32 mm for non-rebated bevel-back boards, or</li>
							<li key="9.4.4.1.b">25 mm horizontal lap for rebated bevel-back and rusticated boards, with a minimum gap of 2 mm at the overlap between boards.</li>
						</ol>
					</subparagraph>
					<subparagraph key="9.4.4.2" title="Joints">
						<p>Joints shall be made only over supports and have:</p>
						<ol>
							<li key="9.4.4.2.a">Corrosion-resistant soakers fitted, complying with Paragraph 4.3.2 to Paragraph 4.3.8, or</li>
							<li key="9.4.4.2.b">Scarf or splay joints.</li>
						</ol>
					</subparagraph>
					<subparagraph key="9.4.4.3" title="Fixings">
						<p>Boards shall be fixed through the wall underlay to the framing in accordance with Table 24.</p>
					</subparagraph>
					<subparagraph key="9.4.4.4" title="External corners">
						<p>External corners shall be weatherproofed by one of the following methods:</p>
						<ol>
							<li key="9.4.4.4.a">
								<p>For rusticated and bevel-back weatherboards, corner boxes with:</p>
								<ol>
									<li key="9.4.4.4.a.i">scribers for bevel-back weatherboards, as shown in Figure 78, or</li>
									<li key="9.4.4.4.a.ii">plugs or scribers for rusticated weatherboards, as shown in Figure 78,</li>
								</ol>
							</li>
							<li key="9.4.4.4.b">
								<p>For bevel-back weatherboards:</p>
								<ol>
									<li key="9.4.4.4.b.i">mitred joints with back flashing as shown in Figure 78, or</li>
									<li key="9.4.4.4.b.ii">mitred joints with corrosion-resistant soakers - refer to Paragraphs 4.3.2 to 4.3.6 and Figure 77.</li>
								</ol>
							</li>
						</ol>
					</subparagraph>
					<subparagraph key="9.4.4.5" title="Internal corners">
						<p>Internal corners shall be made weathertight as shown in Figure 79. A corrosion-resistant flashing shall be fitted behind weatherboards at all internal corners as shown in Figure 79.</p>
					</subparagraph>
					<figure key="77" keyRef="9.4.4.4" title="Corner soakers for bevel-back weatherboards" type="paragraph"/>
					<figure key="78" keyRef="9.4.4.4" title="External corners for horizontal weatherboards" type="paragraph"/>
					<figure key="79" keyRef="9.4.4.5" title="Internal corners for horizontal or vertical weatherboards" type="paragraph"/>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="9.4.5" title="Vertical weatherboards">
					<p>Vertical shiplap and board and batten weather-boards shall be in continuous lengths over a storey height.</p>
					<subparagraph key="9.4.5.1" title="Laps">
						<ol>
							<li key="9.4.5.1.a">Vertical shiplap weatherboards shall be fitted with a minimum gap of 2 mm at the overlap between boards.</li>
							<li key="9.4.5.1.b">
								<p>Board and batten weatherboards shall:</p>
								<ol>
									<li key="9.4.5.1.b.i">be fitted with a 5 mm to 8 mm gap between boards, and</li>
									<li key="9.4.5.1.b.ii">have weather grooves to boards and battens aligned.</li>
								</ol>
							</li>
						</ol>
					</subparagraph>
					<subparagraph key="9.4.5.2" title="Fixings">
						<p>Vertical weatherboards shall be fixed to dwangs at 480 mm maximum centres in accordance with Table 24.</p>
					</subparagraph>
					<subparagraph key="9.4.5.3" title="Corners">
						<ol>
							<li key="9.4.5.3.a">External corners - External corners shall be weatherproofed by the use of corner facings as shown in Figure 80.</li>
							<li key="9.4.5.3.b">Internal corners - A corrosion-resistant corner flashing, as per Table 7 and Figure 79, shall be fitted behind the weatherboards at all internal corners.</li>
						</ol>
					</subparagraph>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="9.4.6" title="Windows and doors in direct fixed weatherboards">
					<p>Window and door details for:</p>
					<ol>
						<li key="9.4.6.a">Direct fixed bevel-back weatherboards are shown in Figure 81,</li>
						<li key="9.4.6.b">Direct fixed rusticated weatherboards are shown in Figure 82,</li>
						<li key="9.4.6.c">Vertical shiplap weatherboards are shown in Figure 83,</li>
						<li key="9.4.6.d">Vertical board and batten weatherboards are shown in Figure 84.</li>
					</ol>
					<p>Door sill details are as shown in Figure 17D.</p>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="9.4.7" title="Windows and doors in cavity walls">
					<p>Window and door details for bevel-back weatherboards on a drained cavity shall be as shown in Figure 85. Window and door details for rusticated weatherboards on a drained cavity are shown in Figure 86. Door sill details are as shown in Figure 17C.</p>
					<commentary title="COMMENT:">The junctions around windows are critical, and it is important that responsibility is taken for the weathertightness of the window as installed within exterior walls. Care should be taken to ensure that this responsibility is clearly defined and assigned. One way is to clearly specify that the window manufacturer shall be responsible for the supply and installation of flashings and frames into openings.</commentary>
					<figure key="80" keyRef="9.4.5.3" title="External corners for vertical weatherboards" type="paragraph"/>
					<figure key="81" keyRef="9.4.6" title="Windows and doors for direct fixed bevel-back weatherboards" type="paragraph"/>
					<figure key="82" keyRef="9.4.6" title="Windows and doors for direct fixed rusticated weatherboards" type="paragraph"/>
					<figure key="83" keyRef="9.4.6" title="Windows and doors for direct fixed vertical shiplap weatherboards" type="paragraph"/>
					<figure key="84" keyRef="9.4.6" title="Windows and doors for direct fixed board and batten weatherboards" type="paragraph"/>
					<figure key="85" keyRef="9.4.7" title="Windows and doors for bevel-back weatherboards on cavity" type="paragraph"/>
					<figure key="86" keyRef="9.4.7" title="Windows and doors for rusticated weatherboards on cavity" type="paragraph"/>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="9.4.8" title="Parapets and enclosed balustrades">
					<p>Parapets shall be in accordance with Paragraph 6.0.</p>
					<p>Enclosed balustrades shall be in accordance with Paragraph 7.4.</p>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="9.4.9" title="Finishes">
					<p>Where a protective finish is required by NZS 3602, all timber surfaces, including end grain and laps, shall be sealed by priming.</p>
					<p>Two coats of exterior grade paint shall be applied, after priming, to all exposed surfaces. Paint systems shall comply with any of Parts 7, 8, 9 or 10 of AS 3730.</p>
					<commentary title="COMMENT:">The minimum durability period for protective coatings is 5 years. Improvement in durability and stability of weatherboards can be achieved by priming all surfaces including backs of boards. Manufacturers of coatings which have a proven performance in use may be able to show compliance with NZBC B2 Durability as detailed in B2/VM1 as an alternative to compliance with AS 3730. With tangentially-sawn weatherboards, particularly painted or stained in dark colours, cupping is possible. Providing additional fixings may help restrain the board, but will usually result in splitting of the boards.</commentary>
				</paragraph>
			</section>
			<section key="9.5" title="Fibre Cement Weatherboards">
				<p>Fibre cement weatherboard claddings shall be either direct fixed to framing over a wall underlay, or fixed over a drained cavity as described in Paragraph 9.1.8.</p>
				<p>Based on the risk score for an external wall, calculated as per Paragraph 3.1, the fibre cement weatherboard cladding may require the inclusion of a drained cavity.</p>
				<paragraph key="9.5.1" title="Limitations">
					<p>This Acceptable Solution is limited to flat fibre cement weatherboards, with a minimum thickness of 7.5 mm.</p>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="9.5.2" title="Material performance">
					<p>Fibre cement weatherboards shall comply with AS/NZS 2908: Part 2.</p>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="9.5.3" title="Installation">
					<p>A wall underlay, as specified in Table 23 and Paragraphs 9.1.5-9.1.7, shall be installed behind fibre cement weatherboard claddings.</p>
					<commentary title="COMMENT:">Refer to Paragraph 1.5 for qualification of installers.</commentary>
					<subparagraph key="9.5.3.1" title="Fixings">
						<p>Fibre cement weatherboards shall be fixed through the wall underlay to the framing at maximum 600 mm centres as per Table 24.</p>
					</subparagraph>
					<subparagraph key="9.5.3.2" title="Laps and joints">
						<p>Horizontal laps shall be a minimum of 30 mm. Joints shall be:</p>
						<ol>
							<li key="9.5.3.2.a">Positioned between studs,</li>
							<li key="9.5.3.2.b">Staggered at a minimum of 600 mm from joints in the adjacent boards, and</li>
							<li key="9.5.3.2.c">
								<p>Weatherproofed by:</p>
								<ol>
									<li key="9.5.3.2.c.i">uPVC H jointers as shown in Figure 87, or</li>
									<li key="9.5.3.2.c.ii">
										<p>hidden soakers as shown in Figure 87, with sealant used between ends of boards complying with:</p>
										<ol>
											<li key="9.5.3.2.c.ii.a">Type F, Class 20LM or 25LM of  ISO 11600, or</li>
											<li key="9.5.3.2.c.ii.b">low modulus Type II Class A of  Federal Specification TT-S-00230C.</li>
										</ol>
									</li>
								</ol>
							</li>
						</ol>
					</subparagraph>
					<figure key="87" keyRef="9.5.3.2" title="Joints in fibre cement weatherboards" type="paragraph"/>
					<subparagraph key="9.5.3.3" title="External corners">
						<p>External corners shall be weatherproofed as shown in Figure 88 by:</p>
						<ol>
							<li key="9.5.3.3.a">The use of corrosion-resistant soakers complying with Paragraph 4.2.2 to Paragraph 4.3.6, or</li>
							<li key="9.5.3.3.b">Facings with weathergrooves.</li>
						</ol>
					</subparagraph>
					<subparagraph key="9.5.3.4" title="Internal corners">
						<p>Internal corners shall be weatherproofed by metal corner flashings as shown in Figure 89.</p>
					</subparagraph>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="9.5.4" title="Windows and doors">
					<p>Windows and doors shall be installed in accordance with Paragraph 9.1.10.</p>
					<subparagraph key="9.5.4.1" title="Windows and doors - direct fixed">
						<p>For direct fixed fibre cement weatherboards, windows and doors shall be detailed as shown in Figure 90 and Figure 17D.</p>
					</subparagraph>
					<subparagraph key="9.5.4.2" title="Windows - on cavity">
						<p>For fibre cement weatherboards fixed over a drained cavity, windows and doors shall be detailed as shown in Figure 91 and Figure 17C.</p>
					</subparagraph>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="9.5.5" title="Parapets and enclosed balustrades">
					<p>Parapets shall be in accordance with Paragraph 6.0. Enclosed balustrades shall be in accordance with Paragraph 7.4.</p>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="9.5.6" title="Protective coating">
					<p>The exposed faces, including top edges at sills and all bottom edges, of horizontal fibre cement weatherboards shall be finished with a minimum of a 2-coat latex exterior paint system complying with any of Parts 7, 8, 9 or 10 of AS 3730.</p>
				</paragraph>
				<figure key="88" keyRef="9.5.3.3" title="External corners in fibre cement weatherboards" type="paragraph"/>
				<figure key="89" keyRef="9.5.3.4" title="Aluminium corners in fibre cement weatherboards" type="paragraph"/>
				<figure key="90" keyRef="9.5.4.1" title="Windows and doors in fibre cement direct fixed weatherboards" type="paragraph"/>
				<figure key="91" keyRef="9.5.4.2" title="Windows and doors in fibre cement weatherboards on cavity" type="paragraph"/>
			</section>
			<section key="9.6" title="Profiled Metal Wall Cladding">
				<p>Horizontal profiled metal wall cladding shall be fixed over a drained cavity as described in Paragraph 9.1.8.</p>
				<p>Vertical profiled metal wall cladding shall be direct fixed to framing over a roof underlay.</p>
				<p>Refer to Table 3: Suitable wall claddings.</p>
				<paragraph key="9.6.1" title="Limitations">
					<p>This Acceptable Solution is limited to corrugated or trapezoidal metal wall cladding with the profiles, as shown in Figure 38, and applied as outlined in Table 3.</p>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="9.6.2" title="General">
					<commentary title="COMMENT:">Refer to Paragraph 1.5 for qualification of installers.</commentary>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="9.6.3" title="Materials">
					<subparagraph key="9.6.3.1" title="Choice of metal">
						<p>The metal cladding shall be selected according to the exposure conditions in Table 20 as defined in:</p>
						<ol>
							<li key="9.6.3.1.a">NZS 3604, or</li>
							<li key="9.6.3.1.b">AS/NZS 2728.</li>
						</ol>
						<commentary title="COMMENT:">The exposure zone in which a building is located can affect the durability of flashings. Exposure zones are defined in NZS 3604, based on the likely exposure to wind-driven sea-salt. Corrosion due to geothermal or corrosive industrial atmospheres, as defined in NZS 3604, requires specific design. Exposure zones are based on AS/NZS 2728. AS/NZS 2728 lists atmospheric classes derived from ISO 9223 for Australia and New Zealand.</commentary>
					</subparagraph>
					<subparagraph key="9.6.3.2" title="Steel">
						<p>Materials for the manufacture of profiled steel cladding shall:</p>
						<ol>
							<li key="9.6.3.2.a">Have a BMT of 0.4 mm minimum,</li>
							<li key="9.6.3.2.b">Be grade G550, or G300 for curved and crimped cladding</li>
							<li key="9.6.3.2.c">Be selected for corrosion protection according to the intended exposure zone as shown in Table 20.</li>
						</ol>
					</subparagraph>
					<subparagraph key="9.6.3.3" title="Aluminium">
						<p>Aluminium for the manufacture of profiled aluminium wall cladding shall comply with AS/NZS 1734, and be:</p>
						<ol>
							<li key="9.6.3.3.a">A base metal thickness (BMT) of a minimum of 0.7 mm,</li>
							<li key="9.6.3.3.b">Minimum 5000 series.</li>
						</ol>
					</subparagraph>
					<p>For pre-painted aluminium, a factory-applied finish complying with AS/NZS 2728 shall be applied.</p>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="9.6.4" title="Maintenance">
					<p>Refer to Paragraph 2.5.</p>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="9.6.5" title="Profiles">
					<p>Profiles covered in this Acceptable Solution are:</p>
					<ol>
						<li key="9.6.5.a">Corrugated - curved with a minimum crest height of 16.5 mm minimum, and</li>
						<li key="9.6.5.b">Trapezoidal - symmetrical and asymmetrical with a minimum crest height of 19 mm.</li>
					</ol>
					<p>For details of these profiles, refer to Figure 38.</p>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="9.6.6" title="Fixing">
					<p>The cladding shall be screw-fixed through the troughs and battens, where applicable, into the framing. Fixings shall:</p>
					<ol>
						<li key="9.6.6.a">Be minimum 12-gauge hexagonal head, self-drilling wood screws,</li>
						<li key="9.6.6.b">Penetrate the framing by a minimum of 30 mm,</li>
						<li key="9.6.6.c">Be minimum Class 4 to AS 3566: Part 2, selected from Table 20,</li>
						<li key="9.6.6.e">Include neoprene (having a carbon black content of 15% or less by weight) or EPDM sealing washers as shown in Figure 39, and</li>
						<li key="9.6.6.f">
							<p>Be used on the cladding at side laps and every second trough or, for trapezoidal where the rib centres exceed 150 mm, at side laps and every trough:</p>
							<ol>
								<li key="9.6.6.f.i">to framing, and</li>
								<li key="9.6.6.f.ii">at all external and internal corners.</li>
							</ol>
						</li>
					</ol>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="9.6.7" title="Flashings">
					<p>Flashings used with metal wall cladding shall be in accordance with Paragraph 4.0, and with the following requirements:</p>
					<ol>
						<li key="9.6.7.a">Hooks and hems shall be as shown in Figure 5,</li>
						<li key="9.6.7.b">Have joints formed with laps and sealant as shown in Figure 6,</li>
						<li key="9.6.7.c">
							<p>Where shown, sealant shall be neutral cure, complying with:</p>
							<ol>
								<li key="9.6.7.c.i">Type F, Class 20LM or 25LM of  ISO 11600, or</li>
								<li key="9.6.7.c.ii">low modulus Type II Class A of Federal Specification TT-S-00230C,</li>
							</ol>
						</li>
						<li key="9.6.7.d">Under-flashings shall be fixed to framing at 600 mm maximum centres.</li>
						<li key="9.6.7.e">
							<p>Flashings shall be fixed together at junctions at 50 mm maximum centres or to cladding at 900 mm centres with:</p>
							<ol>
								<li key="9.6.7.e.i">for galvanized steel, 4 mm diameter monel metal or stainless steel rivets, where compatible as per Table 21, or</li>
								<li key="9.6.7.e.ii">for aluminium-zinc coated steel, 4 mm diameter aluminium rivets, or</li>
								<li key="9.6.7.e.iii">for aluminium, 4 mm diameter aluminium rivets.</li>
							</ol>
						</li>
					</ol>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="9.6.8" title="Vertical profile - direct fixed">
					<subparagraph key="9.6.8.1" title="Installation">
						<p>For direct fixed vertical profile, the wall underlay shall be in accordance with the properties listed for roof underlay in Table 23.</p>
						<p>For copper-based treated framing or underlay refer to Paragraph 9.6.9.2.</p>
						<commentary title="COMMENT:">In direct fixed metal cladding, the wall underlay will be in contact with the back of the vertical profiled metal cladding. Underlay is needed to separate treated timber from the back of the metal to minimise the risk of electrolytic corrosion.</commentary>
					</subparagraph>
					<subparagraph key="9.6.8.2" title="Barges">
						<p>Barge flashings shall be as shown in Figure 92.</p>
						<figure key="92" keyRef="9.6.8.2" title="Barge for vertical profiled metal" type="paragraph"/>
					</subparagraph>
					<subparagraph key="9.6.8.3" title="Bottom of cladding">
						<p>The bottom edge of the cladding shall overlap the foundation wall as described in Paragraph 9.1.3 and as shown in Figure 93.</p>
						<figure key="93" keyRef="9.6.8.3" title="Bottom of cladding for vertical profiled metal" type="paragraph"/>
					</subparagraph>
					<subparagraph key="9.6.8.4" title="Corners">
						<p>Direct fixed vertical profiled metal wall cladding shall be over-flashed at external and internal corners as shown in Figure 94. The cover of the flashings shall:</p>
						<ol>
							<li key="9.6.8.4.a">Be dimensioned to suit the metal wall cladding profile,</li>
							<li key="9.6.8.4.b">Cover at least two crests for corrugated and single crests for other profiles, and</li>
							<li key="9.6.8.4.c">Terminate as shown in Figure 93</li>
						</ol>
					</subparagraph>
					<figure key="94" keyRef="9.6.8.4" title="Corners for vertical profiled metal" type="paragraph"/>
					<subparagraph key="9.6.8.5" title="Vertical profile: penetrations">
						<p>Pipe penetrations shall be as per Figure 53. The heads of larger penetrations shall be flashed in similar fashion to Figure 69, with head flashings adjusted to suit the profile and other flashings as per window and door details in relevant paragraphs.</p>
					</subparagraph>
					<subparagraph key="9.6.8.6" title="Vertical profile: windows and doors">
						<p>Windows and doors in vertical profiled metal claddings shall be flashed as shown in Figure 95 and Figure 100.</p>
					</subparagraph>
					<figure key="95" keyRef="9.6.8.6" title="Windows and doors for vertical profiled metal" type="paragraph"/>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="9.6.9" title="Horizontal profiled metal on cavity">
					<subparagraph key="9.6.9.1" title="Installation">
						<p>A wall underlay, as specified in Table 23 and Paragraphs 9.1.5-9.1.7, shall be installed over the outside face of the framing.</p>
					</subparagraph>
					<subparagraph key="9.6.9.2" title="Cavity battens">
						<p>If the cavity batten contains copper (e.g. CCA, copper azole or ACQ), appropriate separation between the back of the cladding and the cavity batten shall be provided.</p>
						<p>Examples of suitable separation are:</p>
						<ol>
							<li key="9.6.9.2.a">An additional layer of paper-based underlay, complying with Table 23, over cavity battens,</li>
							<li key="9.6.9.2.b">Strips of paper-based underlay complying with Table 23 on the face of cavity battens,</li>
							<li key="9.6.9.2.c">Pre-priming cavity battens.</li>
						</ol>
					</subparagraph>
					<figure key="96" keyRef="9.6.9.3" title="Corner flashings for horizontal profiled metal" type="paragraph"/>
					<subparagraph key="9.6.9.3" title="Corners">
						<p>Corners shall be weatherproofed by using the flashings and details shown in Figure 96. Horizontal profiled metal wall cladding shall be under-flashed using butt flashings which shall:</p>
						<ol>
							<li key="9.6.9.3.a">Be formed in one shaped piece,</li>
							<li key="9.6.9.3.b">Allow metal cladding to butt, with a separation of 5 mm, against sides of the exposed flashing corner, and</li>
							<li key="9.6.9.3.c">Use profiled compressible foam to seal between the flashing underlap and underside of cladding.</li>
						</ol>
					</subparagraph>
					<subparagraph key="9.6.9.4" title="Barges">
						<p>Barge flashings shall be as shown in Figure 97.</p>
						<figure key="97" keyRef="9.6.9.4" title="Barge for horizontal profiled metal" type="paragraph"/>
					</subparagraph>
					<subparagraph key="9.6.9.5" title="Bottom of cladding">
						<p>The bottom edge of the cladding shall overlap the foundation wall as described in Paragraph 9.1.3 and as shown in Figure 98.</p>
						<figure key="98" keyRef="9.6.9.5" title="Bottom of cladding" type="paragraph"/>
					</subparagraph>
					<subparagraph key="9.6.9.6" title="Horizontal profile: penetrations">
						<p>All services penetrations through claddings shall be flashed and sealed. Pipe penetrations are shown in Figure 53.</p>
						<p>The heads of larger penetrations shall be flashed in a similar fashion to Figure 69.</p>
					</subparagraph>
					<subparagraph key="9.6.9.7" title="Horizontal profile: windows and doors">
						<p>Windows and doors shall be installed in accordance with Paragraph 9.1.10, and as shown in Figure 99 and Figure 100.</p>
					</subparagraph>
					<subparagraph key="9.6.9.8" title="Parapets and balustrades">
						<p>Refer to Figures 101 and 102 for horizontal and vertical profiled metal. Parapets shall be in accordance with Paragraph 6.0. Enclosed balustrades shall comply with Paragraph 7.4.</p>
						<commentary title="COMMENT:">Side fixings of handrails or other attachments to enclosed balustrades or parapets will require specific design to demonstrate weathertightness, together with specific structural design for stanchion fixings.</commentary>
					</subparagraph>
					<figure key="99" keyRef="9.6.9.7" title="Windows and doors for horizontal profiled metal on cavity" type="paragraph"/>
					<figure key="100" keyRef="9.6.8.6, 9.6.9.7, 95, 99" title="Window and door flashings for profiled metal" type="paragraph, paragraph, figure, figure"/>
					<figure key="101" keyRef="9.6.9.8" title="Balustrade and parapet for vertical profiled metal" type="paragraph"/>
					<figure key="102" keyRef="9.6.9.8" title="Balustrade and parapet for horizontal profiled metal" type="paragraph"/>
				</paragraph>
			</section>
			<section key="9.7" title="Fibre Cement Sheet">
				<p>Fibre cement sheet claddings shall be either direct fixed to framing over a wall underlay or fixed over a drained cavity based on the risk score for an external wall, calculated as per Paragraph 3.1 and Table 3.</p>
				<paragraph key="9.7.1" title="Limitations">
					<p>This Acceptable Solution is limited to the following types of fibre cement sheet cladding systems:</p>
					<ol>
						<li key="9.7.1.a">
							<p>Flush-finished systems over a drained cavity using sheets of 7.5 mm minimum thickness, with</p>
							<ol>
								<li key="9.7.1.a.i">fibre cement sheets manufactured with a rebated edge for this purpose,</li>
								<li key="9.7.1.a.ii">if necessary for part sheets, rebated on site using a purpose-made tool, and</li>
								<li key="9.7.1.a.iii">have all edges sealed,</li>
								<li key="9.7.1.a.iv">joints, comprising a bedding compound and reinforcing tape, that are finished in accordance with Paragraph 9.7.10.4, or</li>
							</ol>
						</li>
						<li key="9.7.1.b">
							<p>Jointed systems in accordance with Paragraph 9.7.3 using sheets of 6 mm minimum thickness with:</p>
							<ol>
								<li key="9.7.1.b.i">purpose-made jointers,</li>
								<li key="9.7.1.b.ii">timber battens over joints.</li>
							</ol>
						</li>
					</ol>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="9.7.2" title="Material and installation - both systems">
					<p>Fibre cement shall comply with AS/NZS 2908: Part 2.</p>
					<subparagraph key="9.7.2.1" title="Installation">
						<p>Install sheets with:</p>
						<ol>
							<li key="9.7.2.1.a">Paint seals to all sheet edges and cut edges, including 100 mm across back face from each edge</li>
							<li key="9.7.2.1.b">A wall underlay, as specified in Table 23 and Paragraphs 9.1.5-9.1.7, installed behind fibre cement sheet claddings</li>
							<li key="9.7.2.1.c">Fixings as required in Table 24, installed through the wall underlay into the wall framing</li>
							<li key="9.7.2.1.d">All sheet joints located over solid framing.</li>
						</ol>
					</subparagraph>
					<commentary title="COMMENT:">Refer to Paragraph 1.5 for qualification of installers. Edge sealing can be improved by application of a second seal coating. It is recommended that the applicator of the flush-finished jointing and coating be trained and approved by the supplier of the jointing and finish system.</commentary>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="9.7.3" title="Jointed systems">
					<p>Jointed systems shall have:</p>
					<ol>
						<li key="9.7.3.a">
							<p>Vertical joints with either:</p>
							<ol>
								<li key="9.7.3.a.i">uPVC jointers - Figure 104A</li>
								<li key="9.7.3.a.ii">timber battens - Figure 105A.</li>
							</ol>
						</li>
						<li key="9.7.3.b">
							<p>Internal corners:</p>
							<ol>
								<li key="9.7.3.b.i">uPVC jointers - Figure 104B</li>
								<li key="9.7.3.b.ii">timber battens - Figure 104B.</li>
							</ol>
						</li>
						<li key="9.7.3.c">
							<p>External corners</p>
							<ol>
								<li key="9.7.3.c.i">timber battens - Figure 105.</li>
							</ol>
						</li>
						<li key="9.7.3.d">
							<p>Horizontal joints with either:</p>
							<ol>
								<li key="9.7.3.d.i">'Z' flashings, to Figure 107 for Direct fixed claddings</li>
								<li key="9.7.3.d.ii">'Z' flashings to Figure 108 for cavity fixed systems</li>
							</ol>
						</li>
					</ol>
					<p>Flashings shall be either, uPVC, aluminium, stainless steel, or copper to Paragraph 4.3. Timber battens shall comply with NZS 3602.</p>
					<figure key="104A" keyRef="9.7.3" title="Vertical uPVC joints for fibre cement sheet" type="paragraph"/>
					<figure key="104B" keyRef="9.7.3" title="Internal corners for fibre cement sheet" type="paragraph"/>
					<figure key="105" keyRef="9.7.3" title="Vertical timber batten joints for fibre cement sheet" type="paragraph"/>
					<figure key="106" keyRef="9.7.3" title="Horizontal joints for direct fixed fibre cement" type="paragraph"/>
					<figure key="107" keyRef="9.7.3" title="Horizontal joints for fibre cement sheet on cavity" type="paragraph"/>
					<subparagraph key="9.7.3.1" title="Paint finish">
						<p>For jointed systems, all sheet edges shall be sealed prior to fixing. Fibre cement shall be finished with a latex exterior paint system complying with any of Parts 7, 8, 9 or 10 of AS 3730.</p>
					</subparagraph>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="9.7.4" title="Flush-finished systems">
					<p>Flush-finished systems shall be constructed over a drained cavity outlined in Paragraph 9.1.8.</p>
					<ol>
						<li key="9.7.4.a">
							<p>Flush-finished joints shall be finished with a textured finish system that:</p>
							<ol>
								<li key="9.7.4.a.i">complies with BRANZ EM 4, when tested with the specific fibre cement substrate and jointing system used for the cladding</li>
								<li key="9.7.4.a.ii">has all components approved by the supplier of the jointing and finish system</li>
								<li key="9.7.4.a.iii">where a topcoat of paint over the finish is required to provide weather protection, is a latex exterior paint system complying with any of Parts 7, 8, 9 or 10 of AS 3730.</li>
							</ol>
						</li>
						<li key="9.7.4.b">
							<p>Joints shall be positioned so that they:</p>
							<ol>
								<li key="9.7.4.b.i">do not occur at corners of window or door openings or at changes in the height of a wall</li>
								<li key="9.7.4.b.ii">are a minimum of 200 mm on either side of the jamb-line of an opening</li>
								<li key="9.7.4.b.iii">detailed as shown in Figure 110.</li>
							</ol>
						</li>
						<li key="9.7.4.c">External corners shall use uPVC corner reinforcement beneath tape and finishing compound as shown in Figure 113.</li>
						<li key="9.7.4.d">Internal corners shall use a sealant-filled joint over compressible foam tape as shown in Figure 111 b) with polyethylene bond breaker tape behind joint.</li>
					</ol>
					<p>Figure 109 deleted</p>
					<subparagraph key="9.7.4.1" title="Control joints">
						<p>Vertical control joints shall be located as shown in Table 19, and:</p>
						<ol>
							<li key="9.7.4.1.a">May occur at the edge of window or door openings,</li>
							<li key="9.7.4.1.b">Shall extend the full height of the wall, including where there is a horizontal joint and a vertical control joint on the wall - refer to Figure 111, and</li>
							<li key="9.7.4.1.c">May be staggered across horizontal control joints.</li>
						</ol>
					</subparagraph>
					<subparagraph key="9.7.4.2" title="Finishes">
						<p>Finish colour shall have a reflectance of 40% or more, as outlined in Paragraph 2.4.</p>
					</subparagraph>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="9.7.5" title="Soffit details">
					<p>Soffits shall be detailed as shown in Figure 114 for flush-finished and Figure 8A for jointed.</p>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="9.7.6" title="Windows and doors">
					<p>Windows and doors shall be installed in accordance with Paragraph 9.1.10 and:</p>
					<ol>
						<li key="9.7.6.a">Direct fixed windows and doors shall be detailed as per Figure 115</li>
						<li key="9.7.6.b">Windows and doors on cavity shall be detailed as per Figure 116.</li>
					</ol>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="9.7.7" title="Parapets and enclosed balustrades">
					<p>Parapets shall comply with Paragraph 6.0.</p>
					<p>Enclosed balustrades shall comply with Paragraph 7.4. Balustrade cappings may include:</p>
					<ol>
						<li key="9.7.7.a">Metal, butyl or EPDM to Paragraph 6.3, or,</li>
						<li key="9.7.7.b">Flush-finished fibre cement to Paragraph</li>
					</ol>
					<figure key="110" keyRef="9.7.4" title="Flush-finished joints for fibre cement sheet" type="paragraph"/>
					<figure key="111" keyRef="9.7.4.1" title="Vertical movement control joint for flush-finished fibre cement sheet" type="paragraph"/>
					<p>Figure 112 deleted</p>
					<figure key="113" keyRef="9.7.4" title="Flush-finished external corners for fibre cement sheet" type="paragraph"/>
					<figure key="114" keyRef="9.7.5" title="Soffit for flush-finished fibre cement sheet" type="paragraph"/>
					<figure key="115" keyRef="9.7.6" title="Windows and doors for direct fixed fibre cement sheet" type="paragraph"/>
					<figure key="116" keyRef="9.7.6" title="Windows and doors for fibre cement sheet and flush-finished fibre cement on cavity" type="paragraph"/>
					<subparagraph key="9.7.7.1" title="Flush-finished topped balustrades">
						<p>Where the tops to enclosed balustrades are formed using flush-finished fibre cement, they shall have a minimum fall of 10° (1:6), and be wrapped as shown in Figure 117, with a waterproofing membrane, approved by the supplier of the jointing and finish system. The membrane shall be fully protected by the coating and shall comply with the requirements of AS/NZS 4858 Table 8, Parts (a) to (e), except that bleach and detergent immersion set out in Appendix A1 shall not be required.</p>
						<figure key="1" keyRef="6.6, 9.7.7.1" title="Enclosed balustrade to wall for fibre cement sheet" type="paragraph"/>
						<p>Figure 118 deleted</p>
					</subparagraph>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="9.7.8" title="Decorative attachments">
					<p>Where decorative attachments are used, seal sheets prior to attachment of the decorative elements. The final weatherproofing system shall be applied over decorative elements and wall cladding. Horizontal decorative elements shall have top surfaces sloped to a minimum of 10¼ and drip mouldings to bottom edges. Attachments shall not interfere with the functioning of critical joints such as control joints.</p>
					<commentary title="COMMENT:">Alternatively, a decorative moulding may be formed from the coating by using mesh and plaster.</commentary>
				</paragraph>
			</section>
			<section key="9.8" title="Plywood Sheet">
				<p>Plywood-sheet claddings shall be either direct fixed to framing over a wall underlay or fixed over a drained cavity as per Paragraph 9.1.8.</p>
				<p>Based on the risk score for an external wall, calculated as per Paragraph 3.1, the sheet cladding may require the inclusion of a drained cavity.</p>
				<paragraph key="9.8.1" title="Limitations">
					<p>This Acceptable Solution covers plywood panel claddings with vertical battened joints and flashed horizontal joints.</p>
					<p>Figure 118 deleted</p>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="9.8.2" title="Materials">
					<p>Batten-jointed panels shall have weather-grooved timber battens as shown in Figure 119. Plywood panels shall be:</p>
					<ol>
						<li key="9.8.2.a">Manufactured to AS/NZS 2269, grade CD,</li>
						<li key="9.8.2.b">A minimum of 5 ply,</li>
						<li key="9.8.2.c">A minimum of 12 mm in thickness, and</li>
						<li key="9.8.2.d">Treated as required by NZS 3602.</li>
					</ol>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="9.8.3" title="Installation">
					<p>A wall underlay, as specified in Table 23, shall be installed behind plywood sheet claddings.</p>
					<commentary title="COMMENT:">Refer to Paragraph 1.5 for qualification of installers.</commentary>
					<subparagraph key="9.8.3.1" title="Fixings">
						<p>Plywood sheets shall be fixed through the wall underlay into the wall framing with fixings as required in Table 24.</p>
					</subparagraph>
					<subparagraph key="9.8.3.2" title="Joints">
						<p>All joints shall:</p>
						<ol>
							<li key="9.8.3.2.a">Be made only over supports, and</li>
							<li key="9.8.3.2.b">If horizontal, incorporate a 10 mm expansion gap, and be fitted with a flashing, as shown in Figure 121, or</li>
							<li key="9.8.3.2.c">If vertical, have battened joints - refer to Figure 119.</li>
						</ol>
						<figure key="119" keyRef="9.8.2, 9.8.3.2" title="Battened joints for plywood sheet" type="paragraph"/>
						<p>Figure 120 deleted</p>
						<figure key="121" keyRef="9.8.3.2" title="Horizontal joints for plywood sheet" type="paragraph"/>
					</subparagraph>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="9.8.4" title="Corners">
					<subparagraph key="9.8.4.1" title="External corners">
						<p>External corners shall be fitted with flashings or timber battens, as shown in Figure 122.</p>
					</subparagraph>
					<subparagraph key="9.8.4.2" title="Internal corners">
						<p>Internal corners shall be as shown in Figure 123 and have:</p>
						<ol>
							<li key="9.8.4.2.a">Flashings and timber battens for direct fix</li>
							<li key="9.8.4.2.b">Timber battens for cavity fix.</li>
						</ol>
					</subparagraph>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="9.8.5" title="Flashing material">
					<p>Flashings shall be metal selected in accordance with Table 20 to Table 22 and Paragraph 4.3.</p>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="9.8.6" title="Soffit details">
					<p>Soffits shall be as shown in Figure 8A and Paragraph 5.3.</p>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="9.8.7" title="Parapets and enclosed balustrades">
					<p>Parapets and enclosed balustrades shall be capped with metal, butyl or EPDM membrane. Cappings shall comply with the requirements of Paragraph 4.0.</p>
					<ol>
						<li key="9.8.7.a">Parapets shall be in accordance with Paragraph 6.0</li>
						<li key="9.8.7.b">Enclosed balustrades shall be in accordance with Paragraph 7.4.</li>
					</ol>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="9.8.8" title="Windows and doors">
					<p>Windows and doors shall be installed in accordance with Paragraph 9.1.10.</p>
					<subparagraph key="9.8.8.1" title="Windows and doors: direct fixed">
						<p>Windows and doors shall be detailed as shown for fibre cement sheet cladding - refer to Figure 115.</p>
					</subparagraph>
					<subparagraph key="9.8.8.2" title="Windows and doors: with cavity">
						<p>Windows and doors shall be detailed as shown for fibre cement sheet cladding - refer to Figure 116.</p>
						<commentary title="COMMENT:">The same principles of window installation apply to both fibre cement and plywood sheet cladding.</commentary>
					</subparagraph>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="9.8.9" title="Finishes">
					<p>A solution of 12.5% copper naphthenate in white spirits, or mineral turpentine, shall be brushed on to any edges cut after treatment.</p>
					<p>Direct fixed plywood cladding used as bracing requires a minimum 50-year durability, and shall be treated to H3, painted on all edges and the outer face with a latex exterior paint system complying with any of Parts 7, 8, 9 or 10 of AS 3730.</p>
					<commentary title="COMMENT:">Plywood for cladding, treated to H3, does not require painting. While H3 plywood can be left unpainted, it is likely to develop checking and mould growth on the surface. Plywood used as bracing requires painting and regular maintenance of the paint finish to ensure the 50-year durability is achieved.</commentary>
					<figure key="122" keyRef="9.8.4.1" title="External corners for plywood sheet" type="paragraph"/>
					<figure key="123" keyRef="9.8.4.2" title="Internal corners for plywood sheet" type="paragraph"/>
				</paragraph>
			</section>
			<section key="9.9" title="EIFS">
				<p>This paragraph covers polymer-modified cement-based plaster or polymer-based polystyrene-based plaster Exterior Insulation and Finish Systems (EIFS).</p>
				<p>EIFS cladding shall be fixed over a drained cavity as described in Paragraph 9.1.8.</p>
				<paragraph key="9.9.1" title="Limitations">
					<p>This Acceptable Solution is limited to EIFS cladding systems that are:</p>
					<ol>
						<li key="9.9.1.a">Designed and tested as a total system, and</li>
						<li key="9.9.1.b">
							<p>Not fixed:</p>
							<ol>
								<li key="9.9.1.b.i">so as to form a horizontal surface,</li>
								<li key="9.9.1.b.ii">as a replacement for roofing, or</li>
								<li key="9.9.1.b.iii">in such a way as to allow water to pond.</li>
							</ol>
						</li>
					</ol>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="9.9.2" title="General">
					<commentary title="COMMENT:">Refer to Paragraph 1.5 for qualification of installers.</commentary>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="9.9.3" title="Materials">
					<p>EIFS cladding systems shall comprise the following parts:</p>
					<ol>
						<li key="9.9.3.a">A polystyrene sheet cladding material,</li>
						<li key="9.9.3.b">A polymer-modified cement-based plaster or a polymer-based plaster, reinforced with fibreglass mesh,</li>
						<li key="9.9.3.c">A polymer-modified cement or polymer-based finishing plaster, and a latex exterior paint system complying with any of Parts 7, 8, 9 or 10 of AS 3730,</li>
						<li key="9.9.3.d">A range of head, sill, jamb, corner and base mouldings suitable for exterior use, and</li>
						<li key="9.9.3.e">
							<p>A flexible polymeric neutral cure sealant that:</p>
							<ol>
								<li key="9.9.3.e.i">is approved by the cladding system supplier, and</li>
								<li key="9.9.3.e.ii">
									<p>complies with:</p>
									<li key="9.9.3.e.ii.a">Type F, Class 20LM or 25LM of ISO 11600, or</li>
									<li key="9.9.3.e.ii.b">low modulus Type II Class A of  Federal Specification TT-S-00230C.</li>
								</li>
							</ol>
						</li>
					</ol>
					<commentary title="COMMENT:">This is the minimum standard, and extra elements deemed suitable by the system supplier should not be excluded on the basis of this Acceptable Solution.</commentary>
					<subparagraph key="9.9.3.1" title="Polystyrene sheet">
						<p>Polystyrene sheet shall be a minimum of 40 mm thick and shall be either:</p>
						<ol>
							<li key="9.9.3.1.a">Expanded polystyrene (EPS) complying with AS 1366: Part 3, Class H or Class S, or</li>
							<li key="9.9.3.1.b">Extruded polystyrene (XPS) that complies with AS 1366: Part 4.</li>
						</ol>
					</subparagraph>
					<subparagraph key="9.9.3.2" title="Fibreglass reinforcing mesh">
						<p>Fibreglass reinforcing mesh shall be alkali-resistant fibreglass mesh, and shall:</p>
						<ol>
							<li key="9.9.3.2.a">Weigh no less than 150 grams per m2,</li>
							<li key="9.9.3.2.b">Have an aperture size from 3 mm x 3 mm to 6 mm x 6 mm square, and</li>
							<li key="9.9.3.2.c">Comply with the requirements of EIMA 101.9 test No. 6.3 and ASTM E2098.</li>
						</ol>
					</subparagraph>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="9.9.4" title="Installation">
					<p>A wall underlay, as specified in Table 23 and Paragraphs 9.1.5-9.1.7, shall be fixed to the framing.</p>
					<subparagraph key="9.9.4.1" title="Fixings">
						<p>Polystyrene sheets shall be fixed through the cavity battens, and wall underlay into the wall framing with fixings as required in Table 24.</p>
						<p>Fixings shall:</p>
						<ol>
							<li key="9.9.4.1.a">Be spaced as shown in Table 24,</li>
							<li key="9.9.4.1.b">Penetrate the framing by 30 mm minimum,</li>
							<li key="9.9.4.1.c">Comply with AS/NZS 4680, and</li>
							<li key="9.9.4.1.d">
								<p>Be either:</p>
								<ol>
									<li key="9.9.4.1.d.i">hot-dipped galvanized springhead nails with a 22 mm top, or</li>
									<li key="9.9.4.1.d.ii">hot-dipped galvanized flat head nails used in conjunction with a 22 mm minimum diameter plastic washer. </li>
								</ol>
							</li>
						</ol>
					</subparagraph>
					<subparagraph key="9.9.4.2" title="Joints">
						<p>Joints to plain-edged sheets shall be butt jointed over solid timber backing.</p>
						<p>Rebated or tongued boards may be jointed away from solid timber backing, providing the joint is self-supporting at both edges.</p>
						<p>Corner joints shall be butted together and fully supported along the length of the joint.</p>
					</subparagraph>
					<subparagraph key="9.9.4.3" title="Movement control joints">
						<p>Control joints shall always be located over solid timber backing. Control joints shall be as shown in Figure 124, and shall be provided:</p>
						<ol>
							<li key="9.9.4.3.a">On all walls over 20 metres long or over 7 metres high including gables,</li>
							<commentary title="COMMENT:">The system supplier may require control joints at   closer spacings.</commentary>
							<li key="9.9.4.3.b">At abutments to different cladding types, </li>
							<li key="9.9.4.3.c">Where cladding covers different structural materials such as timber to concrete, and </li>
							<li key="9.9.4.3.d">Over a movement control joint in the underlying framing. </li>
						</ol>
					</subparagraph>
					<subparagraph key="9.9.4.4" title="Fixing blocks">
						<p>H3.2 treated timber blocks shall be provided  at appropriate locations for fixing all downpipe brackets, garden taps, and other outside fittings.</p>
						<p>The blocks shall be cut to suit the polystyrene thickness, and fixed to framing or cavity battens. Prior to applying the plaster basecoat, a patch shall be applied that:</p>
						<ol>
							<li key="9.9.4.4.a">Extends over the timber block face and overlaps the adjacent polystyrene by a minimum of 50 mm, and</li>
							<li key="9.9.4.4.b">
								<p>Is suitable for the direct application of the base coat, and is either:</p>
								<ol>
									<li key="9.9.4.4.b.i">a butyl-based flexibleflashingtape   that complies with Parts 3.2 and 4 of   ICBO Acceptance Criteria AC148, or</li>
									<li key="9.9.4.4.b.ii">a waterproofing membrane that    complies with the requirements of    AS/NZS 4858 Table 8, Parts (a) to (e),   except that bleach and detergent    immersion set out in Appendix A1 shall   not be required.</li>
								</ol>
							</li>
						</ol>
						<p>The design of fixing blocks for connecting items carrying substantial loads such as stringers for decks are outside the scope of this Acceptable Solution. These will require specific design.</p>
						<figure key="124" keyRef="9.8.4.3" title="Control joints for EIFS" type="paragraph"/>
					</subparagraph>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="9.9.5" title="Battens">
					<p>Cavity battens shall comply with Paragraph 9.1.8.4, installed as in Paragraph 9.1.8.</p>
					<commentary title="COMMENT:">Cavity spacers must be short and sloped to prevent water being trapped by the battens and ventilation being restricted.</commentary>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="9.9.6" title="Coating">
					<p>Suppliers of EIFS cladding systems shall demonstrate that their systems meet the tensile-adhesion performance requirements of ASTM E2134.</p>
					<subparagraph key="9.9.6.1" title="Reinforcing">
						<p>The entire surface of the polystyrene sheet (including corners) must be continuously reinforced with alkali-resistant fibreglass reinforcing mesh as specified in Paragraph 9.9.3.2.</p>
					</subparagraph>
					<subparagraph key="9.9.6.2" title="Reinforcing base coat">
						<p>The reinforcing base coat shall have:</p>
						<ol>
							<li key="9.9.6.2.a">
								<p>A base coat plaster at the greater of the system supplier's minimum recommended thickness or 3 mm thick, and be either:</p>
								<ol>
									<li key="9.9.6.2.i">polymer-modified cement-based, or</li>
									<li key="9.9.6.2.ii">polymer-based,</li>
								</ol>
							</li>
							<li key="9.9.6.2.b">Reinforcing with an alkali-resistant fibreglass mesh (Paragraph 9.9.3.2), and</li>
							<li key="9.9.6.2.c">Cover to mesh by at least 1.5 mm plaster.</li>
						</ol>
					</subparagraph>
					<subparagraph key="9.9.6.3" title="Finish coats">
						<p>Finish colour shall have a reflectance of 40% or more, as outlined in Paragraph 2.4.</p>
						<p>The finish shall comprise either:</p>
						<ol>
							<li key="9.9.6.3.a">One or more coats of polymer-modified cement-based plaster or polymer-based plaster, or</li>
							<li key="9.9.6.3.b">One or more coats of a pre-coloured polymer-modified cement-based plaster, or</li>
							<li key="9.9.6.3.c">A pre-coloured polymer-based plaster applied according to the conditions specified by the plaster manufacturer.</li>
						</ol>
						<p>Where necessary to maintain weather-tightness, EIFS shall be finished with a latex exterior paint system complying with any of Parts 7, 8, 9 or 10 of AS 3730.</p>
						<p>Polymer-modified cement-based plaster shall only be applied out of direct sunlight and when the temperature is between 5ûC and 30ûC, with the expectation that the temperature will be in that range for the following 24 hours.</p>
					</subparagraph>
					<subparagraph key="9.9.6.4" title="Decorative mouldings">
						<p>Decorative mouldings shall be formed from polystyrene, and shall be glued or mechanically fastened to ensure they remain securely attached to EIFS cladding or framing.</p>
						<p>Where decorative mouldings are attached, the basecoat shall be applied before the moulding.</p>
						<commentary title="COMMENT:">Alternatively, a decorative moulding may be formed from the coating by using mesh and plaster.</commentary>
					</subparagraph>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="9.9.7" title="EIFS/floor slab junction">
					<p>The bottom of the EIFS cladding shall be as shown in Figure 125.</p>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="9.9.8" title="Pipes and service penetrations">
					<p>All pipes and service penetrations through the EIFS shall be made weatherproof, by either:</p>
					<ol>
						<li key="9.9.8.a">A flange penetrating the EIFS as a sleeve and sealed into the EIFS system as shown in Figure 126, or</li>
						<li key="9.9.8.b">
							<p>A face-fitted flange at EIFS surface, sealed with a neutral cure sealant complying with:</p>
							<ol>
								<li key="9.9.8.b.i">Type F, Class 20LM or 25LM of  ISO 11600, or</li>
								<li key="9.9.8.b.ii">low modulus Type II Class A of Federal Specification TT-S-00230C.</li>
							</ol>
						</li>
						<li key="9.9.8.c">Pipe penetrations shall be installed to slope downwards to exterior. Refer to Figure 68</li>
					</ol>
					<p>Where cables penetrate cladding, a sleeve or conduit shall be provided and sealed into the EIFS system. All wires that pass through a conduit shall be sealed into position inside the conduit.</p>
					<figure key="125" keyRef="9.9.7" title="Bottom of cladding for EIFS" type="paragraph"/>
					<figure key="126" keyRef="9.9.8" title="Penetration for EIFS" type="paragraph"/>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="9.9.9" title="Windows and doors">
					<p>Windows and doors shall be installed in accordance with Paragraph 9.1.10, and shown in Figures 17C, 127 and 128.</p>
					<p>Install uPVC three-way corner flashings at jamb/sill junctions as shown in Figure 127. Corner flashings shall be installed behind EIFS jamb and sill flashings, with flanges turned out over polystyrene backing sheets.</p>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="9.9.10" title="Parapets and enclosed balustrades">
					<p>Parapets shall comply with Paragraph 6.0. Enclosed balustrades shall comply with Paragraph 7.4.</p>
					<subparagraph key="9.9.10.1" title="Flush-finished balustrade top">
						<p>Where the tops to enclosed balustrades are formed using EIFS, they shall have a minimum fall of 10° (1:6), and be wrapped as shown in Figure 129 and 130, with a liquid waterproofing membrane approved by the supplier. The EIFS system shall be fully protected by the coating, and shall comply with the requirements of AS/NZS 4858 Table 8, Parts (a) to (e), except that bleach and detergent immersion set out in Appendix A1 shall not be required.</p>
					</subparagraph>
					<subparagraph key="9.9.10.2" title="Metal cappings">
						<p>Metal cappings shall comply with the requirements of Paragraph 6.4, and shall be as shown in Figure 130.</p>
						<p>Where a parapet or an enclosed balustrade meets EIFS wall cladding, a saddle flashing shall be used, as shown in Figure 12 and Figure 13.</p>
					</subparagraph>
					<figure key="127" keyRef="9.9.9" title="Window and door corner flashing for EIFS" type="paragraph"/>
					<figure key="128" keyRef="9.9.9" title="Windows and doors in EIFS" type="paragraph"/>
					<figure key="129" keyRef="6.6, 9.9.10.1" title="Enclosed balustrade-to-wall junction for EIFS" type="paragraph"/>
					<figure key="130" keyRef="9.9.10.2" title="Parapet with metal capping for EIFS" type="paragraph"/>
				</paragraph>
			</section>
		</part>
		<part key="10" title="Construction Moisture">
			<section key="10.1" title="Moisture in materials">
				<p>Moisture contained in the building structure at completion of construction shall not be permitted to damage the building elements.</p>
				<p>Construction moisture includes the moisture contained in:</p>
				<ol>
					<li key="10.1.a">Timber products as a result of a treatment or manufacturing process,</li>
					<li key="10.1.b">Green timber, and timber or other materials that have been exposed to the weather, and</li>
					<li key="10.1.c">Concrete, mortar or plaster that is not completely cured.</li>
				</ol>
			</section>
			<section key="10.2" title="Maximum acceptable moisture contents">
				<p>The maximum moisture contents shall be:</p>
				<ol>
					<li key="10.2.a">
						<p>For timber framing at the time of installing interior linings, the maximum acceptable moisture content shall be the lesser of:</p>
						<ol>
							<li key="10.2.a.i">20% for insulated buildings, 24% for non-insulated buildings, or</li>
							<li key="10.2.a.ii">as specified in NZS 3602,</li>
						</ol>
					</li>
					<li key="10.2.b">For timber weatherboards and exterior joinery, 20% at the time of painting,</li>
					<li key="10.2.c">For reconstituted wood products, 18% at all times, and</li>
					<li key="10.2.d">For concrete floors, sufficiently dry to give a relative humidity reading of less than 75% at the time of laying fixed floor coverings.</li>
				</ol>
				<commentary title="COMMENT:">Some manufacturers of timber or other wall or floor components may recommend lower moisture contents for their products. It is advisable to use the manufacturer's moisture content requirements, if these are lower than those required by this paragraph.</commentary>
			</section>
			<section key="10.3" title="Measuring moisture content">
				<paragraph key="10.3.1" title="Timber">
					<p>Measurement shall be by the recommended procedure in the Scion (New Zealand Forest Research Institute) publication 'Measurement of moisture content of Wood' using electrical resistance type moisture meters with insulated probes. Representative samplings of measurements shall be taken:</p>
					<ol>
						<li key="10.3.1.a">With meters calibrated to AS/NZS 1080.1 Appendix E</li>
						<li key="10.3.1.b">By inserting probes to at least 1/3 the depth of timber being measured, at a distance exceeding 200 mm from board ends</li>
						<li key="10.3.1.c">Using correction factors for timber species, temperature, and treatment type (outlined in Scion publication above).</li>
					</ol>
					<commentary title="COMMENT:">For convenience of site measurement, readings of moisture content can be compared against a 'control' framing sample of known acceptable moisture content. The comparative readings must be taken during the same test period, be of the same framing type, and using the same resistance moisture meter. This method of moisture testing may be appropriate for non-boron treated framing, or processed timber framing.</commentary>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph key="10.3.2" title="Concrete floors">
					<p>Measurement shall be made in accordance with BRANZ Bulletin 330 Thin Flooring Materials using hygrometers calibrated to ASTM E 104 - 2002 Standard practice for maintaining constant relative humidity by means of aqueous solutions.</p>
				</paragraph>
			</section>
		</part>
	</document>
	<document key="E2/AS2" title="Acceptable Solution E2/AS2">
		<part key="1" title="Earth buildings">
			<p>Earth buildings complying with NZS 4299 as modified by this Acceptable Solution meet the performance criteria of NZBC E2.</p>
			<p>Where buildings are based on NZS 4299 but require specific structural engineering design input, the structure must be of at least equivalent stiffness to the provisions of NZS 4299. Such designs are outside the scope of this Acceptable Solution and proposals must be submitted to, and approved by, the building consent authority as part of the normal building consent process.</p>
			<section key="1.1" title="Modifications to NZS 4299">
				<p>Clause 2.1.8.5 Add new Clause: 2.1.8.5 Install a damp proof course (DPC) to separate timber from concrete, cement stabilised earth and lime stabilised earth. DPC material must be bituminous paint or sheet material as specified in Clause 4.9.1.</p>
				<p>Figure 4.1 Replace Figure 4.1 with:</p>
				<figure key="4.1" title="Footing dimensions and general details"/>
				<p>Clause 5.1.8 Add new Clause: 5.1.8 The external surface of earth walls must be finished in accordance with Clauses 2.2.3.5, 2.2.4.2 and 2.2.4.3 of NZS 4298. The external surface of earth walls must be free from features, such as horizontal protrusions, that could cause water to become trapped or directed towards the inside of the building.</p>
				<commentary title="C5.1.8">Water must be able to flow downwards and off the external surface of earth walls. External earth wall surfaces are not required to have a surface coating to meet this Acceptable Solution. The use of surface coatings does not replace or diminish the need for eaves as required by Clause 2.10.</commentary>
				<p>Clause 5.12 Add new Clause and Figure: 5.12 Soffit to wall junction The junction between the soffit and the earth wall must be constructed as shown in Figure 5.11.</p>
				<figure key="5.11" title="Soffit to wall junction A) Flat soffit"/>
				<figure key="5.11" title="Soffit to wall junction B) Angled soffit"/>
				<p>Clause 5.13 Add new Clause and Figure: 5.13 Timber-framed gable wall The junction between timber-framed gable walls and earth walls must be constructed as shown in Figure 5.12.</p>
				<figure key="5.12" title="Timber-framed gable to earth wall"/>
				<p>Clause 9.2 Add the following new paragraph to end of Clause 9.2: 'Windows and doors with arched or sloping heads are outside the scope of this Standard'.</p>
				<p>Clause C9.2 Add the following new paragraph to end of commentary Clause C9.2:</p>
				<commentary title="COMMENT:">Requirements for window and door joinery are not included in this Acceptable Solution. For more information, designers may refer to: - NZS 3504: 1979 Specification for aluminium windows - NZS 3610: 1979 Specification for profiles of mouldings and joinery - NZS 3619: 1979 Specification for timber windows.</commentary>
				<p>Figure 9.2 Replace Figure 9.2 with:</p>
				<figure key="9.2" title="Head details A) Timber joinery with timber-framed wall insert"/>
				<figure key="9.2" title="Head details B) Aluminium joinery with timber-framed wall insert"/>
				<figure key="9.2" title="Head details C) Timber joinery with timber lintel"/>
				<figure key="9.2" title="Head details D) Aluminium joinery with timber lintel"/>
				<p>Figure 9.3 Replace Figure 9.3 with:</p>
				<figure key="9.3" title="Jumb details A) Timber joinery"/>
				<figure key="9.3" title="Jumb details B) Aluminium joinery"/>
				<p>Figure 9.4 Replace Figure 9.4 with:</p>
				<figure key="9.4" title="Sill details A) Timber joinery with brick or tile sill"/>
				<figure key="9.4" title="Sill details B) Aluminium joinery with brick or tile sill"/>
				<figure key="9.4" title="Sill details C) Timber joinery with concrete sill"/>
				<figure key="9.4" title="Sill details D) Aluminium joinery with concrete sill"/>
				<p>Clause 9.7 Add new Clause: </p>
				<p>9.7 Penetrations</p>
				<p>9.7.1</p>
				<p>The upper surface of elements (e.g. pipes and meterboxes) that penetrate external walls must be sloped downwards to the exterior to direct moisture away from the wall and to discharge it clear of the wall surface.</p>
				<p>COMMENT: C9.7.1 Penetrations should be located where they are sheltered from wind-driven rain - this may be achieved by positioning the penetration in a sheltered location or as high as practical under eaves on the wall.</p>
				<p>9.7.2</p>
				<p>Penetrations less than 200mm wide must meet the requirements of NZS 4298 Clause 2.1.12 and must be sealed all round with a tight-fitting moisture resistant compressible closed cell foam rod or tube that is finished 25 mm behind the wall surface, with the resulting gap filled with:</p>
				<p>i) for unstabilised earth construction, a compatible unstabilised mortar</p>
				<p>ii) for stabilised earth construction, a compatible stabilised mortar.</p>
				<p>COMMENT: C9.7.2 Generally sealants do not adhere well to earthen surfaces with the possible exception of dense stabilised rammed earth or pressed earth brick.</p>
				<p>9.7.3</p>
				<p>Penetrations more than 200mm wide (e.g. meterboxes) must be anchored as required in Clause 9.1 and must meet the following requirements:</p>
				<p>a) Where the depth of the penetration is more than 1/3 of the wall depth, the penetration must incorporate head, jamb and sill details similar to those required for windows.</p>
				<p>b) Where the depth of the penetration is less than 1/3 of the wall depth, the penetration must be sealed all round with a compatible mortar as required by Clause 9.7.2.</p>
			</section>
		</part>
	</document>
	<document key="E2/AS3" title="Acceptable Solution E2/AS3">
		<part key="1" title="Concrete and Concrete Masonry Buildings">
			<p>Concrete and concrete masonry construction with the scope of CCANZ CP 01, and that complies with CCANZ CP 01,will meet the performance criteria of NZBC E2.</p>
		</part>
	</document>
</documents>
</lrml:LegalRuleML>